<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Best practice recommendations for long term archiving of TEI XML
               resources</title>
            <author xml:id="lou">Lou Burnard</author>
            <author>Nicolas Larrousse</author>
            <funder>TGIR Huma-Num</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished draft circulated for comment</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>An original work: no pre-existing source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#lou" when="2013-10-20">Started draft</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="intro">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>This document arises out of a study commissioned by the TGIR Huma Num in
               collaboration with the CINES. <!-- more bumf expanding these acronyms -->
            </p>
            <p>The object of the study was to identify and then to promote best practice amongst the
               community of researchers wishing to deposit textual resources encoded using TEI XML
               with the CINES for long term preservation. Although the CINES already has extensive
               experience and expertise in the long term preservation of resources which conformant
               with generic standards such as XML and PDF, it was recognised that the increasing use
               of TEI-XML in the French research community offered both an opportunity and a
               challenge. On the one hand, as a more expressive and richer formalism than generic
               XML, TEI offered the possibility for the CINES of ensuring the preservation of more
               contextual and semantic data forming part of a resource; on the other hand, the ways
               in which TEI XML is applied in practice varies quite widely amongst different
               researchers, and so simply to say that a document is "TEI-conformant" may leave
               unspecified a great deal of useful contextual information about it. </p>
            <p>Although the community of TEI users is highly divers, its members share an
               understanding of the best way to use the TEI Guidelines, just as those Guidelines
               express a common understanding of how the structure and metadata associated with a
               textual resource should be documented and defined. This community of practice has
               been increasing in size and scope quite significantly over the last few years, and
               notably so in France, where a number of large-scale resource-creation projects have
               already expressed a committment to the use of TEI XML, just as several smaller scale
               individual resource projects have adopted and adapted it to their needs. For the
               purposes of this project we approached initially only a small number of projects,
               selecting those which were known to be engaged in the creation of significant amounts
               of TEI-XML material likely to be of long-term interest in the scholarly research
               community. Examples included the Open Edition project (CLEO), which will publishes
               several hundred scholarly books in a TEI format over the next few years; the CNRTL,
               which has long been responsible for creation and distribution of a wide range of
               TEI-encoded language corpora and is a major French partner in CLARIN;
               <!-- some more examples here? --></p>
            <p>The usefulness of TEI-XML as a format for scholarly analysis and interchange is
               widely accepted. However the question arises as whether TEI-encoded resources are
               also suitable for long term preservation purposes : more specifically, if a project
               wishes to ensure long term preservation of its resources, should it archive them in a
               TEI format, or should it regard the TEI format simply as a means to an end, archiving
               only a processed form of the TEI source as HTML or PDF, for example? For projects
               where the TEI form is considered only as a means to the end of displaying the texts,
               this may well be adequate. But since TEI to HTML or TEI to PDF are lossy
               transformations, in which the added value constituted by TEI structural annotation is
               systematically removed this seems in general a less than optimal solution. We would
               like to be able to preserve our digital resources without loss of information, so as
               to facilitate future use of that information by means of technologies not yet in
               existence. Such data-independence was, after all, one of the promises XML (and before
               it SGML) offered.</p>
            <p>If then it is decided to preserve the original TEI XML sources, what other components
               (schema files, stylesheets, etc.) should accompany them when submitting them for long
               term preservation in a digital archive? TEI encoded resources typically contain
               mostly XML-encoded text, possibly with links to files expressed using other commonly
               encountered web formats for graphics or audio; is there advantage to be gained by
               treating them differently from any other XML encoded resource? When such resources
               are deposited in a digital archive, what tools and expertise will the archivist need
               to have available in order to ensure that they are valid and will continue to be
               usable? </p>
            <p> This study attempts to address these questions by providing (in section <ptr
                  target="#rex"/>) <list>
                  <item>recommendations for the data depositor, specifically about what documents
                     should accompany a resource to be archived ; </item>
                  <item>recommendations for the archiving services, specifically about what tools
                     may be used to validate TEI XML documents ; </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>A number of different scenarios are envisaged, depending on the technical expertise
               and other resources available to the depositor (and the archive). We provide some
               technical background on the technologies concerned in section <ptr target="#tech"/>
               below.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="rex">
            <head>Recommendations</head>
            <!-- outcomes of this study -->
            <p>Our first recommendation is that depositors should as
               far as possible ensure that TEI-XML resources are accompanied by a file which
               accurately describes their encoding practices and purposes. The most appropriate
               format for this description would be the TEI-XML vocabulary commonly known as ODD,
               although producing documentation in this format is not as yet as well-understood or
               widely practiced within the TEI community as might be desired; a point to which we
               return below. Documentation in other forms, accompanied by validation schemas, are
               also useful, but they do not necessarily guarantee that the resources concerned will
               be TEI conformant. For this, an ODD is required. </p>
            <p>In the absence of ODD documentation from which a more appropriate schema may be
               derived, the only validation check possible before a resource can be accepted into
               the Archive will be against the generic TEI_All schema. According to the TEI
               definition, those parts of a document using the TEI namespace most be valid against
               this schema, which includes declarations for all possible TEI elements and
               attributes. </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="tech">
            <head>Technical background</head>
            
         </div>
         <div xml:id="gloss">
            <head>Glossary</head>
            <list type="gloss">
               <label>TEI</label><item></item>
               <label>schema</label><item>a set of rules expressed using a formal language (examples include RELAXNG, W3C Schema, and DTD) which can be used to validate the tagging of an XML document</item>
               <label>ODD</label><item>("One Document Does it all") a format defined by the TEI which documents the schema applicable to a set of TEI XML documents; also, a document in that format</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bibl">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <head>Literature on ODD</head>
               <bibl>
                  <note>Specification complète du langage ODD</note><ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html"
                     >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html</ref></bibl>
               <bibl><note>Description du traitement des fichiers ODD</note>
                  <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM"
                     >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM</ref></bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Support/Learn/odds.xml">Getting started with P5
                     ODDs</ref>
                  <ref target="http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm"
                     >http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm</ref>
                  <note>Introduction tutoriel </note></bibl>
               <bibl><ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml"
                     >http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml</ref>
                  <note>Introduction tutoriel</note></bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <author>
                     <forename>Lou</forename>
                     <surname>Burnard</surname>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <forename>Sebastian</forename>
                     <surname>Rahtz</surname>
                  </author><title>RelaxNG with Son of ODD</title>
                  <ptr
                     target="http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2004/Burnard01/EML2004Burnard01.html"/>
                  <title level="m">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages 2004</title>
                  <note>Technical description of the new ODD system developed for TEI P5.</note>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
