TEI as an archival format

The adoption of the TEI as a common storage format for digital resources in the Humanities has many consequences for those wishing to interchange, integrate, or process such resources. The TEI community is highly divers, but there is a general feeling that all of its members share an understanding of the best way to use the TEI Guidelines, and that those Guidelines express a common understanding of how text formats should be documented and defined. There is also (usually) a general willingness to make resources encoded according to the TEI Guidelines available in that format, as well as in whatever other publishing or distribution format has been adopted by the project. The question arises as whether such TEI-encoded resources are also suitable for long term preservation purposes : more specifically, if a project wishes to ensure long term preservation of its resources, should it archive them in a TEI format? And if so, what other components (schema files, stylesheets, etc.) should accompany the primary resource files when submitting them for long term preservation in a digital archive? TEI encoded resources typically contain mostly XML-encoded text, possibly with links to files expressed using other commonly encountered web formats for graphics or audio; is there any advantage to be gained in treating them any differently from any other such XML encoded resource?

This is not an entirely theoretical question : as more and more digitization projects seek to go beyond simply archiving digital page images,  the quantity of richly encoded TEI XML resources representing primary print or manuscript sources continues to increase.  In France alone, we may cite projects such as the ATILF, OpenEditions, BVH, BFM, Obvil and many more for all of which the TEI format is likely to be seen as the basic storage format, enabling the project to represent a usefully organised structural representation of the texts, either to complement the digital page images, or even to replace them for such purposes as the production of open online editions.  When such resources are  deposited in a digital archive, how should the archivist ensure that they are valid TEI and will continue to be usable ? One possibility might be to require that such resources are first converted to some other commonly recognised display format such as PDF or XHTML; and indeed for projects where the TEI form is considered only as a means to the end of disolaying the texts, this may well be adequte. But since TEI to HTML or TEI to PDF are lossy transformations, in whioch the added value consititured by TEI structural annotation is systematiocaly removedm this seems to us in general a less than desirable solution. We would like to be able to preserve our digital resources without loss of information, so as to facilitate future use of that information by means of technologies not yet in existence. Such data-independence was, after all, one of the promises  XML (and before it SGML) offered. 

The data archivist needs to be able to test the coherence and correctness of the resources entereung the archive, and also to monitor their continued usability. For an XML-based format, this is a relatively simple exercise. An XML file must be expressed using one of a small number of standard character encodings, and must use a tagging system the syntactic rules of which can be written on the back of a not particularly large envelope. The algorithm by which an XML document can be shown to be syntactically correct, (”well formed”) is expressible within the same scope and producing a piece of software able to determe that correctness is consequently equally trivial.  







 