<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Modelling meaning: a short history of text markup
        </title>
         <author>Lou Burnard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Unpublished draft for presentation at Paderborn</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Various old talks and TEI-L</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2019-04-01">First draft</change></revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div><head>Abstract</head>
        <p>Not so long ago (about 30 years ago to be precise), it was easy to
          decide how to process text by computer. If you wanted to store and
          then print the text out nicely, you would use one kind of software. If
          you wanted to analyse the text linguistically (yes, people did that 30
          years ago too), you'd use another. And if you were really interested
          in what the text was *about*, then you would probably throw the text
          away and use a database. But then someone realised that actually it
          might be more fun to combine all three kinds of process -- dealing
          with the text as an image, as a linguistic construct, and as a body of
          assertions about the real world -- and the need for a new kind of
          markup was born. In this talk I'll give a biassed and unreliable
          account of some key moments in the evolution of our current markup
          systems: from the corporate database of the 1970s to today's world
          wide web of documents and tomorrow's web of data, by way of SGML, TEI,
          XML, and other acronyms. Time permitting, I'll also try to explain why
          data and text are not so different after all.
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
    <div type="slide"><head></head>
    <list><item></item></list></div>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
