<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ab>  
<listPerson>
    <person xml:id="ELFALAKI">
        <p> Mahmoud Pacha El-Falaki (1815-1885) is a 19th century Egyptian astrologist and
            a pioneer of the Egyptian Renaissance in the mid 19th century. Born in
            Gharbiya, west of the Nile Delta to a fellah (peasant) father, Mahmoud moved to
            Alexandria in the company of his elder brother where they both studied at the
            Royal Maritime School. Mahmoud later joined the Mohandeskhana (School of
            Engineering). Upon graduation from the Mohandeskhana in 1839, Mahmoud's
            inquisitive intellect caught the attention of Ali Pacha Mubarak who nominated
            Mahmoud for a Royal Scholarship to study in France. In France, Mahmoud studied
            mathematics and French and was soon able to publish Arabic translations of
            books on differentiation and integration. In 1842, Mahmoud decided to study
            astronomy and practised at the Royal Rassd-e-khana (Observatory). During that
            time, Mahmoud wrote academic papers from his experiences and observations which
            earned him another royal scholarship to study in France once again between 1850
            and 1854. While in France, Mahmoud excelled in astronomy and geophysics and
            returned to Egypt nine years later (1859) during the reign of Khedive Said. He
            was elected to the membership of The Egyptian Scientific Association before he
            was commissioned to observe the solar eclipse in the 1860s. He quickly made
            news in the Royal Court and the Khedive Said who bestowed the title of Pacha
            unto him. Mahmoud Pacha El-Falaky was asked to head royal and ministerial
            commissions discussing the dissemination of education and knowledge. He was
            appointed Minister of Labour in the short-lived Mahmoud Samy Al-Baroudi
            government (1882) and then Minister of Knowledge in the Nobar Pacha government
            (1884-1888) until his death a year later. </p>
        <p>Voir http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k840511v/f9.image</p>
    </person>
</listPerson>
<listPlace>
    <place xml:id="MALEKA">
        <p>The Mosque of Maleka Safiya is 200 meters downward Mohamed Ali St in the side
            street of Sikket El-Maleka. Northward the mosque stands the Sabil-Kuttab of
            Mustafa El-Muhasibgi surrounded by a number of modern buildings that took a
            part of the original garden of the mosque. </p>
        <p> The mosque was constructed by Uthman Agha Dar El-Saada who was a Black Eunuch
            and an agent and servant of Queen Safiya. After his death before finishing the
            building, Queen Safiya, the wife of Sultan Murad III and the mother of Sultan
            Muhammed III, took it as a part of her fortune. She completed the construction
            of the mosque and supplied it with many custodians some of them carried the
            responsibility of cleaning the mosque and its garden, while others carried
            other responsibilities including teaching people the Islamic rites and the
            correct way of Reciting Quran. </p>
        <p> Of special interest in the interior plan of the mosque is the variety of
            styles of decoration used in it. It is quite different from the mosques that
            were built in the Ottoman period in Cairo for its structure that resembles that
            of the mosques of Istanbul. This appears clearly in the attachment of a garden
            to the mosque and the central dome of the mosque that is fixed upon six arches
            supported by Granite columns. At the same time it is similar to the other
            mosques of Cairo in placing the prayer niche in the back wall. </p>
        <p>The Mihrab with marble panels follows the Mamluk style of decoration, while the
            Minbar is ornamented on the Ottoman style. The mosque is illuminated through
            windows beautifully decorated with stained glass. There were many gatways for
            the mosque but now there is only one remaining entrance preceeded by a number
            of stairsteps. </p>
    </place>
</listPlace>
<listOrg>
    <org/>
</listOrg>
</ab>
