<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen NVDLSchema="../teitalks.nvdl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xml:lang="fr">

  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Interoperability of  TEI projects : apotheosis or chimera?</title>
<author>Lou Burnard</author>     
 </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>MEET</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Draft blog posting.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Original draft written on a train speeding across France.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2013-05-20">Added header
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>

<body>
<p>This was the fancy title (sounds better in French) of the closing talk
I gave at <ref target="http://gmlc.imf.csic.es/2013/workshop">an interesting 
workshop</ref> last week. A prevous COST-funded meeting in Krakow had
brought together teams working on several different dictionaries of
medieval Latin to elaborate the idea that maybe they could make their
various lexica interoperable if only they could agree on a common
format, for which the TEI seemed the most plausible candidate. Susanna
Allés, the energetic organizer of this workshop, got funding for it
from several sources, notably the ALLC or European Society for Digital
Humanities as it now prefers to be known. She also seems to have hit
on the wheeze of inviting a number of luminaries to make the case for
the TEI dictionary tagset (notably L. Romary, F. Glorieux, P. Banski),
but in the event alas only I turned out to be available. Which was
useful for me, since preparing for the workshop meant rediscovering
all sorts of dusty and neglected (by me, though not by others) parts
of the Guidelines.
</p><p>
The workshop was held in the CSIC (Spanish for CNRS) Istitucio Milà i
Fontanals, which occupies a rather grand building conveniently located
in the Raval, a picturesque if slightly seedy district of Barcelona,
to the left of the Ramblas, and we were all accomodated next door in
the splendidly-named Investigators' Residence on Calle
Hopital. Barcelona is not a place for those uninterested in food and
drink; and we were very well fed, in large quantities, if at strange
hours and (on one occasion) after a lengthy walk up town through an
unexpected tropical-style deluge. The ravioli stuffed with pears and
cheese offered by the resto "En Ville" for lunch was particularly
memorable, invidious though it is to single out this one occasion.
</p><p>
More intellectual fare was also on offer, of course. It is always a
pleasure to arrive amongst a group of specialists personally unknown to
me and from a domain of which I am more or less totally ignorant and
find that word of the TEI has already reached them, and often in a far
from superficial way. So I was made very happy indeed to hear Sabine
Thuillier (currently working in Madrid on the <title>Diccionario
Griego-Espanol</title> but <soCalled>formed</soCalled> as they say at the Ecole Nationale
des Chartes) evangelise for the TEI as an international open source
community, and impressed by the way she is implementing it in a
workflow which though its editors remain obstinately based on Word
Perfect, remains determed to envisage production of a respectable TEI
P5 version.
</p><p>

Similarly, the team responsible for the <title>eLexicon Mediae Latinitatis
Polonorum</title> lead by Krzysztof Nowak from Krakow, while maintaining a
proper scepticism about some aspects of the TEI's conceptual model,
was clearly persuaded of its virtues as an open standard, notably as
evidenced by both the amount of open source software (they mentioned
XTF, Philogic, and TXM) and the number of comparable projects (they
mentioned the Anglo Norman Dictionary, the Glossarium DuCange, and
several others) using TEI. Their workflow starts with an OCR phase,
since they are starting from an extensive library of source texts (see
http://scriptores.pl/fontes), and then uses LibreOffice and a
customised library of styles to enhance it to the point where it can
be automaticalty converted to TEI, thus (apparently independently)
following the same path as is used by Lodel, OxGarage, Agora, and no
doubt others, to combine the user friendliness of a word processing
style interface with the rigour of a TEI structured maintenance
format.
</p><p>

Catalonia has ambitions (as posters everywhere proclaim) to become
politically independent of Spain, and certainly its linguistic
independence is a well established fact. As a confirmed non-speaker of
either Spanish or Catalan (nor of Basque, Galician, or Portuguese for
that matter) I regretfully let the interventions in those languages
wash over me, and thus missed out, notably on Jose Manuel de
Bustamente's insights on the relation between textual corpus and
dictionary. I did however manage to understand the German colleagues
present since they made the effort to speak in English or French, for
example Alexandra Gorbrecht from the Trier Centre for Digital
Humanities gave a brief overview of the dozen or so dictionaries put
together online at woerterbuchnetz.de with a well designed query
interface. Allegedy all of these dictionaries are locally stored in
TEI XML, but as this is not currently exposed one cannot tell how
consistently it has been done.  None of the other major TEI dictionary
projects in Germany I am aware of was represented here: presumably
because none of them is specifically concerned with Mediaeval Latin. I
had to console myself for the absence of Werner Wegstein from Wurzburg
by stealing one of his examples for my own talk.
</p><p>

Bruno Bon and Renaud Alexandre from the IRHT in Paris had the
advantage, if advantage it be, of being able to develop their
proposals for an over-arching <title>Novum Glossarium Mediae
Latinitatis</title> on the basis of the already existant complete <ref
target="http://ducange.enc.sorbonne.fr">Glossarium of Du Cange</ref>
which has been freely available in TEI-inspired XML markup for some
time now, thanks to the work of Fréderic Le Glorieux. The idea seems
to be to develop a set of proposals able to express the (not
inconsiderable) variation in practice amongst these and others working
on different lexica of medieval Latin in Europe, and thus create what
(inevitably) Bruno suggested would be called NGML (the Novum
Glossarium Markup Language). As a first step they have set up <ref target="http://scriptores.pl/santiago/index.php?title=Accueil">an
exploratory wiki</ref> with some nice visualisation tools, based on a few
sample entries taken from each of the five different lexical projects (specifically, in Barcelona, Prague, Krakow, Munich and Paris), and are
inviting more. This could be fun, though I think expressing NGML as a
real TEI ODD would be more of a challenge.  </p>

<p> Susanna Allés and her graduate student Frédérique Laugrost (on
secondment from the Ecole Nationale des Chartes) talked about the
specific problems they faced when starting to apply the TEI to the
text of their dictionary: the <title>Glossarium Mediae Latinitatis
Cataloniae</title>. Many of these are familiar, of course: notably
those which derive directly from the wish to preserve the punctuation
and use of abbreviation which characterize such sources and at the
same time model the logical structure which they determine. Some of
these problems do however point to aspects of the current TEI
dictionary model which could be improved.  </p>

<p>I started making a short list of such points
during the workshop, but sadly did not get very far:
<list>
<item>too many of the proposed TEI dictionary elements  relate only to
modern lexicographic practice. Deciding which ones to filter out to
make a kind of TEI Lite for dictionaries would be very desirable.
</item><item>
an element for "translated segment" is desired, even if it is just
syntactic sugar for <gi>mentioned</gi> with a value for xml:lang other than
that of the surrounding text
</item><item>
some dictionaries have entries which are large enough to have
multiple paragraphs but there is no place for <gi>p</gi> in any
model.entryLike element
</item><item>
when a term is identical in two or more languages, can xml:lang take
more than one value (I confidently said it couild, but I think I am
wrong)
</item><item>
how should you mark a word which is clearly readable in the text when its
meaning is entirely uncertain? (I suggested <gi>orig</gi>, but there must be
better ideas)
</item><item>
The typology currently used for <gi>form</gi> combines categories from
entirely dissimilar taxonomies, e.g @type=lemma is an entirely
different kind of thing from @type=compound. Likewise, the typology
one might want to use for <gi>usg</gi> should be more to do with the way the
sense had evolved. To both these points I said (in my best French)
"Bof", Or, more precisely, it's only by getting together with
specialists in the field able to define more appropriate typologies
than the TEI currently proposes
</item></list></p>
<p>I'm hoping that the undoubted success of this workshop will encourage the
participants to form a SIG on the subject or (as Piotr Banski had
previously suggested to several of them) to make an active contribution
to the existing LingSig. Plenty of scope for very interesting work to
come, not to mention the opportunity of returning to Barcelona for
the paella which I somehow failed to find time for on this occasion.
</p></body></text></TEI>