<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:eg="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>What is the Text Encoding Initiative?</title>
        <author>Lou Burnard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>For publication by Open Edition Press </p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>All my own work</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc><tagsDecl>
      <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="title">font-style:italic</rendition>
      <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="foreign">font-style:italic</rendition>
      <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="term">font-style:italic</rendition>
      <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="emph">font-style:italic; font-weight: bold;</rendition>
      <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="tag">font-family:monospace</rendition>
      <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="gi">font-family:monospace</rendition>
      <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="att">font-family:monospace</rendition>
      <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="label">font-weight: bold;</rendition>
      <rendition scheme="css" xml:id="ident">font-family:monospace</rendition>
    </tagsDecl></encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>  
        <change>
          <name>Lou Burnard</name>
          <date>2013-11-20</date>
          <desc>Minor revisions for conversion to Lodel</desc>
        </change>
      <change>
        <name>Lou Burnard</name>
        <date>2013-11-02</date>
        <desc>Revised after further comments from reviewers; added glossary</desc>
      </change>
      <change>
        <name>Lou Burnard</name>
        <date>2013-08-18</date>
        <desc>Revised section ANA and HDR; feels like this is finished</desc>
      </change>
      <change>
        <name>Lou Burnard</name>
        <date>2013-08-09</date>
        <desc>Spellcheck</desc>
      </change>
      <change>
        <name>Lou Burnard</name>
        <date>2013-08-06</date>
        <desc>Added proper bibliog</desc>
      </change>
      <change>
        <name>Lou Burnard</name>
        <date>2013-07-18</date>
        <desc>Started topping and tailing</desc>
      </change>
      <change>
        <name>Lou Burnard</name>
        <date>2013-05-05</date>
        <desc>About two-thirds done</desc>
      </change>
      <change>
        <name>Lou Burnard</name>
        <date>2013-04-07T18:47:43</date>
        <desc>Started hacking</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>The Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) is one of the longest-lived and most influential
          projects in the field now known as the Digital Humanities. Its purpose is to provide
          guidelines for the creation and management in digital form of every type of data created
          and used by researchers in the Humanities, such as source texts, manuscripts, archival
          documents, ancient inscriptions, and many others. As its name suggests, its primary focus
          is on text rather than sound or video, but it can usefully be applied to any form of
          digital data. Crucially, it was created and is maintained by the scholarly community for
          the use of that community. In this little book, we will try to explain the nature and
          goals of the TEI and to provide some concrete examples of how it may be used in a variety
          of digital resource creation projects. But before that, we will try to answer a question
          which introductory texts such as this one tend to neglect: why bother with TEI in the
          first place? After all, almost everyone now knows how to use a word processor to create
          digital documents, or a database system to create and manage information, or a simple
          editor to create web pages. What advantage is there to learning XML or TEI to do the same
          job? </p>
        <p>There are many answers, but we will discuss three in particular. The first is that TEI
          XML focuses on the meaning of text, rather than its appearance. The second is that TEI XML
          is independent of any particular software environment. The third is that TEI XML was
          designed by and for the scholarly research community, which is also responsible for its
          ongoing development. </p>
        <list type="gloss">
          <label>Meaning before format</label>
          <item><p>If you care about the words in your text and their meanings more than you do
              about the way they are laid out on the page you will soon encounter some frustrating
              limitations when using a typical word processor. Almost any such system will readily
              search through hundreds of pages of text and retrieve all the occurrences of the
              string "London" for you. But an intelligent search ― one in which "London" as the name
              of a place in Canada is distinguished from that of a place in England, or the surname
              of an author ― requires something more. As <ref target="#Coombsetal1987">Coombs et
                al</ref> pointed out back in 1987, there is a significant difference between the way
              a scholar looks at textual resources and the way in which most automated document
              preparation systems text are designed. To use an often quoted phrase, <q>What You See
                is What You Get means What You See is ALL you Get</q>: that is, systems which are
              mostly concerned to narrow the gap between what you see on the screen and what you
              type at the keyboard tend to achieve this by reducing what you can express and store
              in digital form to information about the appearance of strings of characters rather
              than their linguistic properties or function. You can adjust the font, size,
              alignment, or colour of each occurrence of the word "London" in your document as much
              as you like; but you cannot reliably or consistently use word processing software to
              indicate which ones are personal names and which are place names. </p></item>
          <label>Software independence</label>
          <item><p>If you want to share the textual resources you create with other people (or with
              yourself a few decades hence) you should also be concerned about the tendency of many
              computer systems to enforce their own idiosyncratic ways of storing information. How
              easily can a document or database prepared using your current favourite software be
              used by a different piece of software? can it be transferred from your PC to her Mac
              to my Linux box without loss of information? Of course software exists to make
              transformations amongst the dozens of different file formats currently in use; that is
              the good news. The bad news is that such transformations are always necessary, and are
              often complex, lossy, or costly to perform. Even within the same style of software
              true interoperability remains problematic: a document prepared on one word processor
              (say Word) may or may not look the same when opened by another (say Open Office); a
              database created by Filemaker Pro may or may not be easy to convert to one using
              Microsoft Access, and vice versa. </p>
            <p>The information captured in a TEI XML document looks exactly the same to every piece
              of software using it. There is no special magic, accessible only to one particular
              piece of software running in one environment. A TEI XML file, like other XML files, is
              just a sequence of readable characters, with no secret embedded codes. Indeed, a TEI
              XML document represents a text largely without <emph>any</emph> consideration of the
              software which might be used to visualise, analyse or store it. Instead, the content
              of a TEI XML document represents directly whatever its creator considers significant
              about its structure and content. If there is a string of characters which the encoder
              identifies as the name of a person or place, or as a foreign word, or as the title of
              a song, or as a passage of direct speech (for example), the TEI provides labels to
              identify them. It may be desirable to visualise song titles in italic when printing
              them, but to add links to a database entry when displaying them on a website. It might
              be desirable to include (or exclude) passages of direct speech or foreign words when
              doing a vocabulary analysis of a text. Texts in digital form can be used in many many
              different ways, after all: that is why we create them. If all that is needed is a new
              copy of an old book, a digital photocopy will suffice. But if the goal is to make an
              old text accessible to a variety of new readers, then just reproducing its appearance
              on the page will hardly suffice. TEI-XML gives us a framework for representing
              whatever is considered of importance about the text, not just its appearance, so that
              software can act on the distinctions identified, generating new visualisations and new
              perspectives. Consequently, deciding what TEI-XML markup to use is always a scholarly
              activity, always involving conscious choice. </p></item>
          <label>Community-driven</label>
          <item><p>The TEI was first developed over thirty years ago, as a research project in the
              then-emerging field of "humanities computing". The original idea was to propose a set
              of recommendations about how researchers should create "machine-readable" textual
              resources, which would be adequate to the needs of research, to the extent that
              consensus on the topic existed, but which would also be expandable as those needs
              changed and evolved. This combination of flexibility with a focus on the scientific
              needs of a particular community makes the TEI unique among other standardisation
              efforts, and is also one of the factors underlying its longevity. In a strictly
              Darwinian sense, the TEI evolves by responding to changes that are considered
              beneficial by its user community, while ignoring those which are not.</p><p>This close
              involvement with its user community also has beneficial effects for the novice:
              awareness of and expertise in the TEI can now readily be found in most disciplines in
              the humanities: it is not restricted to a recondite area of information science.
              Institutions like the TEI mailing list TEI-L provide vivid testimony of the
              heterogenous nature of the TEI community, as well as repeatedly demonstrating its
              openness, friendliness, and readiness to assist the beginner. </p></item>
        </list>
        <p>This book aims to showcase a few of the many varieties of TEI markup without going into
          much detail for any of them. We hope it will be accessible to a wide readership, including
          both the practising digital humanist and those who have not yet fully succumbed to the
          lure of the computer. To understand it, you need only some very general notions about XML
          technologies and an interest in the traditional problems of textual scholarship. You
          should also be aware that using the TEI does not mean using the whole of the TEI : on the
          contrary, most TEI users use only a small subset of what it offers. But deciding which
          subset is best for your purposes is something that only you can decide. </p>
        <p>Chapter <ptr target="#TEIXML"/> gives a little technical background introducing the XML
          concepts that underlie TEI markup. Chapter <ptr target="#STRUC"/> describes how TEI
          documents are structured, followed by a number of typical examples in chapter <ptr
            target="#STRUCEGS"/>. The two following chapters then go into more detail, discussing
          first some textual features common to most types of document (chapter <ptr target="#CORE"
          />) and then a few of the more specialised possibilities offered by the TEI system
          (chapter <ptr target="#TOPS"/>). Chapter <ptr target="#HDR"/> describes the TEI Header,
          the mandatory <q>digital title-page</q> of a TEI document that provides its metadata.
          Chapter <ptr target="#ODD"/> discusses how to tailor the TEI system to the needs of a
          particular project. We conclude with some discussion of how the TEI itself is organized,
          its present, and its future. </p>
        <!--p> For every element mentioned there is a link to <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/REF-ELEMENTS.html">the page on the TEI
            website </ref> where full information about that element is provided and from which detailed
          discussion of its functionality and examples of usage are readily accessible in a few clicks.</p-->
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="TEIXML">
        <head>The TEI and XML</head>
        <p>The TEI emphasizes what is common to every kind of document, whether physically
          represented in digital form on disk or memory card, in printed form as book or newspaper,
          in written form as manuscript or codex, or in inscribed form on stone or wax tablet. This
          continuity facilitates the migration of text from older manifestations such as print or
          manuscript to newer ones such as disk or display. Hence, the TEI view of what text
          actually <emph>is</emph> is largely conditioned by what text <emph>has been</emph> in the
          past, without however compromising too greatly what text may become in the future. It
          attempts to treat all kinds of digital document in the same way, whether they were
            <soCalled>born digital</soCalled> or not. </p>
        <p>As a consequence, the TEI framework provides a useful way of thinking about the nature of
          text: it constitutes a kind of encyclopaedia of generally-agreed textual notions. In this
          brief guide we will try to exemplify some of these notions, using the vocabulary defined
          by the TEI in its <title>Guidelines</title>
        </p>
        <p>At present TEI documents in digital form are expressed using a very widely-used formal
          encoding language called XML, the <q>extensible markup language</q>, first published by
          the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) in 1998, but with origins in the document preparation
          systems of the 1980s. XML provides a simple way of representing structured data as a
          linear stream of character data, and of labelling particular parts of that stream with
          named <q>tags</q> to indicate structural function or semantics. Because it has become such
          a pervasive technology, many excellent introductory guides are available elsewhere and we
          will therefore assume in the reader a basic understanding of such key concepts as
            <q>element</q>, <q>attribute</q>, <q>schema</q>, <q>name space</q>, briefly glossed
          below for the sake of intelligibility. The TEI <title>Guidelines</title> include a
            <soCalled>Gentle Introduction</soCalled> to XML, which may be useful to the novice, but
          many other tutorials on the subject are to be found.</p>
        <p>Here is an example of a minimal XML document: </p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0"?>  
          <doc xmlns="http://example.org/namespace">
            <p n="1">This is a paragraph.</p>
            <p n="2">This paragraph mentions <placeName>Bristol</placeName>.</p>
          </doc>]]></egXML>

        <p>The first line of an XML document always takes the form shown above: a special kind of
          instruction indicating that what follows is an XML document conforming to the version of
          the XML standard indicated (in this case, version 1). An XML document consists of a
          sequence of human-readable characters, with no special additional codes or binary data.
          The characters &lt; and &gt; are used to mark the start and end of <term>tags</term>
          within this sequence. A tag may be a start-tag (such as <code>&lt;p&gt;</code>) or an
          end-tag (such as <code>&lt;/p&gt;</code>). A tag always begins with a name
            (<code>doc</code>, <code>p</code>, <code>placeName</code> in the above example) and may
          also contain attribute specifications (such as <code>n="1"</code>). The purpose of a
          start-tag is to mark the point in the sequence of characters at which some
            <term>element</term>, of a type indicated by the tag name, starts, and the purpose of an
          end-tag is to mark where that element ends. The purpose of an attribute specification is
          to add some extra information about an element occurrence beyond its name. In the above
          example we have an element named <gi>doc</gi> which contains two <gi>p</gi> elements. The
            <gi>p</gi> elements both have an <att>n</att> attribute which supplies a number, and
          both contain plain text. The second <gi>p</gi> element also contains an element called
            <gi>placeName</gi></p>
        <p>An XML document like this is said to be <term>well-formed</term> if it respects the
          syntax exemplified here, with start- and end-tags both present and correctly nested. But
          the XML standard says nothing at all about how elements or attributes should be named
          (unlike, for example, HTML which defines a specific set of tags that must be used in a
          particular way in all documents), much less what their names mean. We may guess that the
            <gi>p</gi> elements above are marking up numbered paragraphs, but there is nothing in
          the XML representation to warrant that assumption ― they could just as well mark up pages,
          or entries in a glossary, or lines of verse. If therefore I find another document
          containing <gi>p</gi> elements, how will I know whether they have the same function? The
          function of the <att>xmlns</att> attribute above is to help solve this problem by
          supplying a default for what is called the <term>namespace</term> of all the elements
          contained by the <gi>doc</gi> element. </p>
        <p>It is not unusual to find elements from many namespaces in a single document : for
          example, a document containing music notation, vector graphics, and text all represented
          in XML might use tags from three different namespaces, one for the musical elements, one
          for the graphical ones, and one for the textual ones. A namespace is a way of labelling a
          group of elements: in our example, its use makes clear that the <gi>p</gi>elements here
          are different from any <gi>p</gi> elements defined by some other namespace. </p>
        <p>The reason for introducing tagging into a document is to label and organize it for
          machine processing. If the paragraphs are clearly marked, then a formatter can lay them
          out properly. If the place-names are clearly marked, a program can automatically pick them
          out to make a geographical index. But this can really only be done reliably if we have
          some control over what tags are introduced into the document and where they appear. XML
          technology provides this additional level of control by means of what is called a
            <term>schema</term>, a kind of combined lexicon and grammar for valid XML documents. We
          noted above that an XML document is said to be well-formed if it respects the syntactic
          rules of the XML standard. It may, optionally, also be said to be <term>valid</term>, if
          the tags it contain conform to a schema.</p>
        <p>A <term>schema</term> specifies a set of element names, the names and datatypes of any
          attributes associated with them, and rules about the contexts in which they may legally
          appear. A schema for our simple example above will say that elements named <gi>doc</gi>,
            <gi>p</gi>, <gi>placeName</gi> etc exist. It may also specify that <gi>p</gi> elements
          may appear within <gi>doc</gi> elements, that <gi>placeName</gi>s may appear within
            <gi>p</gi>s, that the attribute <att>n</att> must have a numeric value etc. Note however
          that an XML schema still has no way of specifying that the tag <gi>placeName</gi>
          indicates the name of a place, or what we mean by "a place": such additional semantic
          constraints must be specified elsewhere, for example by documentation such as that
          provided by the TEI <title>Guidelines</title>. </p>
        <p>The TEI provides names and definitions for many hundred tags, together with rules about
          how they may be combined. More exactly, the TEI Guidelines define some five or six hundred
          different <emph>concepts</emph>, along with detailed specifications for the XML elements
          and element classes which may be used to represent them. Most, if not all, TEI documents
          need to use only a small amount of what is provided. It is therefore somewhat misleading
          to think of the TEI as a single monolithic schema. To facilitate interoperability, every
          TEI document uses components taken from the same mammoth schema, but most TEI projects use
          quite small subsets of it, and a well-organised project will generally have its own
          customized documentation identifying that subset. </p>
        <p>Software such as the web application <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Roma">Roma</ref>
          can be used to select amongst the TEI specifications and generate from them a schema
          appropriate to the needs of your own project, or you can simply assemble a schema by hand.
          We discuss this topic in more detail in chapter <ptr target="#ODD"/> below. The TEI's
            <title>Guidelines</title>, freely accessible from its web site at <ptr
            target="www.tei-c.org/Guidelines"/>, constitute a complete reference manual for these
          concepts, combining technical specification with detailed discussion of how they are meant
          to be used. </p>
        <p>There is a very wide range of software tools available to create, transform, and process
          XML documents in general, or TEI XML in particular. This is a very large and fast-moving
          topic which is not treated here, though you will find some useful pointers on the TEI
          website and the TEI Wiki.</p>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="STRUC">
        <head>The structural organization of a TEI document</head>
        <p>All TEI documents are organized in a similar way, no matter what kind of original they
          represent. We will introduce some of the most commonly encountered variations on this
          structure by means of some simple examples.</p>
        <div>
          <head>Header, Text, and Divisions</head>
          <p>To begin at the beginning, every TEI document (represented by means of a <gi>TEI</gi>
            element) has at least two parts: a <term>header</term> (represented by means of a
              <gi>teiHeader</gi> element) containing metadata describing the document, and the text
            itself (usually represented by a <gi>text</gi> element). For example :</p>
          <eg><![CDATA[
                <TEI xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0'> 
                <teiHeader>
                <!-- metadata describing a text  --> </teiHeader> 
                <text> <!-- a representation of the text itself --> </text> 
                </TEI>]]></eg>
          <p>Like every other TEI XML document, this one explicitly states that the elements it
            contain are by default to be understood as coming from the TEI namespace
              <val>http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0</val>. </p>
          <p>We describe the header in more detail in section <ptr target="#HDR"/> below; for the
            moment we note simply that a minimal header must contain information identifying the
            document itself (in the <gi>titleStmt</gi>), information about how it is distributed or
            published (in the <gi>publicationStmt</gi>) and some indication of its origins (in the
              <gi>sourceDesc</gi>). The <gi>text</gi> element is used to hold an encoded version of
            the text itself, in which its structure is represented by elements such as
              <gi>front</gi> (for prefaces etc.) <gi>body</gi> (for the body of the text proper) and
              <gi>back</gi> (for any appendixes etc.). Within these components, we may also
            represent further subdivisions such as volumes, parts, chapters etc. using the
              <gi>div</gi> element. </p>
          <p>For example, here is the start of a minimal TEI version of a famous novel, as it might
            be distributed by an imaginary digital publisher: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <![CDATA[  <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <teiHeader>
                  <fileDesc>
                    <titleStmt>
                      <title>The life and opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gentleman: TEI
                        edition</title>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                      <publisher>Web Head Press</publisher>
                      <date>2013</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                      <p>Transcribed from the first edition, 1708</p>
                    </sourceDesc>
                  </fileDesc>
                </teiHeader>
                <text>
                  <body>
                    <div type="volume" xml:id="TS01">
                      <div type="chapter" xml:id="TS0101">
                        <head>Chap. I</head>
                        <p>I wish either my father or my mother, or indeed both of them, as they
                          were in duty both equally bound to it, had minded what they were about
                          when they begot me; ...</p>
                        <!-- remainder of chapter 1 here -->
                      </div>
                      <div type="chapter" xml:id="TS0102">
                        <head>Chap. II</head>
                        <p>―― Then, positively, there is nothing in the question, that I can see,
                          either good or bad.―― Then let me tell you, Sir, it was a very
                          unseasonable question at least ...</p>
                        <!-- remainder of chapter 2 here -->
                      </div>
                      <!-- remaining chapters of volume 1 here -->
                    </div>
                    <!-- remaining volumes of work here -->
                  </body>
                </text>
              </TEI>]]>
          </egXML>

          <p>In this example the body of a text contains smaller divisions, themselves containing
            sub-divisions. Such textual subdivisions have different names in different cultures and
            in different kinds of document; many western cultures use names such as <q>section</q>,
              <q>part</q>, <q>book</q>, or <q>chapter</q> (or their equivalents) for these sub-parts
            of the body, but often in inconsistent or mutually incompatible ways. What is called a
              <q>part</q> within a <q>book</q> in one text may be called a <q>section</q> within a
              <q>chapter</q> in another, or a <q>book</q> within a <q>part</q> in a third. Hence,
            the TEI proposes a single element <gi>div</gi> for any such structural subdivision of
            the body of a text.</p>
          <p>The <gi>div</gi> element can carry a number of attributes to indicate its function and
            its properties more exactly. Here, we have used the <att>type</att> attribute to
            characterize or classify the content of the element, thus distinguishing the
              <gi>div</gi> elements containing <soCalled>volumes</soCalled> from those containing
              <soCalled>chapters</soCalled>. We have also used the <att>xml:id</att> attribute to
            provide a unique identifier for each division of the novel. </p>
          <p>This same kind of hierarchic structure may be used for any kind of text. For example,
            an epic poem divided into books might tag each book as a <tag>div type='book'</tag>; a
            play divided into acts and scenes might tag them <tag>div type='act'</tag> and <tag>div
              type='scene'</tag> respectively; and so on. The values available for use with the
              <att>type</att> and <att>xml:id</att> attributes are not defined by the TEI, but are
            chosen by the encoder. For <att>xml:id</att> the values used are arbitrary codes unique
            to the element on which they appear: they provide a way of labelling the element
            concerned so that other parts of this or other documents can point to it directly. For
              <att>type</att> the values are also arbitrary codes, chosen by the encoder to indicate
            the function of the <gi>div</gi> concerned. Some commonly encountered values such as
              <val>chapter</val> or <val>volume</val> are suggested in the Guidelines, but it is
            left to individual projects using the TEI to define their own taxonomy. It is however
            easy both to document and to enforce any chosen taxonomy by means of a TEI
            customisation, as discussed further in chapter <ptr target="#ODD"/>. </p>
          <p>The <gi>div</gi> element is so named because it is a <emph>division</emph>; it should
            not therefore be used for something which is complete in itself. If the body of a text
            is undivided there is no need to provide a single <gi>div</gi> element to contain it.
            Instead, the <gi>body</gi> element may contain directly one or more of the elements
            described in the next section.</p>
          <p>A <gi>text</gi> is typically something like a book or an article, but may be anything
            which it is convenient to regard as a discrete but complete textual object, such as a
            single poem or archival document, or something as small as a postcard. As an alternative
            or in addition to the <gi>text</gi> element, the TEI also provides a <gi>facsimile</gi>
            element which could be used to provide a complementary visual representation, for
            example as a series of digitized page images. And the TEI also provides ways of
            representing collections of such things, as discussed in section <ptr target="#compo"/>
            below.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="STRUCEGS">
        <head>Varieties of textual structure</head>
        <p>In the TEI view, texts and their divisions may contain a fairly limited range of
            <soCalled>structural</soCalled> components. These include such things as the headings or
          preliminary matter at the start or end of a division, and a number of basic building
          blocks which are characteristic of prose, verse, or drama. Prose, for the most part,
          consists of paragraphs or lists, marked using the elements <gi>p</gi> or <gi>list</gi>
          respectively. Verse consists of verse lines, marked using the <gi>l</gi> element, or
          sequences of verse lines marked using the <gi>lg</gi> (line group) element. In drama, an
          additional building block is provided in the form of the <gi>sp</gi> (speech) element,
          which combines a <gi>speaker</gi> element with one or more <gi>p</gi> or <gi>l</gi>
          elements depending on whether the drama is in verse or prose.</p>
        <div>
          <head>A journal article</head>
          <p>The body of an academic article, for example, might be encoded with a structure like
            the following : </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><body xml:lang="en">
              <div type="section">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>We recommend the use of TEI markup as a means of representing scientific prose.
                  It has a number of practical advantages: </p>
                <list>
                  <item>TEI markup is easy to add;</item>
                  <item>TEI markup is widely understood;</item>
                  <item>TEI markup is easy to convert to other formats.</item>
                </list>
                <p>TEI markup also has some scientific advantages, which we discuss in section <ptr
                    target="#SEC3"/>.</p>
                <!-- further introductory paragraphs here -->
              </div>
              <div type="section">
                <head>Origins of the TEI</head>
                <p>The Text Encoding Initiative was born in 1987 .... </p>
                <!-- many more paragraphs here -->
              </div>
              <div xml:id="SEC3">
                <head>Scientific properties of TEI markup</head>
                <p>TEI markup expresses a view of the nature of text ... </p>
                <!-- many more paragraphs here -->
              </div>
            </body>
          </egXML>

          <p>Note that this markup indicates only the organization of the document. It says nothing
            about how it should be visualised on screen or on paper. It indicates that there are
            sections which have titles, and which contain paragraphs and lists. It distinguishes the
            items in the list, but it does not specify whether they should be prefixed with a bullet
            or a dash or a number. The <gi>ptr</gi> element indicates the existence of a cross
            reference from one part of the document (the location of the <gi>ptr </gi> element) to
            another (the <gi>div</gi> element entitled <q>Scientific properties...</q>). The value
            of the <att>xml:id</att> attribute introduced above specifies the target of the cross
            reference, but it does not specify whether this should be realised as (say) an HTML
            link, or some added text (such as the section number) or both. Of course, it is not hard
            to imagine how we might display these document components using a formatting language
            such as Word, HTML, or LaTex but that is not the primary purpose of this markup. Because
            these aspects are all left unspecified in the encoding, the same document can be re-used
            in different processing contexts. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>A poetic text</head>
          <p>Our second example shows a famous Shakespearian sonnet, transcribed from a specific
            print copy: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="en">
            <lg type="sonnet">
              <head>130</head>
              <l>My Mistres eyes are nothing like the Sunne,</l>
              <l>Currall is farre more red, then her lips red,</l>
              <l>If snow be white why then her brests are dun:</l>
              <l>If haires be wiers, black wiers grow on her head:</l>
              <l>I have seene Roses damaskt, red and white,</l>
              <l>But no such Roses see I in her cheekes,</l>
              <l>And in some perfumes is there more delight,</l>
              <l>Then in the breath that from my Mistres reekes.</l>
              <l>I loue to heare her speake, yet well I know.</l>
              <l>That Musicke hath a farre more pleasing sound:</l>
              <l>I graunt I never saw a goddesse goe,</l>
              <l>My Mistress when she walkes treads on the ground.</l>
              <lg type="couplet">
                <l>And yet by heaven I thinke my love as rare,</l>
                <l>As any she beli'd with false compare.</l>
              </lg>
            </lg>
          </egXML>
          <p>Again, this markup captures only the structure of the sonnet: indicating the individual
            verse lines of which it is composed, and marking explicitly the couplet at its end.
            Because individual lines are distinguished in the encoding, rather than being treated as
            if they were paragraphs, or accidents of formatting, a metrical analysis of the poem can
            automatically be generated.</p>
          <p> Comparing it with the following digital image of the original source we can see that
            although the original spelling has been retained, this encoding has chosen to ignore
            such layout features as the use of dropped caps or the indentation associated with the
            couplet. It has retained the original spelling, but silently modernised some of the
            typographic variation, such as the long S, or the ligatured letters. </p>
          <p><figure>
              <graphic url="shakson.png" width="90%"/>
              <head>Sonnet 130 from <title>Shake-speares Sonnets. Never before Imprinted</title>
                (1609)</head>
            </figure> We will see below how this encoding could be enhanced to produce an acceptable
            modern reading version as well as the quasi-diplomatic version shown here. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>A play text</head>
          <p>Our third example shows how we might encode the structure of a dramatic text : in this
            case, the end of Beckett's <title>Waiting for Godot</title>. </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <div type="scene">
              <!-- ... -->
              <sp>
                <speaker>Vladimir</speaker>
                <p>Pull on your trousers.</p>
              </sp>
              <sp>
                <speaker>Estragon</speaker>
                <p>You want me to pull off my trousers?</p>
              </sp>
              <sp>
                <speaker>Vladimir</speaker>
                <p>Pull <emph>on</emph> your trousers.</p>
              </sp>
              <sp>
                <speaker>Vladimir</speaker>
                <p><stage>(realizing his trousers are down)</stage>. True</p>
              </sp>
              <stage>He pulls up his trousers</stage>
              <sp>
                <speaker>Vladimir</speaker>
                <p>Well? Shall we go?</p>
              </sp>
              <sp>
                <speaker>Estragon</speaker>
                <p>Yes, let's go.</p>
              </sp>
              <stage>They do not move.</stage>
            </div>
          </egXML>
          <p>In this encoding, we have introduced a few more TEI elements, to enable us to
            distinguish the stage directions (<gi>stage</gi>) from the individual speeches of the
            characters (<gi>sp</gi>). Note that a stage direction can appear both within and between
            speeches and that a speech always contains both an identifying label to show who is
            speaking (<gi>speaker</gi>) and a paragraph (<gi>p</gi>) to contain what they say. In a
            verse drama, of course, the speeches would probably contain a sequence of <gi>l</gi>
            elements. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>A postcard</head>
          <p>The TEI is widely used for existing literary or formally published works. However it
            can also be used for entirely different kinds of document, such as authorial
            manuscripts, archival papers, or any other kind of informal writing. Our fourth example
            shows how we might use the TEI to encode the structure of this postcard : </p>
          <figure>
            <graphic url="postcard.jpg" width="90%"/>
            <head>A picture postcard (verso)</head>
          </figure>
          <p>All postcards have two sides, a recto and a verso: we represent these as <gi>div</gi>
            elements. Within the side shown above, we can see that there is a clear distinction
            between the part carrying the message, to the left, and the part relating to the sending
            of the card, containing various stamps and an address. Here is one possible encoding,
            which uses the same <gi>div</gi> and <gi>p</gi> elements we have already seen, together
            with some additional more specialised elements and attributes: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <div type="verso">
              <div type="message">
                <p>You should try this place. You can see how genteel it is</p>
                <p> Hope you enjoyed Wales, as they said to Mrs Fitzherbert</p>
                <signed>Mama</signed>
              </div>
              <div type="destination">
                <ab>
                  <stamp type="publicity">Silhouette of vintage car and slogan <mentioned>Brighton
                      &amp; Hove all set for the seventies.</mentioned></stamp>
                  <stamp type="postmark">Circular mark specifying <mentioned>Brighton &amp; Hove -
                      Sussex</mentioned> and <date when="1970-10-26">26 Oct 1970</date></stamp>
                  <stamp type="postage"> Machin design. 4d, vermillion. </stamp>
                </ab>
                <address>
<addrLine>Mr Louis Burnard</addrLine>
<addrLine>4 Freeland Cottages,</addrLine>
<addrLine>Stanton St John</addrLine>
<addrLine>OXFORD</addrLine>
</address>
              </div>
            </div>
          </egXML>
          <p>The <gi>signed</gi> element used to enclose the signature block is one of several
            specialised elements provided by the TEI for material such as signatures or headings
            which can appear at the beginning or end of a <gi>div</gi>. It seems useful to
            distinguish it from the rest of the message, since other such <q>signing off</q> phrases
            or <foreign rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">formules de politesse</foreign> contain a
            different, more formal, kind of language from the rest.</p>
          <p>In the other division, we have distinguished three different kinds of stamp: the
            postage stamp itself, the postmark indicating when and where the card was posted, and an
            additional publicity stamp promoting the Brighton and Hove Vintage Car Rally. The TEI
              <gi>stamp</gi> element is intended to contain descriptive text about any kind of
            stamp; where our description includes words actually appearing as part of the stamp we
            use the TEI <gi>mentioned</gi> element. In the case of the postmark, we have also
            distinguished the date given. Much of our research on an archive of such encodings will
            want to search and group cards reliably by the date on which they were posted. Dates as
            given in postmarks often use different formats and may be incomplete: we therefore add
            to the encoded date a normalised value, supplied on the <att>when</att> attribute.
            Finally, we have given the address to which the card was sent, simply dividing it up
            into lines. </p>
          <p>In a more detailed encoding we would probably distinguish the names of people and
            places, perhaps adding geographic co-ordinate information for the place names mentioned.
            We might wish to add some explanation of the little joke about <q>Wales</q>. We would
            probably want to distinguish the formulaic parts of the message, such as its opening and
            closing lines, from the content. And we would also consider how best to record the
            textual information printed on the back of the card ― the title and the name of its
            publisher for example. The scope of such metadata, which provides useful information
            about how the card was produced and used is very large and it is hard sometimes to know
            where to stop. For example, the yellow stain visible on the image suggests that this
            card was once attached to something by means of cheap adhesive tape. If this were a very
            rare historical artefact such evidence of provenance might be of considerable importance
            and would need to be encoded using (for example) the <gi>damage</gi> element. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>A minimally structured text</head>
          <p>Finally, if this all seems too much, we should note that the TEI can also support a
            very simple structural view in which all these conventional, semantically-charged,
            components such as paragraphs, speakers, verse lines, etc. are elided or ignored in
            favour of a neutral segmentation based on orthographically-defined sentences. In such a
            view, we might decide to keep the main divisions of the text, but then simply split it
            up into linguistically convenient segments at every appropriate punctuation mark, using
            the generic <gi>s</gi> (segment) and <gi>ab</gi> (anonymous block) elements. To reprise
            our first example: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <body xml:lang="en">
              <div type="section">
                <ab>
                  <s n="1">Introduction</s>
                  <s n="2">We recommend the use of TEI markup as a means of representing scientific
                    prose.</s>
                  <s n="3">It has a number of practical advantages:</s>
                  <s n="4">TEI markup is easy to add;</s>
                  <s n="5">TEI markup is widely understood;</s>
                  <s n="6">TEI markup is easy to convert to other formats.</s>
                  <s n="7">TEI markup also has some scientific advantages, which we discuss in
                    section <ptr target="#SEC3"/>.</s>
                </ab>
              </div>
            </body>
          </egXML>
          <p>Although such markup obviously lacks information present in the richer version we
            presented before, and is thus less generally useful, its simplicity and regularity means
            that it is much easier to process for such comparatively mechanical tasks as vocabulary
            analysis or linguistic enrichment. As ever, to get the best out of the TEI requires us
            to think carefully about our priorities before making our encoding decisions.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="compo">
          <head>Composites</head>
          <p>A TEI text may be <term>simple</term> (for example, a single book) or
              <term>composite</term> (for example a collection or anthology). In either case the
            main body of the text may be preceded or followed by additional distinct matter (title
            pages, prefaces, dedications, indexes etc.). The TEI proposes a mandatory element
              <gi>body</gi> for the main part of a text, and optional elements <gi>front</gi> and
              <gi>back</gi> to group additional matter preceding or following the body respectively.
            In a composite text, the <soCalled>body</soCalled> of the text is represented by a
              <term>group</term> element, which can contain multiple <gi>text</gi> elements, or
            groups of them, as in the following schematic:</p>

          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><TEI>
              <teiHeader>
                <!--[ header of a composite text ]-->
              </teiHeader>
              <text>
                <front>
                  <!--[ front matter for the composite text  ]-->
                </front>
                <group>
                  <text>
                    <front>
                      <!--[ front matter for the first text in the composite ]-->
                    </front>
                    <body>
                      <!--[ body  of the first text in the composite ]-->
                    </body>
                    <back>
                      <!--[ back matter for the first text in the composite ]-->
                    </back>
                  </text>
                  <text>
                    <front>
                      <!--[ front matter for the second text in the composite ]-->
                    </front>
                    <body>
                      <!--[ body  of the second text in the composite ]-->
                    </body>
                    <back>
                      <!--[ back matter for the second text in the composite ]-->
                    </back>
                  </text>
                  <!--[ more texts, simple or composite  ]-->
                </group>
                <back>
                  <!--[ back matter of the composite text  ]-->
                </back>
              </text>
            </TEI></egXML>
          <p>A structure like this would be appropriate for encoding a pre-existing anthology of
            verse by many authors but a single editor.</p>
          <p>In this model there is just one TEI Header for the whole of the composite text. The TEI
            also allows for a composite which represents a collection of documents originally
            distinct but put together by the encoder for some purpose: language corpora are typical
            examples. Each constituent document in a language corpus has its own metadata,
            represented by its own <gi>teiHeader</gi>, but there is an additional layer of metadata
            relating to the corpus as a whole. This is encoded in TEI using a structure like the
            following: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><teiCorpus><teiHeader>
                <!--[metadata relating to the whole corpus]--></teiHeader><TEI>
                <teiHeader><!--[metadata relating to the first text in the corpus]--></teiHeader>
                <text>
                  <!--[first text in the corpus]-->
                </text>
              </TEI><TEI>
                <teiHeader><!--[metadata relating to the second text in the corpus]--></teiHeader>
                <text>
                  <!--[second text in the corpus]-->
                </text>
              </TEI></teiCorpus></egXML>

          <p>A structure like this would be appropriate for encoding a newly-constructed collection
            of postcards or other independent textual objects. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="CORE">
        <head>The TEI cornucopia, part one</head>
        <p>In this and the following chapter we discuss and exemplify some of the elements defined
          by the full TEI. The elements discussed in the present chapter are likely to be useful in
          almost every kind of encoding project; those discussed in the next are more specialized.
          It should be emphasized that all we aim to do here is to give some sense of the rich
          variety offered by the TEI; for complete information the <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/P5">Guidelines</ref> should always be consulted. </p>
        <div xml:id="milestones">
          <head>Milestones</head>
          <p>We noted above that the TEI is most often used to represent the organization of a book
            into components such as chapters, paragraphs, etc. or of a poem into verses and stanzas.
            But books and printed poems also exist as physical objects, which are typically made up
            of pages with verso and recto surfaces. Why does the TEI not provide an element
              <gi>page</gi> to represent each page of a book? Surely it is at least as important to
            know on which page a sentence begins as it is to know that it is in the fifth paragraph
            of the second chapter of the ninth subsection of a work? Surely we would like to be able
            to display the text paginated on screen in the same way as it was paginated in the
            original source?</p>
          <p>The answer to these perfectly reasonable questions is perhaps surprisingly complex. In
            fact, the TEI does provide an element to mark up page boundaries (<gi>pb</gi>), but it
            is an empty element which should be placed at the beginning of the text transcribed from
            each page:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <body xml:lang="en">
              <pb n="42"/>
              <p>This paragraph begins on the page numbered 42... <!-- lots more text here -->
                <pb n="43"/>
                <!-- yet more text here --> ... and finishes half way down the page numbered 43.</p>
              <p>This much shorter paragraph begins and ends on page 43. </p>
            </body>
          </egXML>
          <p> A close study of the above example may help explain why a <gi>page</gi> element that
            actually encloses all the text on a page (rather than an empty <gi>pb</gi> which simply
            flags the beginning of a page) is not possible. In XML and similar markup languages, it
            is an absolute requirement that the elements defined by the markup tags should be
            properly nested one within another. If we start a <gi>page</gi> element, and then within
            it start a <gi>p</gi> element, the syntax of the language requires us to close that
              <gi>p</gi> before we can close the <gi>page</gi>, even though it is an observed fact
            of life that paragraphs frequently span across page boundaries. </p>
          <p>Users of XML (and before that SGML) have been trying to find better ways of
            representing textual structure without falling foul of this constraint for decades, and
            we don't intend to debate the <soCalled>overlap problem</soCalled> in any more detail
            here. We note simply that one well-established TEI way of addressing this problem takes
            the form of the <soCalled>milestone</soCalled> tags, of which <gi>pb</gi> is probably
            the most frequently encountered example. Whereas normal tags in an XML document mark
            explicitly both the start and the end of an element and thus always enclose something, a
            milestone tag marks simply a point at which something changes, but do not enclose
            anything. Milestone number 42 on the road from London to Bath marks the point at which
            the forty-second section of that road begins. We can guess that if we keep going we will
            eventually reach milestone number 43, which will mark the point at which the forty-third
            section starts, and hence (since a stretch of road cannot be in two sections at once)
            the point at which the forty-second section finishes, but it is not explicitly marked. </p>
          <p>The element <gi>lb</gi> (line break), <gi>cb</gi> (column break), and <gi>gb</gi>
            (gathering or folio break) are all milestones in this sense. In addition the TEI
            provides a generic <gi>milestone</gi> element which can be used to mark any kind of unit
            not otherwise provided for. As an example consider the practice (common in the 19th
            century) of publishing novels in serial form. We might wish to mark the boundary of the
            individual part issues, even though these do not necessarily fit well with the novel's
            internal organization as a series of chapters. (Dickens, for example, was not above
            closing a part issue with a mid-chapter <q>cliff-hanger</q>). A <tag>milestone
              unit='serialPart' n='12'/</tag> can be used to represent the point at which
              <q>serialPart</q> number 12 begins, independent of the structure of <gi>div</gi> and
              <gi>p</gi> elements used for the text itself.</p>
          <p>This generic element can be used for any kind of shift, of course, not simply
            structural units. A narratological analysis might be represented using
              <gi>milestone</gi> elements to mark points at which the narrative voice changes; a
            stylistic analysis might use them to mark points of stylistic variation. There are also
            other specific elements which behave in a milestone-like fashion for example to indicate
            changes of voice quality in transcribed speech, or changes of hand in transcribed
            manuscript. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Languages and writing systems</head>
          <p>Unless it is an empty milestone every element in a TEI document can contain one of
            plain text, <soCalled>element content</soCalled>, or (by far the most frequent case)
              <soCalled>mixed content</soCalled>. Plain text consists of encoded characters
            represented using the Unicode standard; element content consists of other XML elements;
            and mixed content combines the two. TEI elements and attributes are used to associate
            semantic and other properties with the content so that a processor can treat it
            correctly in a variety of situations. One particularly important property is the human
            language in which the textual content is expressed; another is the way the textual
            content is displayed or formatted. These properties are potentially important at almost
            every level: we might want to say that a whole document uses a specific language, or
            that just a few words here and there do; we might want to say that the whole of a
            document was typeset in a Roman font of a given size, and then indicate those parts of
            it which use some other font or size. Because such information is potentially applicable
            to every element, the TEI proposes <term>global attributes</term> to specify it.</p>
          <div>
            <head>Languages</head>
            <p>The global <att>xml:lang</att> attribute is the recommended means of specifying the
              human language in which the content of an element is expressed. (As the
                <code>xml:</code> prefix suggests, this attribute is common to all XML documents: it
              is not defined by the TEI but by the W3C, as part of the definition of XML.) Its value
              applies hierarchically to all the elements contained by that element, unless
              overridden:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <div xml:lang="la">
                <s>Pars haec lingua Latine composita est.</s>
                <s xml:lang="en">Except that this sentence is in English.</s>
                <s>Vita brevis, ars longa.</s>
              </div>
            </egXML>
            <p>Here we specify that the whole <gi>div</gi> element uses the language with the coded
              identifier <q>la</q> (The codes used are taken from ISO standard 639 for language
              identifiers) i.e. Latin. Since it is contained by that <gi>div</gi> there is no need
              to supply this information again for the first <gi>s</gi> element. The second
                <gi>s</gi> element however overrides this value, and indicates that its content is
              in English (the language with identifier <code>en</code>). The third <gi>s</gi>
              element is again in Latin. To find the language for any element's content, a processor
              must first look to see whether that element, or any of its parents, supplies a value
              for <att>xml:lang</att>. As you may suppose, the nearest parent is the one applicable,
              if there is more than one. Suppose, for example, that the second sentence above also
              contained a phrase in French. Such a phrase will need to be tagged with some element
              of course: the element <gi>foreign</gi> is provided for cases like this, where we
              simply want to show that some sequence of content uses a different language:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <div xml:lang="la">
                <s>Pars haec lingua Latine composita est.</s>
                <s xml:lang="en">Except that <foreign xml:lang="fr">sacrebleu</foreign> this
                  sentence is in English.</s>
                <s>Vita brevis, ars longa.</s>
              </div>
            </egXML>
            <p>The codes used to identify language may (as here) be standard two-letter codes; more
              complex codes can be used to distinguish such things as geographically or
              socially-defined variants, or to distinguish the same language written using different
              scripts. These codes, and ways of using them, are defined by the ISO rather than the
              TEI, and we do not discuss them further. <!--See further CH and HD.--></p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Nonstandard characters</head>
            <p>We noted above that a TEI document is an XML document, and therefore expressed using
              Unicode characters. The Unicode standard at the time of writing covers a very high
              proportion of existing and ancient writing systems, but quite properly does not
              attempt to standardize writing systems still in the course of being studied or
              defined, nor does it attempt to provide codes for every possible character or glyph
              variant likely to be encountered in the study of ancient documents. For these reasons,
              the TEI provides an element <gi>g</gi> which can be used to mark the presence in a
              document of some character or glyph for which there is no existing standard Unicode
              codepoint.</p>
            <p>Suppose for example that we are studying a range of manuscripts characterized by a
              particularly striking variant form of some letter (say an R); our TEI transcriptions
              can distinguish this variant glyph from the usual form of the same letter by using a
                <gi>g</gi> element to mark the former. The content of the <gi>g</gi> might simply be
              a normalised form, or the element might be empty; in either case it will carry a
                <att>ref</att> attribute which points to a <gi>glyph</gi> element somewhere, in
              which we define the nature, function, appearance, name etc. of this variation. Thus,
              supposing that we have identified and described three variant forms of the letter R,
              giving them codes R1, R2, R3, we might represent individual occurrences of these forms
              as <tag>g ref='#R1'/</tag>, <tag>g ref='#R2'/</tag> or <tag>g ref='#R3'/</tag>. The
              associated definitions may be provided within the<gi>charsDecl</gi> element of the TEI
              Header, as further discussed in <ptr target="#HDR"/> below. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="rend">
          <head>Rendition</head>
          <p>The term <term>rendition</term> is used in a TEI context to describe the way in which
            an element is formatted or presented, on screen or on the page. The TEI is not a
            document formatting system, and (as we suggested above) generally aims to facilitate an
            encoding which is faithful to the perceived meaning of a text rather than one which
            reproduces its appearance, or intended appearance. This is one of many aspects which
            distinguish the TEI from systems such as those typically used for word processing, as we
            noted above. Nevertheless, recognizing that it may be important to retain information
            about the original rendition of a document for analytic purposes (not least because it
            may be that its appearance is all we can reliably describe in an ancient document), the
            TEI provides a number of mechanisms for encoding such data. We emphasize again that the
            function of such renditional markup is always to describe the appearance or rendition of
            one or more original source documents; of course, it is likely that when displaying a
            text encoded in such a manner we will wish to achieve a similar appearance using
            different technology, but this is by no means always or necessarily the case. </p>
          <p>The simplest method is to use the global attribute <att>rend</att>. This attribute
            behaves in a way similar to the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute discussed above: it
            supplies a coded value for the rendition associated with an element and (unless
            overridden) its children. Unlike <att>xml:lang</att> however, the values available for
            use with the <att>rend</att> attribute are not formally defined, either by the TEI or
            any other agency, although a comparatively small number of codes are conventionally
            used. The encoder is free to make up their own set of labels and to apply them as
            consistently (or inconsistently) as they wish. </p>
          <p>The <att>rendition</att> attribute, by contrast, behaves more like the <att>ref</att>
            attribute on <gi>g</gi> in that it references a definition (or set of definitions)
            provided elsewhere; the encoder is thus constrained both to use only a specified set of
            renditional labels and also to supply (or refer to) some kind of definition of the
            intended meanings for each such label. </p>
          <p>Such <q>style definitions</q> are of course most easily expressed using an encoding
            language designed for formatting software, such as a web browser or document processing
            system. The TEI allows you to express your definitions in whatever such language you
            choose; currently a well established W3C recommendation called CSS (Cascading
            Stylesheets) is the most practical, since it is both powerful and very widely
            implemented. The syntax of this language is very simple and it can even be used directly
            within a TEI document, either to provide a default rendition for an element, or to
            override that default using yet another global attribute: <att>style</att>. </p>
          <p>We show how each of these methods might be used to encode the following brief passage,
            taken from an early 17th century schoolbook.</p>
          <figure>
            <graphic url="sample.png"/>
            <head>Extract from Henry Care's <title>The tutor to true English</title> (1687), p
              70</head>
          </figure>
          <p>In this passage, we observe sequences of words in a gothic or black letter font, in a
            normal roman font, and in italics. We can speculate about the reasons for this
            typographic variation, but supposing that at least initially all we want to do is record
            it, we might adopt a encoding like the following:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p rend="roman"><lb/>And here note, for a Caution against <hi rend="italic">Extrava-<lb
                  break="no"/>gance</hi>, and for encouragement to <hi rend="italic">Frugality</hi>
              and <lb/>good Husbandry in all People, especially <hi rend="italic">Youth</hi>,</p>
            <p rend="gothic"><lb/>That <hi rend="roman">every Penny</hi> any Person spends
              <lb/>idly, would purchase a <hi rend="roman">Yard</hi> (that is three <lb/>foot)
              square, and somewhat above, of as <hi rend="roman">
                <lb/>good Land</hi> as most in England, to <hi rend="roman">him <lb/>and his Heirs
                for ever.</hi></p>
          </egXML>
          <p>This encoding uses the milestone <gi>lb</gi> element to mark explicitly the start of
            typographic lines. It also uses a new element <gi>hi</gi> (short for
            <q>highlighted</q>). This element has no particular semantics ― it simply indicates that
            its content is visually distinct from what surrounds it, in rather the same way that
              <gi>foreign</gi> simply shows that its contents are linguistically distinct from what
            surrounds it. The nature of this visual distinction is not fully specified since this
            encoding does not explain what the values <val>roman</val>, <val>italic</val> or
              <val>gothic</val> mean; nor is there any way of providing such an explanation other
            than a documentary note. Of course, a human reader will know more or less what
              <q>italic</q> means, but a rendering program will probably not. Suppose instead that
            we have provided definitions (expressed in CSS) in the place in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>
            allocated for this purpose:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <rendition xml:id="it" scheme="css">font-family: roman; font-style: italic</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="ro" scheme="css">font-family: roman; font-style: normal</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="go" scheme="css">font-family: unifraktur cursive</rendition>
          </egXML>
          <p>With these definitions in place, we could now simplify our example slightly:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p rendition="#go">That <hi rendition="#ro">every Penny</hi> any Person spends idly
              ...</p>
          </egXML>
          <p>Any rendering program can now process the CSS directly and display our text in a
            visually distinctive manner. </p>
          <p>Moreover, since the CSS expressions are actually quite simple, we might just use the
              <att>style</att> attribute to provide them directly within our text:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p style="font-family: roman">And here note, for a Caution against <hi
                style="font-style:italic">Extravagance</hi>, and for encouragement to <hi
                style="font-style:italic">Frugality</hi> ...</p>
          </egXML>
          <p>As we noted above, the <gi>hi</gi> element has no semantics other than to indicate that
            some part of the document being encoded looks significantly different in some respect.
            In large scale encoding projects identifying such variation may be all that is feasible;
            in projects working with very ancient, visually complex, or scarcely comprehensible
            resources, it may also be very hard to go beyond the point of saying <q>this part of the
              text is visually distinct in some way</q>. But for the vast majority of TEI encoding
            projects it is usually considered both desirable and feasible to add value to an
            encoding by pausing to consider <emph>why</emph> something is visually distinct in the
            source. Where an answer to that question can be reached with any degree of confidence,
            an encoding which shows us what motivated the original renditional decision is more
            likely to be generally useful than one that does not. </p>
          <p>It is not so difficult to list the main reasons why a printer might choose to highlight
            some words in a text printed according to the conventions elaborated in Western Europe
            over the last 300 years or so. Words in a foreign language are almost always
            highlighted, as are words on which the author places some degree of linguistic emphasis.
            Titles and technical terms are conventionally identified by highlighting when they
            appear in running prose. Until recently, words indicating the names of persons, places,
            or abstractions would conventionally be highlighted as well. </p>
          <p>Note that we use the word <term>highlighted</term> here to include any form of visual
            salience, whether it is a passage in italic embedded in one predominantly set in roman
            font, or the reverse, or (as above) a passage in roman embedded in one predominantly in
            gothic. If we extend the meaning of the term to include passages set off by quotation
            marks of various kinds, the list of motivations for highlighting expands to include
            passages of direct speech, material cited or quoted from elsewhere, or which the writer
            wishes to indicate as being in some sense non-authorial, words which are being talked
            about rather than used... and so on and so forth. </p>
          <p>The TEI provides elements which enable the encoder to make all these and other semantic
            distinctions within the simple words of a text, guided by the visual clues implicit in
            the original rendition of a document, and the encoder's understanding of it. This is
            often a useful way of distinguishing an otherwise ambiguous passage of text. In a modern
            journal article, for example, a passage set in italic might be a foreign expression, the
            title of another article or of a film or song, a technical term, or a phrase the author
            wishes to emphasize. By using the appropriate tag (<gi>foreign</gi>, <gi>title</gi>,
              <gi>term</gi>, or <gi>emph</gi> respectively), the encoder enriches the text and
            facilitates more intelligent processing of it, for example to list the titles of works
            mentioned in a document, excluding emphasized or foreign words. </p>
          <p>These tags can also be used even when no highlighting has been applied, of course. The
              <att>rend</att> attribute is also available on all these elements, so that the encoder
            can say both what they believe a highlighted passage to indicate, and in what respects
            (if any) it is visually salient. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Names and dates</head>
          <p>We mentioned above the convention of highlighting the names of persons places, etc. in
            printed text. This practice, which was commonplace till the mid 19th century, testifies
            to a long standing desire on the part of readers to distinguish names clearly from other
            words, and it is one which remains true of modern day digital encoders. Identifying what
            are now often referred to as <q>named entities</q> from the rest of a sea of words is
            just as important a task for today's computational linguist building a language
            understanding system, or today's digital historian tracing social networks within a
            corpus of 18th century correspondence, as it is for today's intelligence operative
            trying to tracking down references to terrorist suspects in vast bodies of surveillance
            data. </p>
          <p>The TEI provides several elements to encode such things once they have been identified.
            Probably the most general-purpose of these is <gi>rs</gi> (short for <q>referring
              string</q>) which can be used to tag any sequence of words considered by the encoder
            to refer to some entity such as a person or place, even if the reference does not take
            the form of a name, but is rather a pronominal reference (<q>she</q>, <q>the king</q>)
            or deictic phrase (<q>that girl</q>, <q>the chap we saw on Thursday</q>), or idiom
              (<q>the great wen</q>, <q>the big apple</q>). When however a reference of this kind
            contains only one or more proper nouns, it should be encoded using the generic
              <gi>name</gi> element. </p>
          <p>Both <gi>rs</gi> and <gi>name</gi> elements have a <att>type</att> attribute which can
            be used to distinguish the type of entity being named, so that, for example. the place
              <code>&lt;name type="place"&gt;London&lt;/name&gt;</code> is distinguishable from the
            author <code>&lt;name type="person" &gt;London&lt;/name&gt;</code>. However, the TEI
            also provides specialised tags which enable you to make the same distinction, and
            others, with more precision. These more specialised elements distinguish names which
            refer to different kinds of entity explicitly: thus it provides <gi>persName</gi>,
              <gi>placeName</gi>, <gi>orgName</gi>, to support the assertion that the name refers to
            a person, place or organization. It is also possible to identify significant
            subcomponents of such names: the TEI provides <gi>surname</gi>, <gi>foreName</gi>,
              <gi>altName</gi> (for an alternative name such as a nickname), <gi>roleName</gi> (for
            a socially-defined role or title such as <q>Lady</q>, <q>Esquire</q>, <q>Preacher</q>,
            etc.), <gi>genName</gi> (for a generational name such as <q>Junior</q>, <q>the
            elder</q>, etc.) and others. For place names, the TEI distinguishes components placing
            the name socio-politically such as <gi>settlement</gi>, <gi>region</gi>,
              <gi>country</gi> and also components such as <gi>geogName</gi> for any purely
            geographic name such as <q>Mount Sinai</q> or <q>River Thames</q>, which can also be
            further decomposed into a name (<q>Thames</q>, <q>Sinai</q>) and the name of some kind
            of geographic feature (<q>Mount</q>, <q>River</q>). </p>
          <p>These elements are particularly useful when dealing with archival documents of any
            kind, in which indexing the names of people and places referred to in a document is a
            major concern, but they may be useful in any kind of digital edition or lexical
            study.</p>
          <p>Suppose, for example, that we are preparing a digital edition of a primary document
            such as the <title>Current Record of Events from 1792 to 1885, As recorded by The Shaker
              community of Canterbury, New Hampshire</title> (a manuscript preserved in the Special
            Collections of Hamilton College Library). This 19th c. document begins with the
            following sentence: <q>On the first of February 1792 Father Job Bishop and Elder Edmond
              Lougee came from New Lebanon N.Y. to organize and establish a community of Believers
              at Canterbury N.H.</q>. </p>
          <p>We might be content simply to record the presence of the proper names (<q>Father Job
              Bishop</q>, <q>Canterbury</q> etc.) using the <gi>name</gi> element as follows: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p>On the first of February 1792 <name>Father Job Bishop</name> and <name>Elder Edmond
                Lougee</name> came from <name>New Lebanon, N.Y.</name> to organize and establish a
              Community of Believers at <name>Canterbury, N.H.</name></p>
          </egXML>
          <p>Even this minimal tagging makes it easy to distinguish the names of the people and
            places mentioned, and hence to process them separately from the rest of the text, for
            example to construct an index of names, or to link these references to further
            information about the person or place concerned.</p>
          <p>A more careful tagging would however distinguish the component parts of the names which
            (as is often the case) combine family names (<q>Bishop</q>, <q>Lougee</q>) with names
            indicating a social role (<q>Father</q>, <q>Elder</q>) and with forenames (<q>Job</q>,
              <q>Edmond</q>). Such distinctions can only be made explicit by proper tagging ―
              <q>Bishop</q> might be a role or a surname, depending on context. Similarly, within a
              <gi>placeName</gi> it is convenient to distinguish the name of an administrative or
            other region such as a US state from the name of a <term>settlement</term> (TEI uses
            this neutral term in preference to other terms such as <q>town</q>, <q>village</q>,
              <q>city</q> etc. which are hard to define outside a very precise context).</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p>On the first of February 1792 <persName><roleName>Father</roleName>
                <forename>Job</forename>
                <surname>Bishop</surname></persName> and <persName><roleName>Elder</roleName>
                <forename>Edmond</forename>
                <surname>Lougee</surname></persName> came from <placeName><settlement>New
                  Lebanon</settlement>
                <region>N.Y.</region></placeName> to organize and establish a Community of Believers
              at <placeName><settlement>Canterbury</settlement>,
              <region>N.H.</region></placeName></p>
          </egXML>
          <p>By definition, a name refers to a specific entity (a person or place) but historical or
            genealogical research would not be much of a challenge if it did so unambiguously or
            directly. Is this <q>Edmond Lougee</q> the same person as the <q>Edmund Lougee</q>
            recorded in other sources? A little further in the source, there is a mention of
              <q>Elder Lougee</q>: does this refer to the same person? As ever, TEI cannot help you
            answer such questions, but it does provide ways of expressing the answer (if any) you
            have reached. </p>
          <p>Proposing a standardised form for a name has, of course, long been the business of
            librarians and cataloguers. For literary works and persons, and for modern or classical
            geographies, there exist well-established reference works or <soCalled>authority
              files</soCalled> which provide a useful point of reference for many of the entities
            that may be named in a TEI document; for others, we may find some kind of canonical
            information in other online references such as wikipedia or ancestry.com. One way of
            making clear which of the many possible people which we believe this <q>Edmond
              Lougee</q> concerns would therefore be to provide a reference to an online definitive
            record for the person : </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> ... <persName
              ref="http://records.ancestry.co.uk/Edmund_Lougee_records.ashx?pid=24762763"> Elder
              Edmond Lougee </persName> ... </egXML>
          <p> However, given that few of the people in an archival document of this kind are likely
            to have such records, it will often be necessary for a project to define their own
            authority file, comprising a series of records, one for each identified individual. The
            TEI provides additional elements which can be used to record such information in some
            considerable detail: biographical or prosopographical information for example can be
            grouped within a <gi>person</gi> element, while geographical information can be grouped
            within a <gi>place</gi> element; if this is done, then the <att>ref</att> attribute can
            be used to point to such a description: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <persName ref="#P1234"> Elder Edmond Lougee </persName>
            <!-- .... -->
            <person xml:id="P1234">
              <p>Edmund or Edmond Lougee was born in Exeter Newmarket, Rockingham, New Hampshire,
                USA on 1731 to John Lougee and Anne Gilman. He married Hannah Lord and had 7
                children. He passed away on 3 Jun 1807 in Loudon, New Hampshire, USA.</p>
            </person>
          </egXML>
          <p>Note that this example simply provides a prose summary of the available information for
            Elder Lougee within the referenced <gi>person</gi> element; it might alternatively have
            been constructed using specialised elements such as <gi>birth</gi>, <gi>death</gi>,
              <gi>marriage</gi>, <gi>relation</gi> etc. </p>
          <p>It may however be sufficient for the needs of a project to provide with each reference
            an arbitrary code, or a normalised form of the name, perhaps including dates or a
            generational marker to make that form unambiguous. The <att>key</att> attribute is
            provided for this purpose: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <persName key="Lougee, Edmond (1731-1807)"> Elder Edmond Lougee </persName>
          </egXML>
          <p>Normalisation by means of attribute values is a mechanism found throughout the TEI. It
            is particularly useful wherever something that a search engine or other processor would
            prefer to find in one particular format actually appears in a document in many different
            forms, some of which may have some linguistic interest or significance. If we want to
            recover from this document all references to events occurring before or after a
            particular date, for example, the task will be much easier if the dates all use a
            standard representation. In the above example, we might therefore choose to encode the
            first date as follows: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p>On <date when="1792-02-01">the first of February 1792</date> ... </p>
          </egXML>
          <p>using the W3C recommendation for the format of dates. The <att>when</att> attribute
            used here allows us to associate a date with a specific point in time. The TEI also
            provides a set of other attributes which can be used in combination to express a variety
            of temporal concepts: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p><date notAfter="1792-02-28" notBefore="1792-02-01">In February 1792</date> ... </p>
          </egXML>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p><date from="1792-02-01" to="1792-02-07">During the first week of February 1792</date>
              ... </p>
          </egXML>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Tables, figures, and bibliographies</head>
          <p>Documents in the real world contain many non-textual or only semi-textual components
            such as figures or tables, as well as textual components that have their own internal
            structure such as indexes and bibliographies. Particularly where the TEI is used to
            encode a new document, but also where there is a need to indicate the presence of such
            features in an old one, the encoder cannot do without elements such as <gi>table</gi>,
              <gi>figure</gi>, or <gi>bibl</gi>, each of which we introduce very briefly in the
            following sections.</p>
          <div>
            <head>Tables</head>
            <p>A table is a way of organizing several related snippets of textual information into
              rows (or columns) composed of cells. Most document production systems have developed
              quite complex ways of indicating exactly how the cells of a table should be displayed,
              but these are largely missing from the TEI table model. In the TEI, a <gi>table</gi>
              element is composed of <gi>row</gi>s, which are composed of <gi>cell</gi>s; a TEI
              table cannot therefore easily be represented as a series of columns. There is an
              attribute <att>role</att> to indicate whether a particular row or cell contains
              labelling information or data, and there are attributes <att>rows</att> and
                <att>cols</att> which can be used to indicate when a row or a cell spans more than
              one row or column respectively.</p>
            <p>Suppose we find the following (imaginary) table in a document we are encoding: <figure>
                <graphic url="table.png"/>
                <head>An imaginary table</head>
              </figure> In our TEI version, we can record that the first column of cells supplies a
              label for the entries in the remainder of each row, and also that the cell in the
              third column of the first row spans two columns. </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <table>
                <row>
                  <cell role="label">Fruit</cell>
                  <cell>apple</cell>
                  <cell>banana</cell>
                  <cell cols="2">cherry</cell>
                  <cell>date</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell role="label">Nuts</cell>
                  <cell>almond</cell>
                  <cell>brazil</cell>
                  <cell>coconut</cell>
                  <cell>doughnut</cell>
                  <cell>pistachio</cell>
                </row>
              </table>
            </egXML>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Figures</head>
            <p>Any kind of graphic component such as an illustration, chart, or diagram may be
              embedded within a document, sometimes as a separate component such as a frontispiece
              or separately paginated illustration, sometimes as a part of some division of the
              text. Such figures often contain headings or titles, possibly associated with some
              running text, as well as an image. To encode them, the TEI provides a <gi>figure</gi>
              element which typically contains at least <gi>graphic</gi> and one or more
                <gi>head</gi> elements, though other textual elements may be used as well if the
              illustration contains text.</p>
            <p>The <gi>graphic</gi> element is a specialised kind of pointer. Its <att>url</att>
              attribute points to a location where a digital representation of the image concerned
              may be found. Attributes <att>scale</att>, <att>width</att> or <att>height</att> are
              available to specify the desired size of the image when it is displayed. </p>
            <p>Consider the following example taken from <title>Punch</title>, a well known 19th
              century British humorous publication:</p>
            <figure>
              <graphic url="punch.png" width="90%"/>
              <head>John Leech: <title>Domestic Bliss</title>,cartoon in Punch vol 13 (July 1847),
                page 14.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>We may encode this as follows: </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <figure type="cartoon" place="topLeft">
                <head rend="caps">Domestic Bliss</head>
                <graphic url="vol13p14.png"/>
                <sp>
                  <speaker rend="italic">Wife of your bussum</speaker>
                  <p rend="smallcaps"><q>Oh! I don't want to interrupt you dear. I only want some
                      money for Baby's socks — and to know whether you will have the mutton cold or
                      hashed.</q></p>
                </sp>
                <figDesc>A domestic interior drawn by Leech, showing a wild-haired man in a dressing
                  gown sitting at a desk covered in papers, with his wife, two small children, one
                  of them banging a drum, and a cat. </figDesc>
              </figure>
            </egXML>

            <p>In our encoding we have transcribed the text below the graphic using the <gi>sp</gi>
              element discussed earlier, to show that the text is presented as a piece of dramatic
              dialogue. We have also used the <gi>figDesc</gi> element to enclose additional text,
              not present in the figure, but supplying useful descriptive metadata which might be
              displayed as an alternative to the graphic itself, or used to index its content. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Bibliographic descriptions</head>
            <p>Bibliographic descriptions, such as would usually be included as a bibliography or
              list of references at the end of an academic article, or in a footnote, are a common
              feature of scientific writing. It is useful to distinguish explicitly such items and
              in particular their components (author, title, publisher, publication date, etc.) both
              to make them more accurately searchable and to make it easier to render or format them
              in different ways. Where large numbers of such references are to be handled,
              specialist tools such as Zotero which can import or export in a TEI format provide an
              efficient way of maintaining them, but they can be treated in just the same way as any
              other component of a TEI document whether they appear in the body of the text, as a
              separate division of the back matter, or in the header. </p>
            <p>It is conventional practice in scientific writing to provide references in a standard
              format, in which the components appear in a specified order, and use consistent
              layout. Whether in a footnote, or in a standalone list of references, a book will
              typically be described something like this:</p>
        <quote rend="block">Cameron, D. (1995) <hi rend="italic">Verbal Hygiene.</hi> London
                and New York: Routledge. </quote>
            <p>TEI markup can be used to show which part of this is the title, which the place of
              publication, etc. The TEI provides two distinct elements for this purpose:
                <gi>biblStruct</gi> and <gi>bibl</gi>. </p>
            <p>The <gi>biblStruct</gi> element provides a <soCalled>structured</soCalled> or
                <term>data-centred</term> view of a bibliographic item, in which each part of the
              description (author, title, etc.) is tagged distinctly, treating it as if it were part
              of a database. Note that punctuation between the components is not allowed between
              components: this is because different visualisations might be appropriate for
              different bibliographic styles. A detailed tagging like the following allows this to
              be done simply: the formatting program simply chooses the elements needed in the order
              required, inserting punctuation according to the style required. </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <biblStruct xml:id="Cameron1995">
                <monogr>
                  <author><surname>Cameron</surname><forename>Deborah</forename></author>
                  <title>Verbal Hygiene</title>
                  <imprint>
                    <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    <date>1995</date>
                  </imprint>
                </monogr>
              </biblStruct>
            </egXML>
            <p>The <gi>monogr</gi> element here indicates that this is what bibliographers call a
                <term>monographic</term> item, that is an individual work, rather than an
                <term>analytic</term> item such as an article in a journal. </p>
            <p>The <gi>bibl</gi> element provides a less structured, more <term>text-centred</term>,
              view of a bibliographic item, in which punctuation is permitted between tagged items,
              along with any running prose found, and the order of the components is not fixed. It
              is useful where the encoder wishes to follow the conventions of the (usually printed)
              catalogue from which such a description is taken or for which it is intended.</p>
            <p>Using this, we might tag this item in a way that more closely resembles the original
              version, at the price of making its subsequent processing a little more difficult: </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <bibl><author>Deborah Cameron</author>: <title level="m">Verbal Hygiene.</title>.
                London, New York: Routledge.<date>1995</date></bibl></egXML>

            <p>Most of the elements available within <gi>biblStruct</gi> are also available (but
              optional) within <gi>bibl</gi>, so it is possible to use either element to provide
              detailed tagging of any kind of bibliographic citation. We give some further examples
              in section <ptr target="#HDR"/> below. </p>
            <p>When a book is mentioned within running text, particularly if it is mentioned more
              than once, it is usual to do so by means of a very short reference such as
                <mentioned>Cameron 1995</mentioned>. To link such a reference to a fuller
              bibliographic description of the work in question we can use the <att>target</att>
              attribute on a <gi>ref</gi> or <gi>ptr</gi> element: </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <p>Humans have <q>a healthy obsession with language</q> (<ref target="#Cameron1995"
                  >Cameron 1995</ref>). It would be surprising if we did not...</p>
            </egXML>

          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xml:id="TOPS">
        <head>The TEI cornucopia, part two</head>
        <div>
          <head>Editorial matters</head>
          <p>When digitization of some primary source materials is undertaken, the first priority is
            usually to produce good quality digital images of the original source documents.
            Transcribing and encoding those images is an expensive and difficult operation which
            cannot readily be automated, if at all, but it is an important next step in the creation
            of a true <soCalled>digital edition</soCalled>. For the skilled human reader, the
            digital image of its pages may be all that is needed to make the source useful. For a
            wider audience however, and certainly for any kind of automated analysis or searching,
            an encoded transcription will be an essential complement to the image. The TEI provides
            a number of mechanisms to facilitate the production of digital editions of every
            kind.</p>
          <div>
            <head>Image and transcription</head>
            <p> We mentioned above the <gi>facsimile</gi> element which can be used to group and
              organize digital images in terms of the physical surfaces they represent (using the
                <gi>surface</gi> element) and the logical zones of interest within those surfaces
              (using the <gi>zone</gi> element). A <gi>facsimile</gi> may be all that a TEI document
              contains, or this may be complemented by a transcription. </p>
            <p>Where both facsimile and transcription are available, a global attribute
                <att>facs</att> may be used to link them, or parts of them, as appropriate. Suppose
              for example that we have a single leaf, with images of its two surfaces in two files
              called <ident>page1r.png</ident> and <ident>page1v.png</ident> respectively. We
              transcribe the two surfaces within a <gi>text</gi> element as usual, using <gi>pb</gi>
              to mark the points in the transcription that correspond with the start of each new
              page in the source. The resulting document might look like this: </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <facsimile>
                <surface xml:id="s1">
                  <graphic url="page1r.png"/>
                </surface>
                <surface xml:id="s2">
                  <graphic url="page1v.png"/>
                </surface>
              </facsimile>
              <text>
                <body>
                  <pb facs="#s1"/>
                  <!-- text transcribed from page 1 recto here -->
                  <pb facs="#s2"/>
                  <!-- text transcribed from page 1 verso here -->
                </body>
              </text>
            </egXML>
            <p>Note that associating the transcription with the surface rather than with the image
              file directly offers us the flexibility of adding further image files (of higher or
              lower resolution, for example) without perturbing the structure. </p>
            <p>The <att>facs</att> attribute used above is global, and can therefore be used to
              associate any part of a transcription with any part of a <gi>facsimile</gi>. We could
              for example link a few words in the transcription with that part of the image where
              they appear. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Editing a transcription</head>
            <p>When transcribing a source, particularly an ancient one, there is always a tension
              between the desire to represent faithfully the actual state of the document, and the
              desire to make that document comprehensible to a modern or untrained reader. The
              process of transcription necessarily involves a kind of normalization, in which the
              different written symbols (the glyphs) of a manuscript or an early print document are
              mapped on to the unambiguous codes of a modern character set. An encoding which tries
              to represent the words of a document produced according to norms different from our
              own, or to correct <q>self evident</q> errors in the copy text is thus almost
              inevitable. The TEI provides ways of marking stretches of text as having been
              normalized or corrected, by the encoder, whether or not we consider this to be
                <q>editing</q> in the traditional sense. </p>
            <p>We mentioned above that the TEI consciously places itself within the long western
              philological tradition concerned with the identification and recovery of text from
              scattered documentary witnesses. It is scarcely surprising therefore to find that it
              also provides facilities for the representation of such phenomena as scribal
              correction or alteration where these are manifest in a particular document, or for the
              representation of a collation of variant readings. Where pre-digital textual editors
              were necessarily concerned with the production of a single carefully considered and
              substantiated print version of a text, the economics of digital production have
              greatly facilitated the production of <soCalled>diplomatic</soCalled> digital or
              documentary editions, which claim to present objectively the facts of a given
              collection of documents in such a way that the reader may determine the plausibility
              of any accompanying <q>edited</q> version, or even derive such an edition for
              themselves. </p>
            <p>When transcribing a source text, the <gi>corr</gi> element can be used to enclose a
              part that has been corrected and the <gi>reg</gi> element a part that has been
              normalised. For the opposite case, the <gi>sic</gi> element may be used where
              something should have been corrected but has not; and the <gi>orig</gi> for cases
              where the original spelling has been retained even though it looks unfamiliar. For
              example, a modernized version of the Shakespeare sonnet shown above would probably
              begin </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <l>My Mistress' eyes are nothing like the sun,</l>
              <l>Coral is far more red than her lips red,</l>
              <l>If snow be white, why then her breasts are dun:</l>
              <l>If hairs be wires, black wires grow on her head:</l>
            </egXML>
            <p>Even in such a modernized version, a conscientious encoder wishing to show where they
              have departed from the original source may simply wrap the words <q>Mistress'</q>
              <q>sun</q> etc. with the <gi>reg</gi> element. More usually however an encoder will
              wish to retain the original orthography along with the modernized version, so that
              either is available for display. The <gi>choice</gi> element addresses this
              requirement:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <l>My <choice><reg>Mistress'</reg><orig>Mistres</orig></choice> eyes are nothing like
                the <choice><reg>sun</reg><orig>Sunne</orig></choice>,</l>
              <l><choice><reg>Coral</reg><orig>Curral</orig></choice> is far more red
                    <choice><reg>than</reg><orig>then</orig></choice> her lips red,</l>
            </egXML>
            <p> The <gi>choice</gi> element may be used wherever several different possible
              encodings are possible but only one of them may be chosen for a particular
              application. It is less appropriate in the case where there are many different
              possible witnesses, providing multiple readings all of which need to be taken into
              consideration. The TEI provides a more powerful and complex set of tags to mark up a
              traditional critical apparatus of this kind. The element <gi>app</gi> (apparatus) is
              used to mark the point of variation being considered; within this element, the encoder
              can supply a series of <gi>rdg</gi> (reading) elements, one for each variant reading
              identified. (If editorial policy permits, one of these readings may be considered as
              the <soCalled>primary</soCalled> or <soCalled>correct</soCalled> one, in which case it
              will be tagged using the <gi>lem</gi> element rather than as just another
              <gi>rdg</gi>.) The <gi>rdg</gi> element has a <att>wit</att> attribute which can be
              used to identify the witnesses in which the reading is question is attested. For
              example, the first line of Chaucer's <title>Wife of Bath's Tale</title> begins
                <q>Experience though noon Auctoritee...</q>, but its first word is spelled quite
              differently in three of the surviving manuscripts. Taken as a whole, such spelling
              variations provide useful evidence for the reconstruction of the history of the
              manuscript tradition in question, and our encoding therefore wishes to preserve them.
              We might do so as follows:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <l n="1">
                <app>
                  <rdg wit="#El #Hg">Experience</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
                  <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
                </app> though noon Auctoritee... </l>
            </egXML>
            <p>Here the values of the <att>wit</att> attribute identify the manuscripts in question:
              as the hash-sign indicates, they are actually links to items in a list of the
              manuscripts which were collated to produce this apparatus. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Encoding the writing process</head>
            <p>Our last example of the facilities offered by the TEI for working on the detailed
              transcription of primary source materials introduces a few of the elements needed to
              record the actual writing process, for example to record passages which have been
              deleted, added, corrected etc. whether by the author of a literary text or by a scribe
              copying out a manuscript. An analysis of such documentary modifications may be
              essential before a reading text can be presented, and is clearly of importance in the
              editorial process. </p>
            <p>The example is taken from the surviving authorial manuscript of a poem by the English
              writer Wilfred Owen, a part of which is shown here: </p>
            <figure>
              <graphic url="PHowen.png" width="90%"/>
              <head>Detail from <title>Dulce et decorum est</title> autograph manuscript in the
                English Faculty Library, Oxford University. </head>
            </figure>
            <p>Owen first wrote <q>Helping the worst amongst us</q>, but then deleted it, adding
                <q>Dragging the worst amongt us</q> over the top. In the same way, he revised the
              phrase <q>half-blind</q> by deleting the <q>half-</q> and adding <q>all</q> above it.
              In the last line, he started a word beginning <q>fif</q> before deleting it and
              writing the word <q>five-nines</q>. We can encode all of this as follows: </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <l>And towards our distant rest began to trudge,</l>
              <l><subst><del>Helping the worst amongst us</del>
                  <add>Dragging the worst amongt us</add>
                </subst>, who'd no boots </l>
              <l>But limped on, blood-shod. All went lame; <subst>
                  <del status="shortEnd">half-</del>
                  <add>all</add></subst> blind;</l>
              <l>Drunk with fatigue ; deaf even to the hoots</l>
              <l>Of tired, outstripped <del>fif</del> five-nines that dropped behind.</l>
            </egXML>
            <p>The tags <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> elements are used to enclose passages added or
              deleted respectively. Additional attributes are available such as <att>resp</att> to
              indicate responsibility for the modification, or <att>place</att> to indicate where in
              the text (for example, above or below the line) the modification has been made. Where
              the encoder wishes to assert that the addition and deletion make up a single editorial
              act of substitution, these elements can be combined within a <gi>subst</gi> element as
              shown above.</p>
            <p>A very careful examination of Owen's second modification shows that he really did
              write <q>amongt</q> rather than <q>amongst</q>, presumably in error. An equally
              careful editor wishing to restore the missing <q>s</q> might use the <gi>supplied</gi>
              element to indicate that they have done so:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <add>Dragging the worst among<supplied resp="#ED">s</supplied>t us</add>
            </egXML>
            <p>Here the <att>resp</att> attribute has been used to indicate that the <val>S</val>
              was not supplied by Owen but by someone else, specifically the person documented
              elsewhere by an element with the identifier <val>ED</val>. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Transcribed speech</head>
          <p>The digital medium stores and represents sound or video just as easily and effectively
            as it does images. Transcriptions of sound or video recordings may be used to complement
            them in the same way as they are used to complement page images. Whether automatically
            or manually produced, transcriptions of speech are of particular interest in many
            branches of linguistics; for example, in language acquisition studies, in studies of
            language variation, or of the relationship between speech and writing in both literate
            and pre-literate societies. The study of transcribed speech is also an essential
            component of sociological studies such as oral history.</p>
          <p> However, the units in which such analysis is carried out — in TEI terms, the component
            elements of a <gi>text</gi> which contains transcribed speech — are not universally
            agreed on, and may even be controversial. Another complicating factor is that the
            process of transcribing speech is technically difficult and often carried out with the
            aid of special-purpose software; this is a complication because most such software
            systems have a preference for using their own internal formats rather than an externally
            defined standard. </p>
          <p>Nevertheless, the TEI does propose a set of elements which may be useful for the
            detailed encoding of speech transcriptions, and which <ref target="#Schmidt2011">a
              recent article by Thomas Schmidt</ref> shows can be used as a kind of interlingua for
            existing alternative encoding methods.</p>
          <p>The TEI model is concerned with speech as a communicative system: it therefore proposes
            the explicit labelling of any part of a recorded sound which has a communicative
            function or effect. Events such as a bell ringing or an airplane flying overhead are
            therefore explicitly noted using the <gi>incident</gi> element. Spoken communication is
            effected using the voice, but not all voice effects are regarded as lexical, and not all
            communication is vocal: the TEI therefore provides an element <gi>vocal</gi> for
            non-lexical phenomena such as coughs or laughter as well as an element <gi>kinesic</gi>
            for non-lexical and non-vocalic phenomena such as gestures or facial expression. These
            elements are complemented with a small number of others concerned with what might be
            called the <q>rendition</q> of speech : notably <gi>pause</gi> and <gi>shift</gi>; the
            latter being used to indicate changes in voice quality (for example in loudness, pitch,
            or speed) and functions in a way very similar to the milestone elements introduced
            earlier. </p>
          <p>One of the more controversial notions in speech research is that of <q>turn</q> or
              <q>utterance</q>: the TEI proposes an element <gi>u</gi> which can be used to delimit
            a stretch of speech from a single speaker, without making any claim as to the status or
            discourse function of such a stretch. The element carries a <att>who</att> attribute
            which can be used to link it to another element providing information about the person
            speaking, in the same way as we have already seen for the <att>ref</att> attribute.</p>
          <p>For many kinds of linguistic analysis, the <gi>s</gi> element mentioned above may be a
            more useful way of organizing a transcription since it permits the encoder to categorize
            each segment independently of the utterance containing it, particularly since utterances
            may be much longer (or shorter) than the usual units of analysis. </p>
          <p>Here is a simplified example taken from the <ref target="http://www.natcorp.ox.ac.uk/"
              >British National Corpus</ref> (BNC) in which both <gi>s</gi> and <gi>u</gi> have been
            used to segment the transcribed speech signal: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <u who="#PS6P0">
              <s n="3">There ain't</s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6NY">
              <s n="4"><shift new="laughing"/>There is<shift/></s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6P0">
              <s n="5">Oh shut up</s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6NY">
              <s n="6">Ach you do get corners on boats</s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6P0">
              <s n="7">No</s>
              <s n="8">Boats are shaped like a bloody rugby ball shape type</s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6NY">
              <s n="9">No they ain't</s>
              <s n="10">One end is and the other one ain't <pause/> and it was a yacht <pause/> and
                a yacht they got little rooms in or something cos <unclear/> innit</s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6P0">
              <s n="11">Oh that<pause/> th the rooms are shaped ni <pause/> like to the size of the
                boat<pause/> you nonce <vocal desc="tut"/></s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6NY">
              <s n="12">Let's ask your Mum if there's <pause/> if there's any corners on a boat</s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6P0">
              <s n="13">Of course there ain't</s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6NY">
              <s n="14">Just ask your Mum that</s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6P0">
              <s n="15">Yeah</s>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6NY">
              <unclear/>
            </u>
            <u who="#PS6P0">
              <s n="16">I bet she'll probably side with you</s>
            </u>
          </egXML>
          <!-- BNC KSP -->
          <p>When transcribing speech, the transcriber must also make decisions about how to
            represent the non-standard or only semi-lexicalised sounds that speakers make, such as
              <q>hmmm</q>, or the <q>ach</q> or <q>tsk tsk</q> in the above example (in this case
            the decision has been to treat the former as a word and the latter as a <gi>vocal</gi>).
            Even when it is clear that the sound is lexical, it's not always clear how it should be
            spelled: for example, the sound represented above as <q>yeah</q> might equally well be
            spelled <q>yeh</q> or <q>yuh</q> or even <q>yes</q>. </p>
          <p>In language corpora of this kind it is also common practice to markup each word
            explicitly, often using the <gi>w</gi> element. Deciding how this tokenisation should be
            done is not always self-evident: in the BNC, for example, elided forms like <q>ain't</q>
            and <q>there's</q> are tagged as two <gi>w</gi> elements and additional tags are used to
            distinguish false starts or truncated forms like <q>th</q> and <q>ni</q> in the above
            example. The main use of such tagging is however to support additional information such
            as <q>part of speech</q> or <q>morphosyntactic</q> analyses, as described in section
              <ptr target="#ANA"/> below.</p>
          <p>There is one further important feature of the TEI model for transcribing speech:
            alignment. Whereas in an image the transcription has to be aligned within a
            two-dimensional co-ordinate space, within a time-based medium such as audio, the various
            parts of a transcription must be located within time. Speakers typically interrupt one
            another, or speak at the same time; understanding a dialogue is impossible without
            information about the sequence of events transcribed. The TEI proposes a way of
            explicitly recording a kind of temporal scale, using the element <gi>timeline</gi>,
            which contains definitions of points in time, represented as <gi>when</gi> elements.
            Events in a transcription taking place at a given point in time can then be aligned with
            the appropriate <gi>when</gi> elements using attributes such as <att>sync</att>
            (synchronous). The advantage of this method is that it permits a transcription to
            represent the minimum of information needed to align its components, without
            necessitating an accurate timestamp for each of them; such timestamping is however
            generally provided by an automatic transcription system and it may therefore be simpler
            to use that.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Dictionaries</head>
          <p>The TEI provides elements for the detailed encoding of only a few distinct kinds of
            document, preferring generally to define elements specific to particular kinds of
            analysis or approach. However, it does provide a set of tags for the markup of
            dictionaries and lexica, perhaps because historically these were amongst the first types
            of major reference work to be demonstrably better managed in digital form than in print. </p>
          <p>Dictionaries, particularly in print form, are unlike many kinds of document in that
            they are not composed of running text, but rather of discrete entries, within which
            individual and semantically significant subcomponents can readily be recognised, even
            though they may not always be presented as consistently as a database designer might
            wish. A dictionary entry always has a headword, followed typically by some linguistic
            information such as its part of speech, and by a series of sense definitions, often
            arranged hierarchically. Etymological information, examples of usage, references to
            homonyms, etc. may also be present. </p>
          <p>In a TEI-style encoding, all of these and other parts of an entry will be distinguished
            as clearly as possible, whether the purpose is to produce a new dictionary (in which
            these things must all be rendered in a consistent way), or to represent an existing one
            (in which distinguishing these things will improve the range of intelligent
            searching).</p>
          <p>As a first simple example, consider the following : <figure>
              <graphic url="johnson-apple.png" width="80%"/>
              <head><q>Apple</q> from Johnson's <title>Dictionary of the English
                Language</title>(1755)</head>
            </figure></p>
          <p>A minimal TEI encoding for this entry would distinguish the word form used as lemma,
            its spelling and grammatical coding, the etymology provided, and the two senses : </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <entry>
              <form type="lemma">
                <orth rend="ALLCAPS">A'PPLE</orth>. <gramGrp><pos norm="noun">n.s.</pos></gramGrp>
              </form>
              <etym>[<foreign xml:lang="ang">æppel</foreign>, <lang>Saxon</lang>.] </etym>
              <sense n="1">
                <def>The fruit of the apple tree.</def>
                <cit>
                  <quote type="verse">
                    <l>Tall thriving trees confess'd the fruitful mold;</l>
                    <l>The red'ning <hi>apple</hi> ripens here to gold.</l>
                  </quote>
                  <bibl>Pope's <title>Odyssey</title>.</bibl>
                </cit>
              </sense>
              <sense n="2">
                <def>The pupil of the eye.</def>
                <cit>
                  <quote> He instructed him; he kept him as the apple of his eye.</quote>
                  <bibl>Deut. xxxii. 10.</bibl>
                </cit>
              </sense>
            </entry>
          </egXML>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="NOTES">
          <head>Notes</head>
          <p>Texts, particularly old ones, are often accompanied by extensive annotation and
            commentary, either supplied by the original writer, or more usually by an editor or
            later commentator. All kinds of academic writing are also typified by footnotes,
            sidenotes, glosses, bibliographic references, etc. For all of these features, the most
            natural kind of tagging is to use a <gi>note</gi> element to contain the annotation
            itself, and to embed it within the text being annotated at the <soCalled>point of
              attachment</soCalled>, that is, the place where a footnote reference, or other mark
            typically appears in a printed text. Attributes on the <gi>note</gi> element can be used
            to categorize it in some way, to indicate its approximate placement, and to indicate who
            is responsible for it. </p>
          <p>In modern printing practice, explanatory annotations are usually moved off to the back
            of the book. For example, in a discussion of contemporary attitudes to linguists
            published in 1995, we find the following comment: <figure>
              <graphic url="cameron-1.png" width="80%"/>
              <head>Extract from Deborah Cameron's <title>Verbal Hygiene</title> (p 229)</head>
            </figure> The raised figure 6 here is an indication that the author has provided a
            further comment, which appears duly collected with others some 18 pages later on: <figure>
              <graphic url="cameron-2.png" width="80%"/>
              <head>Extract from Deborah Cameron's <title>Verbal Hygiene</title> (p 247)</head>
            </figure>. </p>
          <p>One simple way of encoding this would be as follows:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <div>
              <head>Beyond "anything goes"</head>
              <p> Why does the language-maven in the street (or the senior common-room, or the bar
                at the Groucho Club <note>An establishment patronized by media folk in London
                  (provided the club will have them as members).</note>) have such a low opinion of
                linguists? Because...</p>
            </div></egXML>

          <p>Here the note is encoded inline even though the printed source text has separated the
            notes out from the text. This makes it easier to present the note in a variety of ways
            (for example, as a pop up in an online version) and also for simplicity of encoding.
            However, it is also perfectly feasible to treat the notes as a separate section of the
            document, and to place explicit links in the text at the point of attachment, using the
              <gi>ptr</gi> element:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <div>
              <head>Beyond "anything goes"</head>
              <p> Why does the language-maven in the street (or the senior common-room, or the bar
                at the Groucho Club <ptr target="#note6"/>) have such a low opinion of linguists?
                Because...</p>
            </div>
            <back>
              <head>Notes</head>
              <!-- other notes here -->
              <note xml:id="note6">An establishment patronized by media folk in London (provided the
                club will have them as members).</note>
              <!-- and here -->
            </back>
          </egXML>
          <p>To represent the link between the text and the note, we first give the <gi>note</gi>
            element a unique identifier (<ident>note6</ident>) and we then place a <gi>ptr</gi>
            element at the point in the text from which we wish to refer to it (the "point of
            attachment"). This pointer element both represents the supralinear 6 in our original
            source indicates that its function is to point to the note whose identifier is supplied
            by its <att>target</att> attribute. Alternatively, if we care to record exactly the way
            the point of attachment appears in the text, we could use the <gi>ref</gi> element: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> ...the Groucho Club <ref target="#note6"
              >6</ref>) have ...</egXML>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="ANA">
          <head>Linguistic annotation</head>
          <p> In the course of preparing of an encoded text, there is a natural tendency for the
            encoder to wish to add their own annotations. In a sense, of course, every piece of
            markup added to a text represents the result of an analysis, whether human or automatic,
            and so it is natural to think of representing such annotations incrementally by means of
            markup to a digital text. The <gi>note</gi> element may be used for this purpose.
            However, for many people, linguistically motivated analyses (such as <q>this is a
              verb</q>, or <q>this sequence of words has this syntactic function</q>, or even
              <q>this is a metaphor</q>) are of a rather different kind from the kinds of annotation
              (<q>this is a title</q>, <q>this is a personal name</q>, etc.) discussed elsewhere in
            this book. In particular, there is less consensus about the categories involved: most
            people will readily agree that <soCalled>place name</soCalled> is a useful and definable
            concept, but the concepts behind linguistic analysis are much more various. The TEI does
            not, therefore, propose tags such as <gi>noun</gi> or <gi>adjunct</gi> or
              <gi>metaphor</gi>, but instead it proposes general purpose elements for segmenting
            texts into smaller units, any of which can carry labels defined by the project.</p>
          <p>This method is particularly useful when a digital text is automatically analysed by a
            computer program, (for example a morphosyntactic analyser, or part-of-speech tagger)
            since the format used for the outputs from such automated systems differ considerably.
            The TEI offers a simple way of explicitly segmenting running text into word-like units,
            and associating linguistic codes with each such segment. For example, like many other
            language corpora, the BNC provides codes identifying the part of speech (noun,
            adjective, verb etc.) of each word as well as its base or uninflected form. We might
            therefore represent the sentence quoted above in TEI as follows :</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="tiny">
            <u who="PS6NY">
              <s n="12">
                <w ana="#VM0" lemma="lets">Lets</w>
                <w ana="#VVI" lemma="ask">ask </w>
                <w ana="#DPS" lemma="you">your </w>
                <w ana="#NN1" lemma="mum">Mum </w>
                <w ana="#CJS" lemma="if">if </w>
                <w ana="#EX0" lemma="there">there</w>
                <w ana="#VBZ" lemma="be">'s</w>
                <w ana="#DT0" lemma="any">any </w>
                <w ana="#NN2" lemma="corner">corners </w>
                <w ana="#PRP" lemma="on">on </w>
                <w ana="#AT0" lemma="a">a </w>
                <w ana="#NN1" lemma="boat">boat</w>
                <pc>. </pc>
              </s>
            </u></egXML>

          <p>In this encoding (production of which is largely automated, of course) the <gi>w</gi>
            element has been used to delimit each lexical item. For each such unit, the attribute
              <att>ana</att> is used to point to a part of speech definition, and the attribute
              <att>lemma</att> to supply a base form. </p>
          <p>Linguistic analyses of this kind have been in use for many decades and are essential to
            most current systems used in Natural Language Processing (NLP). Consequently, both the
            techniques used and the categories represented are in the process of being standardised,
            at least for major Western European languages. The TEI approach allows the encoder to
            choose how much or how little they wish to make explicit the meaning of the analysis
            pointed to by the <att>ana</att> attribute: that is, how to define what <code>VBZ</code>
            or <code>NN1</code> actually means. </p>
          <p>One method is to provide a further definition for the category, typically within a TEI
            Header, using the <gi>taxonomy</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#encDesc"
            />. Such a definition will typically be meaningful only to a human being, but it can
            still be very useful to provide one. </p>
          <p>At the other extreme, categories may be formally defined using the joint TEI/ISO
            recommendations for representing linguistic analyses in terms of <term>feature
              structures</term> (see further <ref
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/FS.html">Chapter 18 of the
              TEI Guidelines</ref>). Such analyses are now used quite widely in the NLP community,
            for example as a means of mapping information between different computational lexica. </p>
          <p>Or, intermediate between the two, linguistic categorizations may be made with reference
            to an existing standard, such as that provided by the ISO Data Category Registry (see
            further <ref target="#ideromary">Ide and Romary 2009.</ref>). This approach has much in
            common with many other data harmonization efforts on the Web: it makes it simpler for
            systems to interoperate, in the same way as TEI documents in general can be
            interoperable. </p>
          <p> It is also worth noting that the same mechanisms are available for any kind of
            analysis, not necessarily a linguistic one; stylistic analyses (which typically
            characterize stretches of text larger than a single word) can also be encoded in much
            the same way, by attaching the <att>ana</att> attribute to whatever element is chosen to
            enclose the stretch of text concerned, for example a <gi>p</gi>, <gi>div</gi>,
              <gi>s</gi>, etc.</p>
          <p>Of course the units of text being analysed do not necessarily coincide with the units
            of text directly represented within the text. We mentioned one way of dealing with this
            common <soCalled>overlap problem</soCalled> in <ptr target="#milestones"/> above.
            Another is to use <soCalled>stand off</soCalled> markup, in which the units analysed are
            represented not by XML elements but by pointers. <ref
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/NH.html">Chapter 20 of the
              TEI Guidelines</ref> discusses these and other techniques in more detail. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="HDR">
        <head>The TEI Header</head>
        <p>Every TEI document must have a TEI Header, represented by a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element.
          This is a container for all the metadata associated with the digital document itself,
          analogous to the title page of a printed book. In digital libraries and other online
          repositories, it is customary for the metadata associated with each digital document to be
          stored or managed separately, for example in a database structure for reasons of
          efficiency; it is also common practice to expose a subset of such metadata to web search
          engines according to one or more common standards such as Dublin Core. The TEI Header
          element is provided as a way of storing all such information in one place, independent of
          how it may be used. Of course, the scope and quantity of data collected in the Header may
          vary considerably in documents prepared for different purposes or by different projects.
          Furthermore, at least as originally conceived, the content of a TEI Header may not
          necessarily conform to the highest or most precise of cataloguing standards. Nevertheless
          it serves a useful purpose as a place where (for example) the data creator and the data
          curator can share information. </p>
        <p>Originally, the TEI header was designed to suit two rather different requirements. On the
          one hand, it was intended to assist bibliographers and librarians faced with the (then)
          new problem of documenting ‘electronic books’; on the other it was intended to meet the
          needs of researchers working with digital text collections, and needing to document the
          ‘coding practices’ applied to them. For the researcher, the important thing about the
          Header is that it provides a place for everything, supporting as far as possible the full
          range of divergent practice in different research communities, without imposing such
          barriers as a detailed knowledge of cataloguing standards or practices. For the librarian,
          the important thing about the TEI Header is that it conforms to standard bibliographic
          models, using similar terminology, and that it provides a single source of information for
          bibliographic description of a digital resource, with some established mappings to other
          such records (such as MARC or EAD). There is (naturally) some tension between these two
          perspectives, and a need for the elaboration of detailed profiles or <soCalled>Guides to
            Best Practice</soCalled> for different communities. </p>
        <p> The TEI header has four main components, corresponding to the parts defined in one of
          the first attempts at a universal bibliographic description the International
          Bibliographic Standard Description (ISBD) :</p>
        <list>
            <item>
              <gi>fileDesc</gi> (file description) contains a full bibliographic description of an
              electronic file.</item>
            <item>
              <gi>encodingDesc</gi> (encoding description) documents the relationship between an
              electronic text and the source or sources from which it was derived.</item>
            <item>
              <gi>profileDesc</gi> (text-profile description) provides a detailed description of
              non-bibliographic aspects of a text, specifically the languages and sublanguages used,
              the situation in which it was produced, the participants and their setting. (just
              about everything not covered in the other header elements</item>
            <item>
              <gi>revisionDesc</gi> (revision description) summarizes the revision history for a
              file.</item>
          </list>
        
        <div>
          <head>The file description</head>
          <p>Since it is not (usually) a pre-existing document, the structure of a TEI Header can be
            fairly tightly prescribed by the TEI. The first and only mandatory part, known as the
            file description, is represented by a <gi>fileDesc</gi> element, which contains three
            mandatory parts the title statement, publication statement and source description. A
            minimal TEI Header thus looks something like this: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <teiHeader>
              <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                  <title>Title of the work</title>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                  <p>Information about the publication of the work</p>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                  <p>Information about the source from which the work was derived</p>
                </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
            </teiHeader>
          </egXML>
          <p>Within the four main sections of the TEI header, many elements are possible; we can
            give only a superficial overview here. For example, the <gi>fileDesc</gi> can also
            contain an <gi>editionStmt</gi> documenting the particular edition of the resource being
            described, a <gi>seriesStmt</gi> if it is published as part of a series, an
              <gi>extent</gi> element to indicate its size , and even a <gi>notesStmt</gi> to
            capture notes or comments of various types. </p>
          <p>The mandatory title statement, as its name suggests, provides a title for the resource,
            together with information about the people or agencies responsible for its intellectual
            content, in much the same way as the title of printed book, or a conventional catalogue
            record. For example: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <titleStmt>
              <title xml:lang="sk">Yogadarśanam (arthāt yogasūtrapūphah).</title>
              <title>The Yoga sūtras of Patañjali: a digital edition.</title>
              <author>Patañjali</author>
              <funder>Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine</funder>
              <principal>Dominik Wujastyk</principal>
              <respStmt>
                <name>Wieslaw Mical</name>
                <resp>data entry and proof correction</resp>
              </respStmt>
              <respStmt>
                <name>Jan Hajic</name>
                <resp>conversion to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
              </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
          </egXML>
          <p>In this example, the resource has two titles, one of which is given in Sanskrit.
            Details of its original author, the funder of the digital edition, the principal
            investigator, and other people with more specialized responsibilities are also provided.
            Many digital library projects will have their own rules about, for example, the format
            of names, or the use of authority lists to provide titles, which may vary considerably:
            the TEI therefore permits a more exact tagging of components such as proper names (for
            example by distinguishing forenames and surnames) but does not require it. </p>
          <p>The file description describes the <q>file</q> (i.e. the whole of a digital resource ―
            it may of course consist of several operating system files). The <term>publication
              statement</term> describes how this resource may be obtained, in much the same way as
            the imprint of a printed book suggests who is responsible for distributing or publishing
            it. Even if the TEI document is a private document which is not actually available
            anywhere beyond the owner's private hard disk, that fact must be mentioned here; more
            usually, of course, a header will be created only for a TEI resource which is being
            shared. The publication statement allows you to specify who is making the resource
            available, any identifier used for it, such as a catalogue number or Resource
            Identifier, and information about the terms under which it is distributed such as a
            licence, as shown here: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <publicationStmt>
              <publisher>Humanities Media and Computing center</publisher>
              <pubPlace>University of Victoria</pubPlace>
              <date when="2011-08-04">19 August 2011</date>
              <idno type="filename">maladies_des_femmes.xml</idno>
              <availability status="free">
                <p>Copyright 2011. This text is freely available provided the text is distributed
                  with the header information provided.</p>
                <p xml:lang="fr">Les droits de reproduction des gravures ont été achetés de la
                  Bibliothèque Nationale de France grâce à une subvention accordée par le <ref
                    target="http://www.sshrc-crsh.gc.ca/">Conseil de recherches en sciences humaines
                    du Canada</ref>. Les autres éléments du projet (les contributions des éditeurs,
                  les transcriptions des textes, l'encodage et le code) sont distribués sous les
                  termes de cette licence: <ref
                    target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.5/ca/deed.fr_CA">Creative
                    Commons Paternité - Pas d'Utilisation Commerciale - Pas de Modification 2.5
                    Canada</ref>.</p>
              </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
          </egXML>
          <p>This example shows a typical mixture of structured elements and informal prose. The
            name and address of the agency responsible for distribution of the file have been
            distinguished as <gi>publisher</gi> and <gi>pubPlace</gi> respectively (a more detailed
            address, using the <gi>address</gi> element we saw above, could also be used, of
            course); in addition a date of publication and a filename to identify the resource have
            been provided. Since the terms of availability here are a little complex, they have been
            presented informally as a sequence of paragraphs of prose, containing references to
            other online documents as appropriate. In a simpler situation, the TEI <gi>licence</gi>
            element might have been used. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Varieties of source description</head>
          <p>The next and only other mandatory component of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> is the source
            description, represented by the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element. Even for documents which
            are <q>born digital</q> and thus have no pre-existing source, this element must be
            provided. Its purpose is to document formally the object or objects from which the TEI
            document has been derived, using traditional bibliographic terms. The
              <gi>sourceDesc</gi> may contain a simple paragraph of description, or it may contain
            one or more of the specialised elements for bibliographic description provided by the
            TEI. </p>
          <p>As a first example, consider a document which has no form of existence beyond its
            digital version. We may represent this using a pared-down <gi>bibl</gi> : </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <sourceDesc>
              <bibl>
                <title>Manifeste des Digital humanities</title>. <author>Marin Dacos et al.</author>
                Available from <ref target="http://tcp.hypotheses.org/318"
                  >http://tcp.hypotheses.org/318</ref>
                <date when="2010-05-21"/>
              </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
          </egXML>
          <p>or simply give a short paragraph of explanation </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <sourceDesc>
              <p>No source: this is a born digital document.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
          </egXML>
          <p>It is often the case that a digital edition derives from a specific printed source.
            This may also be described using the <gi>bibl</gi> element: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><sourceDesc>
              <bibl xml:id="Sue1846">
                <author><surname>Sue</surname>, <forename>Eugène</forename></author>
                <title level="m">Martin, l’enfant trouvé : Mémoires d’un valet de chambre</title>
                <imprint>
                  <publisher>C. Muquardt</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Bruxelles</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>Leipzig</pubPlace>
                  <date when="1846">MDCCCXLVI</date>
                </imprint>
              </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
          </egXML>

          <p>For digital transcriptions of audio or video recordings, a specialised
              <gi>recordingStmt</gi> element should be used. This can be used to store any technical
            details of the recording itself, and also to store detailed biographical or sociological
            data about the participants in a transcribed dialogue.</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="tiny">
            <sourceDesc>
              <recordingStmt>
                <recording type="audio" dur="P30M">
                  <respStmt>
                    <resp>Location recording by</resp>
                    <name>Sound Services Ltd.</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <equipment>
                    <p>Multiple close microphones mixed down to stereo Digital Audio Tape, standard
                      play, 44.1 KHz sampling frequency</p>
                  </equipment>
                  <date>12 Jan 1987</date>
                </recording>
              </recordingStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
          </egXML>
          <p>For other non-book sources, such as the postcard mentioned above, the <gi>bibl</gi>
            element can also be used: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <sourceDesc>
              <bibl>
                <title level="m">The Bathing Beach, Brighton, in 1845 [postcard]</title>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp>Lithograph by</resp>
                  <name>G. F. Bragg</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                  <resp>after a drawing by</resp>
                  <name>R. H. Nibbs</name>
                </respStmt>
                <publisher>K. J. Bredon's Bookshop</publisher>
                <pubPlace>10 East Street, Brighton</pubPlace>
              </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
          </egXML>
          <p>For a digital edition of a manuscript or early print source, where it is important to
            record the characteristics of the specific copy being transcribed, the detailed elements
            proposed by the TEI for the descriptive cataloguing of manuscripts may be more
            appropriate. Such descriptions use a distinct element, the <gi>msDesc</gi> which has
            quite an elaborate internal structure, as the following example shows:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="tiny">
            <sourceDesc>
              <msDesc>
                <msIdentifier>
                  <country>France</country>
                  <settlement>Paris</settlement>
                  <repository>Archives nationales</repository>
                  <collection>Commerce et Industrie</collection>
                  <idno>F/12/5080</idno>
                </msIdentifier>
                <msContents>
                  <p>Minute d’un rapport de proposition à la Légion d’honneur fait, en 1850, par le
                    ministre du Commerce et de l’Agriculture et président de la Société de
                    géographie, Jean-Baptiste Dumas, au Président de la République, en faveur des
                    frères d’Abbadie, Antoine (1810-1897) et Arnaud (1815-1893), auteurs d’un voyage
                    en Abyssinie.</p>
                </msContents>
                <physDesc>
                  <p>Deux feuilles de papier 24 x 12 cm ; écriture à l’encre noire.</p>
                  <handDesc>
                    <handNote xml:id="AA" scope="major">Antoine d’Abbadie</handNote>
                    <handNote xml:id="DJB" scope="minor">Jean-Baptiste Dumas</handNote>
                    <handNote xml:id="EPR" scope="minor">membre inconnu du cabinet du
                      ministre</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                </physDesc>
              </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
          </egXML>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="encDesc">
          <head>The encoding description</head>
          <p>The second major division of the TEI Header is the <term>encoding description</term>,
            which is represented by an <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element. This optional element may be
            used to supply information about almost any aspect of the encoding process itself,
            either simply summarized as running text, or provided within more specific elements.
            Taken as a whole, the content of a full <gi>encodingDesc</gi> approximates to the kind
            of information typically found in a technical manual associated with a project.</p>
          <p>Some of its components are entirely documentary, for example: </p>
          <list>
              <item>
                <gi>projectDesc</gi>: notes on the overall goals of the project;</item>
              <item>
                <gi>samplingDecl</gi>: notes on the sampling principles applied;</item>
              <item><gi>editorialDecl</gi>: notes on the editorial principals applied, for which
                further specialised elements such as <gi>correction</gi>, <gi>normalization</gi>,
                  <gi>quotation</gi>, <gi>hyphenation</gi>, <gi>segmentation</gi>,
                  <gi>interpretation</gi> are provided.</item>
            </list>
          
          <p>Here is an example showing some of these elements in use:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <encodingDesc>
              <projectDesc>
                <p>Texts collected for use in the Claremont Shakespeare Clinic, June 1990.</p>
              </projectDesc>
              <samplingDecl>
                <p>Each text contains a sample of up to 2000 words, running from the start of the
                  document to the end of the sentence after the 2000 word mark. For the purposes of
                  word counting, hyphens and apostrophes were treated as spaces. </p>
              </samplingDecl>
              <editorialDecl>
                <normalization>
                  <p>Word forms broken by end of line hyphenation have been reconstructed without
                    comment. The hyphen has been removed except for hyphenated forms attested
                    elsewhere in the text. </p>
                </normalization>
                <quotation marks="all" form="std">
                  <p>All quotation marks have been removed. Direct speech is represented by the use
                    of the <gi>said</gi> tag; other quoted material is represented by means of the
                      <gi>q</gi> tag. </p>
                </quotation>
              </editorialDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
          </egXML>
          <p>Such documentation is of course useful only to a human reader. However, other
            components of the encoding description are intended for use by automated processes.
            Typically they provide a set of declarations for particular codes which are subsequently
            referenced or used in the body of the text. Examples include : </p>
          <list>
              <item><gi>charDecl</gi> : XML requires the use of Unicode throughout a document,
                Non-standard glyphs or characters may however be indicated in a TEI document using
                the <gi>g</gi> element to reference definitions for such things provided by this
                element; </item>
              <item><gi>classDecl</gi>: any kind of classification system or taxonomy can be
                declared using this element; parts of a text can then indicate the classification
                code or codes associated with them by using (for example) the <att>ana</att>
                attribute. In a TEI Corpus, this element is typically provided by the corpus header
                so that individual text headers can point to it using the <gi>catRef</gi> element. </item>
              <item><gi>refsDecl</gi>, <gi>geoDecl</gi>, <gi>metDecl</gi>, <gi>fsdDecl</gi>,
                  <gi>variantEncoding</gi> : provide a home for information concerning the encoding
                of reference systems, geographical information, systems of metrical analysis,
                feature systems for linguistic analyses, or the encoding of textual variation. Other
                similarly technical declarations can be added. </item>
            </list>
          <p>We give more detailed examples for each of these three below. </p>
          <p>First, a typical <gi>charDecl</gi> element might define a variant form of the character
            Z which the encoder wishes to distinguish in a transcription. This variant has two
            strokes, but can be replaced by a normal Z. </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <charDecl>
              <glyph xml:id="z103">
                <glyphName>LATIN LETTER Z WITH TWO STROKES</glyphName>
                <mapping type="standardized">z</mapping>
                <mapping type="PUA">U+E304</mapping>
              </glyph>
            </charDecl>
          </egXML>
          <p>Occurrences of this variant form in the transcription can now be distinguished using a
              <gi>g</gi> element to reference the above definition by means of its <att>xml:id</att>
            value as usual. A processor can choose to render it using either the standardized
            mapping or the nonstandard code given by the PUA <note place="foot">PUA is short for
              Private Use Area: a Unicode concept permitting the definition of private codes for
              non-interchangeable characters</note> mapping. </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p> ... mulct<g ref="#z103"/> ... </p>
          </egXML>
          <p>Next we consider the <gi>classDecl</gi> element. This can be used to define any kind of
            private classification system or taxonomy. For a collection of newspaper articles we
            might use a taxonomy like the following: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="tiny">
            <classDecl>
              <taxonomy xml:id="size">
                <category xml:id="large">
                  <catDesc>story occupies more than half a page</catDesc>
                </category>
                <category xml:id="medium">
                  <catDesc>story occupies between quarter and a half page</catDesc>
                </category>
                <category xml:id="small">
                  <catDesc>story occupies less than a quarter page</catDesc>
                </category>
                <!-- etc -->
              </taxonomy>
              <taxonomy xml:id="topic">
                <category xml:id="politics-domestic">
                  <catDesc>Refers to domestic political events</catDesc>
                </category>
                <category xml:id="politics-foreign">
                  <catDesc>Refers to foreign political events</catDesc>
                </category>
                <category xml:id="social-women">
                  <catDesc>refers to role of women in society</catDesc>
                </category>
                <category xml:id="social-servants">
                  <catDesc>refers to role of servants in society</catDesc>
                </category>
                <!-- etc -->
              </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
          </egXML>
          <p>An individual text containing (say) a story of less than a quarter page concerning the
            role of women in society would then reference this classification using the
              <gi>catRef</gi> element as follows:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="tiny">
            <catRef target="#small #social-women"/>
          </egXML>
          <p>The same mechanism can be used to document the codes used in simple linguistic analyses
            such as those discussed in chapter <ptr target="#ANA"/> above. </p>
          <p>Finally, we consider the <gi>tagsDecl</gi> element. This can be used just to list the
            elements actually used within a document, and also to define default formatting styles
            for them (typically using the W3C Cascading Stylesheet Language CSS). In the following
            example, we first define an two font styles, Italic and Roman, using CSS. We then state
            that within the TEI namespace anything tagged as <gi>emph</gi> or <gi>hi</gi> is by
            default in italic. We also state that the <gi>text</gi> element, and by default
            everything contained by it, uses Roman Font. </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <tagsDecl>
              <rendition xml:id="IT" scheme="css">font-style: italic</rendition>
              <rendition xml:id="FontRoman" scheme="css">font-family: serif</rendition>
              <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <tagUsage gi="emph" render="#IT"/>
                <tagUsage gi="hi" render="#IT"/>
                <tagUsage gi="text" render="#FontRoman"/>
              </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
          </egXML>
          <p>Within the body of a document, the <att>rendition</att> attribute can over-ride the
            default styling for an element; see further section <ptr target="#rend"/> above.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>The profile and revision descriptions</head>
          <p>The third major division of the TEI header is the rather oddly-named <term>Profile
              Description</term>, represented by a <gi>profileDesc</gi> element. Like the others,
            this is a group of optional notes or more specialised elements; they have in common
            simply that they are ‘non-bibliographic’. Default members of the model.profileDescPart
            class include: </p>
          <list>
              <item>
                <gi>creation</gi>: information about the origination of the intellectual content of
                the text, e.g. time and place. In a genetic edition, this may include a structured
                  <gi>listChange</gi> element documenting each significant stage identified in the
                evolution of a text; </item>
              <item>
                <gi>langUsage</gi>: information about languages, registers, writing systems etc used
                in the text; each language used being identified by means of a <gi>language</gi>
                element and an identifying code taken from an ISO standard.</item>
              <item>
                <gi>textDesc</gi> and <gi>textClass</gi>: classifications applied to the text by
                means of a list of specified criteria or by means of a collection of pointers,
                respectively</item>
              <item>
                <gi>particDesc</gi> and <gi>settingDesc</gi>: information about the ‘participants’,
                either real or depicted, in the text</item>
              <!--item>
                            <gi>handNotes</gi>: information about each of the hands identified in
                            a manuscript</item-->
            </list>
          
          <p>We noted above the availability of the <gi>catRef</gi> element as a means of
            classifying a text with respect to a predefined taxonomy. The <gi>profileDesc</gi>
            provides several complementary ways of doing this: </p>
          <list type="gloss">
              <label>using <gi>catRef</gi></label>
              <item>by referring to a locally defined (e.g. in the corpus header) category </item>
              <label>using <gi>classCode</gi></label>
              <item>by referring to some commonly agreed and externally defined category, such as
                the Universal Decimal Classification system, </item>
              <label>using <gi>keywords</gi></label>
              <item>by assigning descriptive terms taken from a bibliographic controlled vocabulary
                or a tag cloud</item>
            </list>
          
          <p>In the following example, taken from the British National Corpus, a text is classified
            using all three possible methods: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="tiny">
            <profileDesc>
              <creation>
                <date when="1962"/>
              </creation>
              <textClass>
                <catRef
                  target="#WRI #ALLTIM1 #ALLAVA2 #ALLTYP3 #WRIDOM5 #WRILEV2 #WRIMED1 #WRIPP5 #WRISAM3 #WRISTA2 #WRITAS0"/>
                <classCode scheme="DLEE">W nonAc: humanities arts</classCode>
                <keywords scheme="COPAC">
                  <term>History, Modern - 19th century</term>
                  <term>Capitalism - History - 19th century</term>
                  <term>World, 1848-1875</term>
                </keywords>
              </textClass>
            </profileDesc>
          </egXML>
          <p>Note that this categorization applies to the whole text. For more fine grained
            classification, the <att>decls</att> attribute may be used to select the classification
            applicable to any declarable elemnt, for example to an individual <gi>div</gi>. </p>
          <p>The fourth and last part of the TEI Header is the optional <term>revision
              description</term>, represented by a <gi>revisionDesc</gi> element which contains a
            list of <gi>change</gi> elements, each with <att>date</att> and <att>who</att>
            attributes, and each indicating significant stages in the evolution of a document; by
            convention the most recent such element is given first. The <gi>listChange</gi> element
            mentioned above may also be used here to to refer to identified stages in the evolution
            of the electronic file, as distinct from the text encoded. In a production environment
            an auomated version control system such as SVN will be used to keep detailed track of
            the evolution of a dcument; the TEI encoding of significant stages in the development of
            a document may be performed semi-automatically by such tools, or manually. </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="tiny">
            <revisionDesc>
              <listChange>
                <change when="2013-05-11">First complete draft</change>
                <change when="2013-04-07">Created header and document structure</change>
              </listChange>
            </revisionDesc>
          </egXML>
        </div>
      </div>
      <!-- #HDR-->
      <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ODD">
        <head>Customizing the TEI</head>
        <p>As we have seen, the TEI is designed to support a very wide range of encoding choices. It
          can be used for a simple reading-oriented transcription of a primary source, whether that
          be an authorial manuscript, a printed literary work, an audio broadcast, or a dictionary.
          It can be used for enriched encodings in which many aspects of such texts are made
          explicit, so that software of all kinds can operate upon them, from visualisation tools
          and digital publishing systems to specialised statistical analysis packages. It can be
          used to provide additional annotations and metadata of all kinds. Almost no-one needs
          everything defined by the TEI, yet every one of its elements is of use or interest to
          someone. How should you go about choosing just the parts of the TEI you need? One major
          motivation for creating TEI documents in the first place is the possibility of sharing
          them with others, and integrating them with other TEI documents. How should you
          communicate the particular TEI encoding choices you have made to others so that such
          integration remains possible?</p>
        <p>The TEI provides a way of adressing these concerns, as well as satisfying the important
          need for detailed project-specific documentation, by providing a set of elements which can
          be used both to specify a <term>schema</term> in terms of the names and formal properties
          of the elements and attributes it contains and also to document the way those elements and
          attributes are used in a given application.</p>
        <p>The notion of a schema is fundamental to XML: it provides a kind of document grammar,
          naming the possible components and constraining the organization of an XML document. A
          schema makes it possible to express constraints such as <q><gi>p</gi> elements may appear
            within <gi>div</gi> elements</q> or <q>every <gi>list</gi> element must contain at least
            one <gi>item</gi></q>. Rules of this kind are easily checked by an automatic processor
          (a <term>validator</term>). Constraints such as <q>Use the <gi>p</gi> element to contain
            paragraphs, not pages</q> or <q>use <gi>placeName</gi> for names of places,
              <gi>persName</gi> for names of people, and <gi>name</gi> for any other name</q> are
          much less easy to check automatically, since they relate to the semantics of the content
          rather than its organization. Such rules are defined by documents such as the TEI
          Guidelines, or by documents referrring to them. Understanding of these semantic
          constraints is extremely important for those developing software intended to take full
          advantage of the marked up document, as well as for those wishing to create new documents
          encoded in the same way. This is particularly true if the schema in use permits a wide
          variety of elements to appear very similar meanings, as will be the case for an unmodified
          and uncustomised TEI schema. </p>
        <p>For this reason, serious use of the TEI requires careful consideration of exactly which
          of its elements is appropriate to the needs of a project, and also perhaps of things which
          the project needs to specify more exactly than the TEI requires. For example, the TEI
          makes no binding requirements for the possible values of the attribute <att>type</att>
          used on <gi>div</gi> elements, since these are likely to vary greatly across different
          projects. In a given project, however, it is likely that standardising on an agreed set of
          values will be very helpful, and there will consequently be a need both to ensure that all
          documents use only the agreed set of values, and to ensure that documentation about what
          those values are and what they signify is maintained along with the rest of the schema,
          and readily available to XML-aware document preparation and editing systems (such as the
          widely used oXygen program) to help and guide the human document editor. </p>
        <p>The TEI provides a special set of elements which can be used to create such a schema
          specification. The elements concerned (<gi>schemaSpec</gi>, <gi>moduleRef</gi>,
            <gi>elementSpec</gi>, <gi>classSpec</gi> and others) combine formal XML declarations for
          inclusion in a DTD or Schema with detailed documentation and examples, for inclusion in a
          technical manual about the encoding scheme being specified. For this reason, a document
          using these elements is informally known as an <q>ODD</q>, for One Document Does it all:
          it provides information for a computer to process along with documentation of that
          information for a human being to read, in a single integrated XML document.
          Unsurprisingly, the TEI system itself is expressed using this exact same set of elements,
          but here we focus on its use in the creation of a TEI customization.</p>
        <div>
          <head>Building a customization</head>
          <p>The simplest TEI customization is the null customization, which simply says <q>permit
              every element defined by the TEI</q>. The resulting schema, called
              <ident>TEI-all</ident>, provides (at the time of writing) some 450 different elements,
            and many, many, different ways of solving often over-lapping encoding problems. The size
            and permissiveness of this schema alike make it more or less unusable for practical
            purposes ― except for one very important one related to TEI <term>conformance</term>, to
            which we return below.</p>
          <p>Probably the most widely used and frequently referenced TEI customization is <ref
              target="#BurnardSperberg">TEI Lite</ref>, a subset of some fifty elements claiming to
            satisfy the needs of 90% of TEI users, as evidenced by their actual practice in creating
            digital texts. This was originally produced for a TEI training workshop back in 1997,
            but with some updating has continued to be useful in a very wide range of contexts, to
            the extent that some people think that it <emph>is</emph> the TEI schema. TEI Lite is
            included (as an Exemplar) with the standard release of TEI, in source and derived forms. </p>
          <p>A quick glance at the XML source code for the TEI Lite ODD shows that it appears to be
            a typical TEI document, with <gi>div</gi> elements containing <gi>head</gi>s,
            <gi>p</gi>s and <gi>list</gi>s, containing much discursive prose, as well as
              <gi>ptr</gi> elements for cross references and a few other specialised elements such
            as <gi>egXML</gi> for XML examples. The actual schema specified by this document is
            represented, towards the end of the document, by a <gi>schemaSpec</gi> element which
            contains declarations like the following : </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <schemaSpec ident="tei_lite" start="TEI teiCorpus">
              <moduleRef key="analysis" include="interp interpGrp pc s w"/>
              <moduleRef key="linking" include="anchor seg"/>
              <moduleRef key="tagdocs" include="att code eg gi ident val"/>
              <moduleRef key="tei"/>
              <moduleRef key="textstructure"
                include="TEI argument back body byline closer dateline div         docAuthor docDate docEdition docImprint docTitle         epigraph front group imprimatur opener postscript          salute signed text titlePage titlePart trailer"
              />
            </schemaSpec>
          </egXML>
          <p>The <gi>moduleRef</gi> element is used to reference a TEI <term>module</term>. A module
            is simply a named container for a number of declarations for TEI elements and classes.
            The TEI currently defines 22 modules, each one corresponding to a chapter in the TEI
            Guidelines where its contents are described in detail. By default, a module reference
            implies that all the declarations it contains are to be transferred to the schema being
            specified, but the attributes <att>include</att> and <att>except</att> can be used to
            modify this default behaviour. Thus, in the above example the schema being created will
            include all the declarations found in the module called <ident>tei</ident>, but element
            declarations for only elements <gi>anchor</gi> and <gi>seg</gi> from the module called
              <ident>linking</ident>.
            <!--Any classes
declared by the module (for example, in this case, the attribute class
<ident>att.global.linking</ident>) will however always be included.-->
            Alternatively, the attribute <att>except</att> might have been used to select everything
            from this module <emph>except</emph> for the elements named as its value. </p>
          <p>A module makes available to the <gi>schemaSpec</gi> a declaration for each element
            selected, in the form of an <gi>elementSpec</gi> element. This has several components,
            most of which are visualised in the TEI reference documentation. It includes, for
            example: </p>
          <list>
              <item> one or more <gi>desc</gi> elements to provide a short description of the
                function of the element, possibly in different languages; </item>
              <item>a <gi>classes</gi> element containing a <gi>memberOf</gi> element for each class
                of which the element is a member; </item>
              <item>an <gi>attList</gi> element, containing a structured list of all the attributes
                locally defined for the element, together with information about their datatype and
                any predefined set of values, expressed by means of the elements <gi>attDef</gi>,
                  <gi>valList</gi> and <gi>valItem</gi> respectively; </item>
              <item>a <gi>content</gi> element providing a formal declaration of the legal content
                of the element, and optionally <gi>constraint</gi> elements used to express any
                additional usage constraints; </item>
              <item>one or more <gi>exemplum</gi> elements, each containing an examples of usage, as
                far as possible taken from real documents, plus commentary. </item>
            </list>
            <p><ref
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/REF-ELEMENTS.html"
              >Appendix C of the TEI Guidelines</ref> provides nicely-formatted documentation for
            every defined TEI element on the basis of such declarations. </p>
          <p>As well as selecting or excluding declarations, a <gi>schemaSpec</gi> can modify some
            parts of a declaration. A little later in the ODD for TEI Lite, we find the following: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <elementSpec ident="TEI" mode="change">
              <attList><attDef ident="version" mode="delete"/></attList>
            </elementSpec>
          </egXML>
          <p>the effect of which is to provide a second declaration for the element <gi>TEI</gi>,
            along with that selected from the <ident>textstructure</ident> module. An ODD processor
            must reconcile or unify such duplications, under control of the attribute
              <att>mode</att> . In this particular case, the effect is to change the
              <gi>attList</gi> declared for the <gi>TEI</gi> element by deleting the attribute
              <att>ident</att> from it. </p>
          <p>Exactly the same procedure is used in the remainder of the TEI Lite customization to
            remove from it some other unwanted attributes. For example, the attributes
              <att>notBefore</att>, <att>notAfter</att>, and others are provided by the attribute
            class <ident>att.datable.w3c</ident>. The easiest way of removing them is therefore to
            provide an additional declaration for the class as follows: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <classSpec type="atts" ident="att.datable.w3c" module="tei" mode="change">
              <attList>
                <attDef ident="notBefore" mode="delete"/>
                <attDef ident="notAfter" mode="delete"/>
                <attDef ident="from" mode="delete"/>
                <attDef ident="to" mode="delete"/>
              </attList>
            </classSpec>
          </egXML>

          <p>An ODD specification can include or exclude elements and attributes in these and other
            ways. It can also modify an existing declaration by adding additional constraints to it.
            For an example, consider <ref target="https://sourceforge.net/p/epidoc/wiki/Home/">the
              TEI customization known as Epidoc</ref>, which is widely-used by epigraphers and
            others working with inscriptions from the ancient world. As we noted above, the
              <att>type</att> attribute on the <gi>div</gi> element is not constrained in any way by
            the TEI. The Epidoc community however has decided that it wishes to enforce the presence
            of this attribute and to permit only six predefined values for it. Here is the fragment
            of the Epidoc ODD which achieves that effect:</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <elementSpec ident="div" mode="change" module="textstructure">
              <attList>
                <attDef ident="type" mode="replace" usage="req">
                  <valList type="closed">
                    <valItem ident="apparatus">
                      <desc>to contain apparatus criticus or textual notes</desc>
                    </valItem>
                    <valItem ident="bibliography">
                      <desc>to contain bibliographical information, previous publications,
                        etc.</desc>
                    </valItem>
                    <valItem ident="commentary">
                      <desc>to contain all editorial commentary, historical/prosopographical
                        discussion, etc.</desc>
                    </valItem>
                    <valItem ident="edition">
                      <desc>to contain the text of the edition itself; may include multiple
                        text-parts</desc>
                    </valItem>
                    <valItem ident="textpart">
                      <desc>used to divide a div[type=edition] into multiple parts (fragments,
                        columns, faces, etc.)</desc>
                    </valItem>
                    <valItem ident="translation">
                      <desc>to contain a translation of the text into one or more modern
                        languages</desc>
                    </valItem>
                  </valList>
                </attDef>
              </attList></elementSpec>
          </egXML>
          <p>Note that further constraints could be added to check that these values are correctly
            used: for example to check that a <tag>div type="textpart"</tag> always has a <tag>div
              type="edition"</tag> as its parent.</p>
          <p>The Epidoc project shows how a particular research community can adapt the TEI to their
            own needs, and its customization is a good demonstration of the kinds of things which
            the ODD language makes possible. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Adding a new element</head>
          <p>The ODD system also makes it possible to add entirely new elements to a schema. At its
            simplest this involves no more than the addition of a <gi>elementSpec</gi> for the new
            element to the schema specification, but deciding on the proper content for that new
            element does require some knowledge of the way the TEI system is designed. Choosing
            which class memberships should be specified for a new element, for example, is difficult
            without knowing which classes exist and how they interact. Choosing an appropriate
            content model for the new element similarly requires some thought about how other
            elements are defined, assuming that we wish our new element to behave consistently with
            the rest of the TEI. And finally, because this is a non-TEI element, we must take care
            to define it in a non-TEI namespace. </p>
          <p>For example, suppose we wish to add a new element <gi>speciesName</gi> to mark up the
            names of botanical or other species appearing in a text. Our new element is semantically
            similar to the existing <gi>persName</gi> or <gi>name</gi> elements, so a good starting
            point will be to look at the ODD specification for other name-like elements. For
            example, in the <gi>elementSpec</gi> for the element <gi>persName</gi>, we see that it
            is a member of a model class <ident>model.nameLike.agent</ident>, which is a subclass of
            the more general <ident>model.nameLike</ident> class. Adding our new element to this
            class will ensure that it will appear in the content models of other TEI elements in the
            same places as other naming elements, without any further work on our part. We also note
            that <gi>persName</gi> is a member of several attribute classes, notably
              <att>att.global</att> (which has several subclasses of its own) and
              <ident>att.canonical</ident>, both of which look useful for our purposes. Adding our
            new element to these classes will ensure that it uses these attributes in the same way
            as other name-like elements. </p>
          <p>Next, we consider the content model of our new element. The easiest course of action
            would be to do the same as the other naming elements, and say that it can contain just
            text, mixed in with other phrase-level elements, elements such as <gi>g</gi>, and global
            elements. This is so common a requirement in the TEI scheme that there is a short cut (a
            "macro") defined for it called <ident>macro.phraseSeq</ident>. If however we want to
            represent the internal content of a <gi>speciesName</gi> (for example to distinguish the
            "genus name" from the "specific name" component), we might want to define a more
            specific content model, possibly involving other new elements or other constraints.
            Whichever course of action we take will be explicitly documented in our ODD, so that
            other users of our data can see how we have customized the basic TEI framework.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Customization and Conformance</head>
          <p>The TEI must reflect the diversity of practice within its user community if it is to
            continue to be useful. It is sometimes said that asking two academics the same question
            will always provide you with at least three different answers to it, and so it should be
            unsurprising to find considerable diversity in the TEI's recommendations.</p>
          <p>Nevertheless, one of the purposes of the TEI Guidelines is to <emph>guide</emph>
            encoding practice. It is not a standard which tells you what to do (in the way that
            engineering standards, for example, specify exactly the shape and dimensions of
            electrical fittings); instead it tells you how to communicate what you have done to
            others. This is why, in <ref
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#CF">the section
              of the Guidelines defining TEI conformance</ref>, one of the essential characteristics
            specified is the existence of an ODD, defining a schema which may be used to validate
            the documents in question, along with other possible constraints. Other essential
            criteria for TEI conformance include formal validity with respect to the schema tei_all,
            and respect for the defined semantics of the TEI elements used: a conformant TEI
            document may contain elements from many namespaces, but any elements from the TEI
            namespace must have the semantics defined for them by the TEI. </p>
          <p>Consider for example the redoubtable English nineteenth century novelist Bulwer-Lytton.
            In one corpus of TEI documents we might hope to find his full name tagged, and
            associated with a definition of the person himself, as follows: </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <persName ref="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Bulwer-Lytton,_1st_Baron_Lytton"
                ><forename>Edward</forename><forename>George</forename><surname type="linked"
                >Bulwer-Lytton</surname>, <roleName>Baron Lytton of <placeName>Knebworth</placeName>
              </roleName></persName>
          </egXML>
          <p>But in others we will find versions with less informative markup or using different TEI
            elements, such as </p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p>
              <rs type="name">Baron Lytton of Knebworth</rs>
            </p>
          </egXML>
          <p>or</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p>
              <name type="person" key="BWLY">The Right Honourable the Lord Lytton PC</name>
            </p>
          </egXML>
          <p>or</p>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <p>
              <persName ref="#BWLY">First Baron Lytton of Knebworth</persName>
            </p>
          </egXML>
          <p>Such variations are only to be expected: projects vary considerably in their
            priorities. For some, it is enough just to show that a string of words is a name; for
            others, it is important to distinguish names of persons from names of places; for yet
            others it is essential to disambiguate named entity references, as they are known. The
            outputs from such projects clearly cannot simply be combined in a straightforwardly
            interoperable way, without some additional effort. Can they all be considered
            TEI-conformant? </p>
          <p>An explicit customization, using the features of ODD we have sketched in this section,
            is the easiest way for a project to communicate its own decisions about how the TEI
            should be applied, and hence the easiest way to ensure its documents are interchangeable
            with others. A project can simply suppress (say) the element <gi>rs</gi> from its
            schema, or specify a closed list of values for its <att>type</att> attribute. It can
            choose to use one or other (or both) of the attributes <att>key</att> and <att>ref</att>
            to associate different versions of a person's name with data about the person intended,
            and hence disambiguate them. Such choices can be made explicit in a customized schema,
            and hence tell us which of the many very different approaches to tagging an individual's
            name has been adopted in a given set of documents. And because it is also possible to
            generate an ODD automatically from a set of TEI XML documents, we can also distinguish
            an intended customization ― expressing what the creators of a document intended to be
            their encoding practice ― from an actual customization, expressing the encoding
            practices actually found. </p>
          <p>If the TEI is designed to be customized, how can it also be claim to be an interchange
            format? For "blind interchange" (also known as "interoperability"), the recipient of a
            document must be confident that it will contain only TEI elements, and that those
            elements have been used according to the rules defined by the TEI. Unmodified, those
            rules permit so much variation that it is all but impossible for a developer to
            anticipate every possibility that their software must be able to handle. The
            availability of an ODD greatly simplifies this task, both by limiting the elements
            available, and by optionally adding to the constraints they represent on data content.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <!-- #ODD -->
      <!--]-->
      <div xml:id="WOT">
        <head>Conclusion: what <emph>is</emph> the TEI? </head>
        <p>When we talk about <q>the TEI</q> what do we mean? The administrative body which is
          supported financially by the members of the Text Encoding Initiative Consortium? When we
          say <q>the TEI sent me this newsletter</q> or <q>we support the TEI</q> we are probably
          talking about the Consortium as an organization. But when we say <q>The TEI now supports
            markup of musical notation</q> or <q>The TEI now provides methods for the encoding of
            genetic editions</q> we are talking about something rather different — the technical
          content of the TEI Guidelines. And when we say <q>that's a really TEI point of view</q>
          (for example, with reference to best practice in the long-term archiving of digital
          resources) or <q>the TEI exemplifies our approach to open source</q> we're clearly talking
          about something more than either a set of technical recommendations or the people who
          maintain or who choose to use them. Some people talk about <q>the TEI</q> as it were a
          kind of club or religion, with members and non-believers, to which some aspire and from
          which others wish to distinguish themselves. Within the noisy market place of the
            <q>Digital Humanities</q>, the TEI is a kind of senior member, an annoying parental
          figure for some, a benevolent one for others, something just too old-fashioned even to be
          considered for others. Yet, over the last decade, it has become increasingly clear that
          the TEI is part of what makes the digital humanities happen: it has become a part of the
          infrastructure everyone has to engage with, both technically and socially, once they start
          thinking about text or other forms of cultural resource in digital form. The TEI provides
          a toolkit with which to do that thinking, and, most importantly, it also reflects the
          thinking that is done, both in its preoccupations and its occasional oddities. It is this
          sense of TEI, as an information architecture, which we have used throughout most of this
          text. However, it seems appropriate to conclude with some consideration of the TEI as an
          organization.</p>
        <p>One of the odder things about the TEI, from some perspectives at least, is that it is not
          a government agency like ANSI, or a well-funded international organization like ISO, or an
          industrial consortium like the W3C, though organizationally the TEI Consortium has points
          in common with all of these. The TEI is a not-for-profit membership organization, powered
          entirely by a small amount of funding from institutions and individuals who care enough
          about its activities to put money into their support and maintenance and also by a large
          amount of volunteer effort from institutions and individuals who want to contribute to its
          continued development. Every year, the TEI hosts a conference where the membership meets
          to transact the necessary official business of electing officers, and of course to discuss
          the ways in which the TEI is intellectually strong or weak. The community of those using
          the TEI and contributing to its continued development is however much larger than the
          paid-up membership. Any interested person is free to propose modifications or extensions
          to the system, or to report errors or inconsistencies ― and many people do. The TEI
          maintains an elected Technical Council which is responsible for assessing and acting upon
          all proposed modifications and managing production of regular new releases. This process
          is carried out in public, in the spirit of Open Source development. We thus find it
          natural to refer to the TEI Community, even though the boundaries and constituents of that
          user community remain largely uncharted. It is that community which owns the TEI, which
          speaks for it in the larger Humanities community, and which informs and determines its
          evolution. </p>
        <p>The word <q>evolution</q> is not chosen lightly. The TEI of 2013 is not the same as that
          of 1998, nor even as that of 2009, although most of the element names are still the same.
          The organization and flexibility of the TEI as a system architecture enables it to adapt
          to the changing needs and priorities of its community, in much the same way as other life
          forms have evolved in response to a changing environment. In <ref target="#Burnard2013"
            >Burnard 2013</ref> I have argued that this is the secret of the TEI's longevity: it is
          organized in such a way as to ensure that it can be modified simply and effectively,
          depending on the needs of its users. It seems likely therefore that the TEI will continue
          to evolve, both in taking on new areas of encoding, and in modifying what has already been
          proposed to keep up with the changing digital landscape. At the end of 2010, for example,
          release 2.0 of TEI P5 introduced a whole new way of representing genetic or documentary
          editions defined over the preceding year by an externally-funded workgroup. A method of
          making TEI documents interoperable with a new standard for the representation of notated
          music was introduced at about the same time. More recently, ongoing work in the TEI's
          Special Interest Group on Ontologies ensures that TEI encoded texts will continue to be
          hospitable to emerging best practice in representing Linked Data. </p>
        <p>The TEI as an organization is committed to improving the accessibility and
          comprehensibility of the TEI as a technical system. In addition to the TEI website, which
          acts as a complete online reference for the scheme, there is a continual need to provide
          up to date training materials, and to promote active engagement with those interested in
          using, developing, and maintaining the TEI by wikis, discussion groups, and whatever other
          appropriate means emerge in the future. The development of such resources is an ongoing
          task for all members of the TEI community and beyond. This little book is intended as a
          modest contribution to that agenda.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Further Reading</head>
        <p>The <ref target="http//www.tei-c.org">TEI website</ref> maintains a page of links to
          online tutorial materials at <ptr
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Support/Learn/tutorials.xml"/>; we list a few of these
          below.</p>
        <p>The <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/P5/">TEI Guidelines</ref> include a large reading
          list of publications about markup theory and the TEI in particular at <ptr
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/BIB.html#BIB-RDG"/>. We list
          below a few items from it which the general reader may find helpful or informative. </p>
        <p>The Zotero website hosts two public TEI-related collections of citations: a generic one
          at <ptr target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/tei/items"/>, and one more focussed on
          linguistic issues at <ptr target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/tei-lingsig/items/"/>
        </p>
        <div>
          <head>Tutorial articles and manuals</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bertrand">
              <editor>
                <forename>Lauranne</forename>
                <surname>Bertrand</surname>
              </editor>
              <editor>
                <forename>Marie Luce</forename>
                <surname>Demonet</surname>
              </editor>
              <editor>
                <forename>Jorge</forename>
                <surname>Fins</surname>
              </editor>
              <title level="m">Manuel d’encodage XML-TEI Renaissance et temps modernes (Imprimés -
                manuscrits)</title>
              <ptr target="http://www.bvh.univ-tours.fr/XML-TEI/index.asp"/>
              <note>Detailed encoding manual for early print materials; in French.</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bingenheimer2009">
              <editor>
                <forename>Marcus</forename>
                <surname>Bingenheimer</surname>
              </editor>
              <title level="m" xml:lang="zh">TEI使用指南──運用TEI處理中 文文獻</title>
              <title level="m" xml:lang="zh">Chinese TEI – A guide to using TEI with Chinese
                texts</title>
              <pubPlace>Taiwan</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Taiwan E-learning and Digital Archive Program 數位典藏與數位學習國家型科技計畫</publisher>
              <date>2009</date>
              <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Support/Learn/TEI-ChinLoc-2ndPrintEd.pdf"/>
              <note>Chinese translation of the TEI Lite tutorial (P5 edition) and accompanying
                articles. </note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Bodard">
              <editor>
                <forename>Gabriel</forename>
                <surname>Bodard</surname>
              </editor>
              <editor>
                <forename>Tom</forename>
                <surname>Elliott</surname>
              </editor>
              <editor>
                <forename>Elli</forename>
                <surname>Mylonas</surname>
              </editor>
              <title level="m">EpiDoc Guidelines: Ancient documents in TEI XML</title>
              <ptr target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/"/>
              <note>Detailed encoding manual for epigraphical and other ancient primary source
                materials.</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="BurnardSperberg">
              <author>
                <forename>Lou</forename>
                <surname>Burnard</surname>
              </author>
              <author>
                <forename>C.M.</forename>
                <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
              </author>
              <title level="m">TEI Lite: Encoding for Interchange: an introduction to the TEI: final
                revised edition for TEI P5</title>
              <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-exemplars/html/tei_lite.doc.html"/>
              <date>August 2012</date>
              <note>The original one stop generic tutorial introduction to using the TEI. Also
                available in <ref
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-exemplars/html/tei_lite_fr.doc.html"
                  >a French translation by Sophie David and Lou Burnard.</ref></note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Ciottied2005">
              <editor>
                <forename>Fabio</forename>
                <surname>Ciotti</surname>
              </editor>
              <title level="m" xml:lang="fr">Il Manuale TEI Lite: Introduzione Alla Codifica
                Elettronica Dei Testi Letterari</title>
              <pubPlace>Milano</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Sylvestre Bonnard</publisher>
              <date>2005</date>
              <note>Italian translation of the TEI Lite tutorial (P4 edition); accompanied by
                introductory articles on XML, on the transition from P4 to P5, and on TEI tools and
                techniques. </note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Dalmau">
              <editor>
                <forename>Michelle</forename>
                <surname>Dalmau</surname>
              </editor>
              <editor>
                <forename>Kevin</forename>
                <surname>Hawkins</surname>
              </editor>
              <title level="m">Best Practices for TEI in Libraries</title>
              <ptr target="http://purl.oclc.org/NET/teiinlibraries"/>
              <note>Detailed specification of a subset of TEI appropriate for use in capture of
                primary sources for digital library work.</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Flanders">
              <editor>
                <forename>Julia</forename>
                <surname>Flanders</surname>
              </editor>
              <editor>
                <forename>Syd</forename>
                <surname>Bauman</surname>
              </editor>
              <title level="m">Women Writers Project Guide to Scholarly Text Encoding</title>
              <ptr target="http://www.wwp.brown.edu/research/publications/guide/"/>
              <date>2007</date>
              <note>Website providing documentation and guidance on using the TEI for the encoding
                of early printed books.</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="HawkinsIntro">
              <author>
                <forename>Kevin</forename>
                <surname>Hawkins</surname>
              </author>
              <title level="m">Introduction to XML for Text</title>
              <ptr target="www.ultraslavonic.info/intro-to-xml"/>
              <note>Short introduction to encoding with XML for absolute beginners.</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Loiseau2002">
              <author>
                <forename>Sylvain</forename>
                <surname>Loiseau</surname>
              </author>
              <title level="m">Les standards : autour d'XML et de la TEI</title>
              <ptr target="http://www.revue-texto.net/Corpus/Manufacture/standards/sommaire.html"/>
              <date>2002</date>
              <note>Detailed overview of TEI P4 and related XML standards; in French.</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="VanDen">
              <editor>
                <forename>Ron</forename>
                <surname>Van den Branden</surname>
              </editor>
              <editor>
                <forename>Edward</forename>
                <surname>Vanhoutte</surname>
              </editor>
              <title level="m">TEI By Example</title>
              <ptr target="http://www.teibyexample.org"/>
              <note>Online tutorial site providing practical exercises and examples for the full
                range of TEI (P4) modules.</note>
            </bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Journal articles and books</head>
          <listBibl>
            <biblStruct xml:id="Barnardetal1996">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>David</forename>
                  <forename>T.</forename>
                  <surname>Barnard</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Lou</forename>
                  <surname>Burnard</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>C.</forename>
                  <forename>Michael</forename>
                  <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="a">Lessons learned from using SGML in the Text Encoding
                  Initiative</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Computer Standards &amp; Interfaces</title>
                <imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol">18</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                  <date>1996</date>
                  <biblScope type="pp">3–10</biblScope>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0920-5489(95)00035-6"/>
              <note>Technical article summarizing how SGML was used in TEI P3 to implement
                modularity, customization, and hyperlinking. Of interest in the history of
                ODD.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="BurnardRahtz2004">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>Lou</forename>
                  <surname>Burnard</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Sebastian</forename>
                  <surname>Rahtz</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="m">RelaxNG with Son of ODD</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="m">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages 2004</title>
                <imprint>
                  <date>2004</date>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ref
                target="http://www.mulberrytech.com/Extreme/Proceedings/html/2004/Burnard01/EML2004Burnard01.pdf"/>
              <note>Technical description of the new ODD system developed for TEI P5.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="Burnard2000">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>Lou</forename>
                  <surname>Burnard</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="m">Text Encoding for Interchange: A New Consortium</title>
                <ptr target="http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue24/tei/"/>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Ariadne, Issue 24</title>
                <imprint>
                  <date>June 2000</date>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <note>Press release describing the relaunch of the TEI as a membership
                Consortium.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="Burnard2001">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>Lou</forename>
                  <surname>Burnard</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="a">On the Hermeneutic Implications of Text Encoding</title>
                <ptr target="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~lou/wip/herman.htm"/>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <editor>
                  <forename>Domenico</forename>
                  <surname>Fiormonte</surname>
                </editor>
                <editor>
                  <forename>Jonathan</forename>
                  <surname>Usher</surname>
                </editor>
                <title level="m">New Media and the Humanities: Research and Applications</title>
                <imprint>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Humanities Computing Unit</publisher>
                  <date>2001</date>
                  <biblScope type="pp">31–38</biblScope>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <!-- note>last accessed on August 12, 2007</note-->
              <note>Brief article stressing the interpretive nature of markup and placing it within
                an ancient scholarly tradition.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="Burnard2013">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>Lou</forename>
                  <surname>Burnard</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="a">The Evolution of the Text Encoding Initiative: From Research
                  Project to Research Infrastructure </title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                <imprint>
                  <biblScope type="issue">5</biblScope>
                  <date>2013</date>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/811"/>
              <note>Historical review of the development of the TEI to date.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="Coombsetal1987">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>James</forename>
                  <forename>H.</forename>
                  <surname>Coombs</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Allen</forename>
                  <surname>Renear</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Steven</forename>
                  <forename>J.</forename>
                  <surname>DeRose</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="a">Markup Systems and The Future of Scholarly Text Processing</title>
                <ref target="http://xml.coverpages.org/coombs-hallgren.html"/>
                <ref target="http://xml.coverpages.org/coombs.html"/>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
                <imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol">30</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue">11</biblScope>
                  <date>1987</date>
                  <biblScope type="pp">933–947</biblScope>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ptr target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/32206.32209"/>
              <!-- note>last accessed August 12, 2007</note-->
              <!--idno type="doi">10.1145/32206.32209</idno-->
              <!-- note>last accessed August 12, 2007</note-->
              <!-- note>last accessed August 12, 2007</note-->
              <!--note>Reprinted with new commentary in <ptr target="#Landow1993a"/>, pp
					85–118</note-->
              <note>Classic and influential polemic arguing for descriptive rather than procedural
                markup as a scholarly activity.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="DeRose1997a">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>Steven</forename>
                  <forename>J.</forename>
                  <surname>DeRose</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>David</forename>
                  <forename>G.</forename>
                  <surname>Durand</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Elli</forename>
                  <surname>Mylonas</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Allen</forename>
                  <forename>H.</forename>
                  <surname>Renear</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="a">What is Text, Really?</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Journal of Computer Documentation</title>
                <imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol">21</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                  <date>1997</date>
                  <biblScope type="pp">1–24</biblScope>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ptr target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/264842.264843"/>
              <!--idno type="doi">10.1145/264842.264843</idno-->
              <note>Classic statement of the <soCalled>OHCO</soCalled> hypothesis according to which
                text is fundamentally an "Ordered Hierarchy of Content".</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="HolmesRomary2010">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>Martin</forename>
                  <surname>Holmes</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Laurent</forename>
                  <surname>Romary</surname>
                </author>
                <title type="main" level="a">Encoding models for scholarly literature</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="m" type="main">Publishing and digital libraries: Legal and
                  organizational issues</title>
                <imprint>
                  <publisher>IGI Global</publisher>
                  <biblScope type="pp">88-110</biblScope>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <!--idno type="doi">10.4018/978-1-60960-031-0</idno>
				<idno type="HALid">http://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00390966</idno-->
              <ptr
                target="http://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00390966/PDF/romary_chap_iglezakis_book.pdf"/>
              <note>Discusses use of TEI for the encoding and management of academic
                publications.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="Ide1995b">
              <monogr>
                <editor>
                  <forename>Nancy</forename>
                  <surname>Ide</surname>
                </editor>
                <editor>
                  <forename>Jean</forename>
                  <surname>Veronis</surname>
                </editor>
                <title level="m">The Text Encoding Initiative: Background and Contexts</title>
                <imprint>
                  <pubPlace>Dordrecht</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Kluwer Academic Publisher</publisher>
                  <date>1995</date>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <note>Essential collection of 17 articles originally published as a double issue of
                Computers and the Humanities in 1994. Major TEI contributors of the first generation
                provide overviews of the TEI approach to encoding specific text types, complemented
                by classic articles on TEI objectives and design, and on SGML. </note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="IdeRomary">
              <analytic>
                <author><forename>Nancy</forename><surname>Ide</surname></author>
                <author><forename>Laurent</forename><surname>Romary</surname>
                </author>
                <title type="main" level="a">A Registry of Standard Data Categories for Linguistic
                  Annotation</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title>Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on Language Resources and
                  Evaluation - LREC'04</title>
                <imprint>
                  <pubPlace>Lisbon, Portugal</pubPlace>
                  <date>2004</date>
                  <biblScope type="pp">135-138</biblScope>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ref type="HALid">http://hal.inria.fr/inria-00099858</ref>
              <note>Describes the development of a Data Category Registry (DCR) component for the
                Linguistic Annotation Framework; an ISO standard of major importance in the encoding
                of linguistic analysis. </note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="Mertz2003">
              <monogr>
                <author>
                  <forename>David</forename>
                  <surname>Mertz</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="m" type="main">XML Matters: TEI — the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub"> An XML Dialect for Archival and Complex
                  Documents</title>
                <imprint>
                  <date>2003</date>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ref target="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/xml/library/x-matters30.html"/>
              <!-- note>last accessed January 27, 2005</note-->
              <note>Interesting perspective on TEI-XML as seen from outside the scholarly
                community.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="MylonasandRenear1999">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>Elli</forename>
                  <surname>Mylonas</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Allen</forename>
                  <surname>Renear</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="a">The Text Encoding Initiative at 10: Not Just an Interchange Format
                  Anymore — But a New Research Community</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                <imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol">33</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue">1-2</biblScope>
                  <date>1999</date>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <idno type="DOI">http://dx.doi.org/10.1023/A:1001832310939</idno>
              <note>Introduction to a retrospective collection of 12 selected papers produced for
                the TEI 10th Anniversary Conference, held at Brown University in November 1997.
              </note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="Schmidt2011">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="a">A TEI-based Approach to Standardising Spoken Language
                  Transcription</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                <imprint>
                  <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                  <date>2011</date>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ptr target="http://jtei.revues.org/142"/>
              <note>Surveys existing transcription schemes for spoken language and the feasibility
                of using TEI as an interlingua amongst them.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="SperbergMcQueen1991">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>C.</forename>
                  <forename>Michael</forename>
                  <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                </author>
                <title level="a">Text in the Electronic Age: Textual Study and Text Encoding, with
                  Examples from Medieval Texts</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                <imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                  <date>1991</date>
                  <biblScope type="pp">34-46</biblScope>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/6.1.34"/>
              <!-- note>last accessed August 12, 2007</note-->
              <!--idno type="doi">10.1093/llc/6.1.34</idno-->
              <note>Classic statement of markup theory as applied to the editing of primary
                sources.</note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="Unsworthetaleds2004">
              <monogr>
                <editor>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname>Unsworth</surname>
                </editor>
                <editor>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname>O'Brien</surname>
                  <surname>O'Keeffe</surname>
                </editor>
                <editor>
                  <forename>Lou</forename>
                  <surname>Burnard</surname>
                </editor>
                <title level="m">Electronic Textual Editing</title>
                <imprint>
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                  <publisher>Modern Languages Association</publisher>
                  <date>2006</date>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <note>Collection of articles by 24 leading practioners covering all aspects of
                electronic textual editing within the TEI paradigm. An early online version is
                available at <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/ETE/"/>. </note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="WitternEtAl2009">
              <analytic>
                <author>
                  <forename>Christian</forename>
                  <surname>Wittern</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Conal</forename>
                  <surname>Tuohy</surname>
                </author>
                <author>
                  <forename>Arianna</forename><surname>Ciula</surname>. </author>
                <title level="a">The making of TEI P5</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
                <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                <imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol">24</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                  <date>2009</date>
                  <biblScope type="pp">281-96</biblScope>
                </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqp017"/>
              <note>Detailed report on the editorial work leading up to the first edition of TEI
                P5.</note>
            </biblStruct>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Glossary</head>
          <list type="gloss">
            <label>analytic</label>
            <item>In a bibliographic context, an analytic or analytical title relates to a single
              component of a larger bibliographic item, for example a single article within a
              journal.</item>
            <label>composite</label>
            <item>A composite document is one which has several independent parts, each of which
              could stand alone. </item>
            <label>conformance</label>
            <item>A TEI conformant document must be valid according to the TEI All schema, and must
              also respect the TEI conceptual model. </item>
            <label>data-centred</label>
            <item>An approach to structuring information which prioritizes its informational content
              or structure above its form or appearance. </item>
            <label>element</label>
            <item>Any XML document component identified by tagging </item>
            <label>encoding description</label>
            <item>That part of a TEI Header which describes the encoding and editorial practices
              applied in its production</item>
            <label>feature structures</label>
            <item>A widely-used abstract formalism used in linguistics to represent meaning as
              structures of named features and feature values. </item>
            <label>global attributes</label>
            <item>Attributes which are potentially abvailable on every TEI-defined element</item>
            <label>group</label>
            <item>A number of independent texts which can also be regarded as constituting a single
              one, for example an anthology.</item>
            <label>header</label>
            <item>In the TEI context refers to all the metadata associated with a corpus or
              document. </item>
            <label>highlighted</label>
            <item>In the TEI context, used to describe any form of visual salience.</item>
            <label>module</label>
            <item>One of the named groupings of TEI declarations (for elements, classes, macros
              etc.) making up the TEI framework.</item>
            <label>monographic</label>
            <item>In bibliography, a single identifiable bibliographic item, such as a book.</item>
            <label>namespace</label>
            <item>An identifier associated with a particular group of XML element names or
              vocabulary.</item>
            <label>profile description</label>
            <item>That part of a TEI header concerned with non-bibliographic descriptive
              metadata.</item>
            <label>publication statement</label>
            <item>That part of a TEI header concerned with the publication or distribution of a
              resource</item>
            <label>rendition</label>
            <item>In the TEi context refers to the way some aspect of a document was originally
              presented or formatted.</item>
            <label>revision description</label>
            <item>That part of a TEI header concerned with revisions and changes during production
              of a resource.</item>
            <label>schema</label>
            <item>A set of formally expressed rules concerning the markup of a document. </item>
            <label>settlement</label>
            <item>Any place where people live (a town, city etc.)</item>
            <label>simple</label>
            <item>A unitary text or document, which can stand alone and is complete.</item>
            <label>tags</label>
            <item>Codes or labels embedded within a string of characters to indicate the beginning
              or end of an element.</item>
            <label>text-centred</label>
            <item>An approach to structuring information which prioritizes its presentation in
              textual form over its intentional content.</item>
            <label>valid</label>
            <item>An XML document is said to be valid if it conforms to a schema.</item>
            <label>validator</label>
            <item>A piece of software which checks an XML document against a schema to determine
              whether or not it is valid.</item>
            <label>well-formed</label>
            <item>A document is said to be well-formed if it conforms to the syntactic rules of
              XML.</item>
          </list>

        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
