<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Séminaire ALGORITM: session 2 Transcription des comptes rendus de
               l'Oulipo</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Encoding the history of OuLiPo</head>
            <p>At the beginning of this month, I had the pleasure of co-organising a workshop on
               data capture, as the second event in the <ref
                  target="http://difdepo.hypotheses.org/424">Algoritm Seminar series </ref>which
               forms part of an interesting ANR funded project called DifDepo. The project is a
               collaboration between the BNF and Ecritures de modernité, a <ref
                  target="http://www.univ-paris3.fr/ea-4400-ecritures-de-la-modernite-litterature-et-sciences-humaines-ea-conventionnee-cnrs--3433.kjsp"
                  >research unit located at Paris III,</ref> and its objectives include creation of
               a TEI-based digital archive of the archives of the OuLiPo, which are currently
               stashed away in boxes at the Bibliothèque Nationale's Arsenal depository. The papers
               include letters, photos, press cuttings, postcards, drafts, and notes of all sorts,
               but for the purpose of this exercise we decided to focus on the records of the
               OuLiPo's regular meetings, which have been held approximately monthly since the late
               1960s. The whole of the Archive has already been catalogued, and work is in hand to
               produce digital images of a sizeable proportion of it. The object of our workshop was
               to explore ways of transcribing these documents, given that the project has very
               little funding, and will therefore have to rely on the good will of volunteer
               transcribers, enthused by things OuLiPien but maybe a little deficient in TEI
               knowledge. </p>
            <p>About a dozen people participated, most of them surviving to the end of the day. We
               began by asking them to transcribe a page from <ref target="https://www.dropbox.com/s/mj24oo7h8ffplnj/installezMoi.zip">a small collection of pre-selected
               digital page images</ref>, using Word. (I freely admit to a degree of smugness on
               discovering at the last minute that the teaching room was initially equipped only
               with old-style doc-producing Word, which had to be enhanced to a more modern
               docx-producing version at rather short notice by the unflappable Jerome) This
               exercise demonstrated, as we had hoped, quite a bit of variation about what exactly
               should be transferred from the image to the text, and on what editorial principles,
               thus motivating a useful initial discussion about the principles and praxis of text
               encoding. One of the students proposed (unprompted) the principle of "fidelity" to
               the source, while another argued repeatedly for "capturing the meaning". </p>
            <p>Once lulled into a false sense of security by this exercise, participants were
               exposed to the weirdness of an XML-editing environment using everyone's favourite
               oXyGen and my usual tutorial -- create a document, learn how to tag parts of it,
               learn how to manipulate the structure, etc. We then offered them a more demanding
               workflow, involving first capturing a document in Word using a Word Template, which
               defined Styles to highlight a number of significant features (headings, list items,
               etc., but also personal names etc.), secondly converting this to a TEI form, using
               oxGarage and a specialised profile, thirdly looking at (and possibly modifying) that
               in oXyGen, and then converting it back to Word to confirm the feasibilty of
               round-tripping. Sebastian Rahtz of Oxford (whom God preserve) invested quite a bit of
               pre-workshop effort into setting up the necessary infrastructure for this, and making
               sure that it all worked correctly on the day. He also made it possible for us to
               inflict on the students a third alternative approach, based on an experimental
               installation of Ben Brumfield's "From The Page" crowd-sourcing prototype software. I
               had expected this to be everyone's favourite, but (maybe because we had already by
               then sensitized them to the delights of structural markup) our students seemed to
               find the simplicity of its interface made it hard to take seriously.  We had <ref target="https://www.dropbox.com/sh/w6v9fumgl7e3myc/ILWG4_F_oN"> prepared
               tutorial scripts</ref> for each of the three approaches (TEI source code available from my tei-fr
               repository, if you're interested) so I was able to spend some of the time wandering
               about taking photos of hard-working encoders.</p>
            <p>By the end of the day, everyone had tried all three approaches, and everyone had
               produced a couple of TEI XML files conforming to a simple transcription schema I had
               prepared earlier. We collected them all up and Sebastian showed how our pretend
               archive could be displayed on a web page, complete with corresponding page images,
               and vocabulary lists, and personography. This was (of course) all done with a
               straightforward customization of the standard TEI-HTML stylesheets, now available in
               the Stylesheet package as part of the Difdepo profile. </p>
            <p>Conclusions? We still don't really know whether our TEI-XML transcriptions are aiming
               for "fidelity" or "meaning", but we have at least demonstrated the possibility of
               either (or both) . And we do know that the participants all seemed to be more
               enthusiastic about using the customized-word-template approach than either raw Oxygen
               or (possibly over-cooked) From The Page. We didn't explore the idea of a
               pre-customised oXygen author-mode interface, which might well repay the necessary
               investment of effort, if there is a lot of metadata to be entered, for example.</p>
         </div>
         
         
         
         <div>
            <head>Workplan</head>
            <list type="gloss">
               <label>Objectifs du séminaire</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>se mettre d'accord sur un système d'encodage pour les archives
                        d'Oulipo</item>
                     <item>expérimenter plusieurs outils de saisie et de transcription</item>
                     <item>discuter des attentes de ceux qui vont travailler avec le fonds </item>
                     <item>identifier quelques éléments de recherche et d'exploration que la mise à
                        disposition du fonds numerisé et encodé rendra possible</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>Echantillons du fonds </label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Les participants auront d'abord accès à un ensemble de pages déjà
                        numérisés en mode image. Ces fichiers serviront à concrétiser un peu les
                        discussions. </item>
                     <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>
                     <item>Les échantillons sont à télécharger sur les postes du travail des
                        participants, avec d'autres fichiers de travail<?oxy_custom_end?></item>
                     <!-- question HCC/ faut-il les télécharger à l'avance sur les postes qui seront utilisés? et créer un dossier de référence sur le bureau? -->
                     <item>Nous fournissons également un schéma TEI pour la transcription et
                        plusieurs documents de travail.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <label>Démarche proposée</label>
               <item>
                  <list type="ordered">
                     <item>09h30 : Introduction ; plan de la journée (30 mins)</item>
                     <item>10h00 : Première esquisse de transcription. Les participants sont invités
                        de se regrouper en binômes, et on donne à chaque binôme une page
                        (dactylographiée) de l'archive. Ils sont invités de faire une transcription
                        avec Word, adaptée aux usages qu'ils envisagent faire du fonds oulipien. (30
                        min) </item>
                     <item>10h30 : Discussion et comparaison des résultats de cet exercice:
                        compilation des traits des documents considérés d'importance par tous (45
                        mins)</item>
                     <item>11h15 : Pause café (15 min)</item>
                     <item>11h30 : Présentation de l'approche Word+Styles : Sebastian démontre
                        comment transformer un document stylé avec Word en TEI XML; le charger en
                        Oxygen; le modifier; et le réimporter en Word. (30 min)</item>
                     <item>12h00 : Présentation de l'approche Oxygen : Lou conduit un petit tutoriel
                        sur l'usage de ce logiciel, suivi d'une présentation des balises qui sont
                        proposés par le schéma DifDePo, (éventuellement modifiée selon l'exercice
                        initial). Les participants créent un document minimal conforme au schéma.
                        (30 min)</item>
                     <item>12h30 : Pause-Déjeuner (90 mins)</item>
                     <item>14h00 : On divise les participants en 2 groupes : <list>
                           <item>Groupe 1 : chaque binôme reprend le document qu'ils ont déjà
                              préparé en Word, refait son stylage à partir du template déjà préparé
                              par Sebastian, fait l'export en TEI-XML, contrôle les résultats avec
                              Oxygen ; si tout leur semble bon, ils prennent encore un autre
                              document (un manuscrit par ex) et l'encodent de la même manière. </item>
                           <item>Groupe 2 : chaque binôme prend un nouveau document parmi ceux qui
                              sont installés en <?oxy_custom_start type="oxy_content_highlight" color="255,255,0"?>FromThePage.<?oxy_custom_end?>
                              <!-- question  HCC2: faut-il que Joël Rouqette télécharge aussi ce logiciel sur les postes de la salle à l'avance? -->
                              Ils sont invités de le transcrire avec cet outil, en balisant ce qui
                              est possible, et en faisant l'export en TEI-XML ; ils contrôlent et
                              ensuite améliorent les résultats avec Oxygen. </item>
                        </list> (45 mins) </item>
                     <item>14h45: Les groupes sont échangés et on répète (45 min)</item>
                     <!-- should we have a group doing everything in Oxygen? at least one or two pairs, if possible, yes -->
                     <item>15h30 : Nous rassemblons tous les fichiers TEI XML maintenant disponibles
                        et nous essayons de les traîter avec des feuilles de style XSLT pour : <list>
                           <item>afficher page image et transcription ensemble</item>
                           <item>extraire des listes de noms des Oulipiens </item>
                           <item>considérer l'évolution du lexique Oulipien dans le temps</item>
                           <item>etc </item>
                        </list> (60 min) </item>
                     <!-- can do some of these in Oxygen; they also want to see docs loaded into eg teichi (what is that ???) though:  -->
                     <item>16h30 : Revue et discussions (30 min)</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
