<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TP1 : oXygen</title>
        <author>TEI@Oxford</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative Commons Attribution
            license.</p>
        </availability>
        <date>Jan 2011</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Some bits may be lifted from previous talks/workshops by the TEI Community.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>À la découverte d' Oxygen - 2</head>
        <p>In this second part of the exercise we'll experiment with using Oxygen to  : <list>
            <item>encode a pre-existing document in TEI XML</item>
            <item>represent some typical literary structures</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sample text</head>
        <p>In this essay we will encode a Petrarchan sonnet, respecting its organization into stanzas and lines. To make your life easier, we have prepared a transcription already for you, so you don't need to do quite so much typing as in the previous exercise...  </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Create a new document</head>

        <p>As you did before, open Oxygen and click on the New icon at top left to open the New document dialogue. This time, when asked to choose which schema to use, we suggest you select  <ident>TEI
                P5</ident> and then <ident>TEI-Lite</ident>. This will give you a more useful schema than the minimalist one we used in the first exercise.<list>
           
            <item>As before, Oxygen gives you the basic TEI structure, with a few extra components.  </item>
                  <item>Complete the TEI header quickly, as you did before. We suggest the following as title  <q>A Petrarchan Sonnet in TEI-XML format</q>), and as source <q>Transcription taken from "Il Canzoniere" di Francesco Petrarca
                    a cura di Gianfranco Contini
                    Edizione Einaudi, 1964</q></item>
            <item>Remove everything proposed as content for the <gi>body</gi> element, taking care to retain the  <gi>body</gi> et <gi>/body</gi> tags. </item>

          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Adding text to the document</head>
        <p>You can, of course, type out the poem for yourself as you did before. But this time we propose the following method : <list>
            <item>Check that your cursor is <emph>between</emph> the <gi>body</gi> and
                <gi>/body</gi> tags in your empty document </item>
          <item>Choose  <ident>File -> Insert File</ident> from the  <ident>Document</ident> menu (<hi>Note: Not the File
                Menu on the menu bar, but the one fond under the Document
                Menu!</hi>)</item>
            <item>Navigate to the file <ident>sonnet.txt</ident> which you will find in your working folder, select it  and click Open.</item>
            
            <item>Your document is full of red lines but don't panic! we will sort that out in a moment. Look at the error message at the foot of the screen and see if you understand it.</item>          
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Adding structure to the body of a document</head>
        <p>The structure of a document is important. In this case, the body contains :  <list>
            <item>a heading  ... to be tagged with <gi>head</gi> </item>
         <item>an octet and a sestet ... both to be tagged with <gi>div</gi></item>
          <item>four stanzas ... to be tagged with <gi>lg</gi></item>
          
            <item>14 lines ... to be tagged with  <gi>l</gi></item>
            
          </list> Let's go !</p>


        <list>
          <item>Select the first two lines  <q>Canzoniere (Rerum vulgarium fragmenta) 
            VII </q></item>
          <item>Type CTRL-E and choose head from the list of available tags to select <gi>head</gi>; then click <ident>Accept</ident></item>
       
          <item>For extra marks, you may want to cut this heading in two, distinguishing the number (which is the number of the sonnet) from the general title which precedes it. If so, put the cursor before the number <q>VII</q> and use CTRL-ALT-D or some other way of splitting the heading as you did in the previous exercise.</item>
        </list>
    
        <p>Now for the poem itself. Our goal is to have each verse line tagged  <gi>l</gi>
            (<q>line</q>), each stanza tagged  <gi>lg</gi>, the octet tagged <gi>div type="octet"</gi> and
          the sestet tagged <gi>div type="sestet"</gi>. </p>
        <p>Of course there's more than one way to do this. We suggest one fairly quick way, but feel
          free to experiment with other approaches ! <list>
            <item>Sélectionnez avec la souris tout le texte du poème, jusqu'à la citation d'Horace
                <q>caelo musa beat</q>. </item>
            <item>Entourez toute le poème d'une balise <gi>l</gi>. </item>
            <item>Entourez la citation d'Horace d'une balise <gi>quote</gi></item>
            <item>Le petit carré vert apparaît ! Avons-nous terminé ? Hélas non : un document peut
              être valide, tout en contenant des mensonges ! Voyez-vous des mensonges ? Cliquez sur
              le bouton Indentation (ou tapez CTRL-SHIFT-P). </item>
          </list>
          <graphic height="3cm" url="ambitieux-2.png"/></p>
        <p>Parce qu'elles ne sont pas explicités par le balisage, la distinction entre chaque vers
          et entre chaque strophe ne sont plus affichées. Il fait donc les baliser. (Si vous ne
          voyez pas bien où indiquer ces séparations, vous pouvez ré-établir l'affichage originel en
          tapant CTRL-Z) </p>
        <list>
          <item>Mettez le curseur au début de chaque vers, et distinguez-le du précédent, en vous
            servant du bouton <ident>division</ident> ou en tapant ALT-SHIFT-D </item>
          <item>Si cela vous semble plus rapide, vous pouvez aussi <q>tricher</q> : copiez la
            séquence <code>&lt;/l>&lt;l></code>, et collez-la au commencement de chaque vers.</item>
          <item>Quand vous aurez fini, cliquez encore sur le bouton Indentation. Ou sont les
            strophes ?</item>
          <item>Entourez tous les vers (tous les <gi>l</gi>) avec une balise <gi>lg</gi>.</item>
          <item>Divisez cette strophe unique en quatre strophes distinctes. Attention : il faut
            effectuer cette distinction au bon endroit — entre la fin d’un vers et le début du
            suivant, (i.e. après une balise fermante et avant une balise ouvrante). </item>
        </list>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Affichage du texte balisé</head>
        <p>Est-ce que la disparition graduelle de notre beau sonnet au dessus d'un nuage de balises
          commence à vous inquiéter un peu ? Cela nous permet au moins de visualiser la structure
          émergeante du sonnet -- regardez par exemple dans la fenêtre <q>Sommaire</q> à gauche
          :</p>
        <p><graphic height="4cm" url="../Graphics/Oxy12/sommaire-1.png"/></p>

        <p>Pour contrôler l'affichage d'un text balisé, il faut préciser comment nous désirons
          visualiser chaque balise. Ces précisions se font avec ce qu'on appelle une <term>feuille
            de style</term>.</p>
        <list>
          <item>Sélectionnez <ident>XML Document</ident> et ensuite <ident>Associer une feuille de
              style</ident> à partir du menu <ident>Document</ident>. </item>
          <item>Naviguez jusqu'au fichier <ident>duBellay.css</ident> dans le dossier
              <ident>Travaux</ident> qui devrait se trouver sur votre Bureau, et associez-le (ce
            fichier est aussi disponible à l'URL <ref
              target="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/Oxford/2011-02-aix/Travaux/duBellay.css">sur le
              web</ref> ).</item>
          <item>Notez qu'une ligne contenant un "processing instruction" est ajouté au début de
            votre document.</item>
          <item>Contrôlez l'effet sur l'affichage de votre document au mode Auteur.</item>
        </list>
        <p>On peut changer cet affichage. Ouvrez le fichier <ident>duBellay.css</ident> avec Oxygen
          et modifiez-le, si cela vous intéresse. Mais il y a des limites : <list>
            <item>CSS n'est pas un langage XML, et ne permet que de modifier l'affichage du contenu
              d'un document XML.</item>
            <item>On peut changer la taille de police, l'étendu des marges, les couleurs etc.</item>
            <item>Changez la couleur du titre de <code>red</code> en <code>purple.</code></item>
          </list>
        </p>

        <p>Des transformations beaucoup plus intéressantes sont possibles avec un autre langage de
          feuille de style : le XSLT. On verra cela prochainement...</p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
