<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TP4 : Edition Numerique</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI MEET</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative
            Commons Attribution license.</p>
        </availability>
        <date>Jan 2011</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Some bits may be lifted from previous talks/workshops by the TEI
          Community.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Tagging for a digital edition </head>
        <p>In this exercise we'll revisit the Petrarch sonnet you worked on before. This time we will aim to produce a modern digital edition of the sonnet, by adding more tags specifically to :
<list>            <item>mark the modernizations</item>
            <item>add links to digital images of the manuscript</item>
	    <item>add  notes, commentary, bibliography...</item>
          </list>
        </p>
</div>

<div><head>Modernization</head> <p>Here's an image (kindly provided by
the Bodleian Library) of one of the 16th century manuscripts in which
this Petrarchan sonnet has come down to us.  <figure><graphic
width="70%"
url="Work/bodl_Canon.Ital.69_foll168C_frame11.jpg"/></figure>
</p><p>By comparison with this original manuscript, the text we are
used to reading has been modernized in several ways.  In the original
document, <list>

<item>there is almost  no punctuation and accented letters are used differently</item>
<item>certain words  are spelled differently</item>
</list>
</p><p>We will <soCalled>reverse engineer</soCalled> our modernized text to produce a more diplomatic transcript, without losing the modernization information.</p>

<list>
<item>Using Oxygen, open the version of the sonnet you worked on in the first exercise. (If you've lost it, use the version we made for you, in the file <ident>Work/corr-petrarch.xml</ident>). </item>
<item>Also open the image file <ident>Work/petrach-detail.jpg</ident> and compare the two carefully. </item>
<item>First identify the words which have different spellings. 
(For example, in line 7, the word <q>avea</q> was originally written <q>hauea</q>) </item>
<item>Select the modern reading and surround the word with the tag 
<gi>reg</gi> (regularized); then insert an element <gi>orig</gi> and type the original reading into it. </item>
<item>Finally, select both elements, and surround them with a third one : <gi>choice</gi>.</item>
<item><p>You should now have something like the following :</p>
<p><graphic url="../Graphics/havea.png"/></p></item>
 <item>See if you can find other similar changes and treat them in the same way.</item>
</list>

</div>

<div><head>Add links</head>
<p>To associate our transcribed text with its digitized image file, the easiest method is as follows:
<list>
<item>The poem starts at the beginning of a page, so we can  insert an empty  <gi>pb/</gi> element in front of it. This tag can then be associated with the image file that begins here using the <att>corresp</att> attribute (the <att>facs</att> attribute would be better, but that is not available in the TEI Lite schema we are currently using)</item>
<item>The image file is in the same folder as our transcription, so we can point to it with a simple URI like this: <code>&lt;pb corresp="petrarch-detail.jpg"/></code>. Alternatively, you could link directly to the image in the Bodleian Digital Library, using this link: 
 <code>&lt;pb corresp="http://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/external_collection?col=0e05dd457c794912b09f2eb2aaad791d"/></code>
</item>
</list></p>
</div>

<div><head>Add commentary</head>
<p>You can add your own footnotes and commentary, using the tag <gi>note</gi>. For example :
<list>
<item>At the start or end of the poem, you might insert a <gi>note</gi>
containing some information about this sonnet  : <q>a contemporary musical setting of the sonnet is found in Girolamo Scotto, <title>Il primo libro de i madrigali a doi voci</title> (Girolamo Scotto, Venice 1541)</q>
</item>
<item>You could tag the bibliographiuc reference using <gi>bibl</gi>, or associate it with a URL such as
<ref>http://http://www.gardane.info/bicinium/pagine/duo/scotto/scotto1541_25.php</ref>
</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Don't forget to save your file! You'll need it in the next exercise.</p></div>


</body></text></TEI>
