<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Exercise 10: OxGarage and the TEI Community </title>
                <author>TEI @ Oxford</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>July 2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Oxford</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative
                        Commons Attribution license.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Various previous talks, TEI Guidelines, etc.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>$LastChangedDate: 2012-05-28 10:23:52 +0100 $.</date>
                <name>$LastChangedBy: jamesc$</name>
                <note>$LastChangedRevision: 10412 $</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
       <div>    
           <head>Exercise 10: OxGarage and the TEI Community </head>
           <!-- Learning Outcomes -->
            <div>
                <head>Learning Outcomes</head>
                <p>When you successfully complete this exercise you should be able to:
                        <list type="bulleted">
                        <item>Us OxGarage to convert files from all sorts to and from TEI </item>
                        <item>Understand the limitations of automatic conversion </item>
                        <item>Explore the TEI Guidelines, Website, and Wiki</item>
                        <item>Know how to read and submit bugs and feature requests on the
                            TEI Sourceforge site</item>
                        <item>Subscribe to the TEI-L mailing list </item>
                        <item>Visit the TEI By Examples website for more self-directed
                            training</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>

            <!-- Summary -->
            <div>
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>This exercise is designed to give you some exposure to some of the
                    other TEI resources available online. Not only will you use OxGarage
                    to convert files to and from TEI, but be shown the limitations of such
                    conversions. You'll be directed to more parts of the TEI Guidelines,
                    the TEI-C Website, and the community-developed Wiki. The process for
                    submitting and reviewing bugs and feature requests will be reviewed,
                    along with how to subscribe to the TEI-L mailing list. The TEI By
                    Examples website will be suggested as a good place for further
                    self-directed study. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Starting Up</head>
                <p>This exercise will primarily use a web browser, we recommend Google
                    Chrome or a recent version of Mozilla Firefox. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>OxGarage: Have a quick play</head>
                <p>OxGarage is a pipelining transformation engine with a RESTful Web
                    Service (which in this case means it can be used by programs as well
                    as on the web) that converts documents from one format to another. <list>
                        <item>Go to <ref
                                target="http://oxgarage.oucs.ox.ac.uk:8080/ege-webclient"
                                >http://oxgarage.oucs.ox.ac.uk:8080/ege-webclient</ref> or
                            if this isn't working <ref
                                target="http://www.tei-c.org/oxgarage/"
                                >http://www.tei-c.org/oxgarage/</ref>.</item>
                        <item>Click on 'Documents' and select "TEI P5 XML Document" as
                            your input. When you do so a list of possible conversion
                            targets should appear on the right. Choose "Microsoft Word
                            Document (.docx)". </item>
                        <item>When you've done this a 'Choose File' button should appear
                            on the upper left. Click the button and navigate to your
                            finished (if well-formed and valid) file from way back in
                            Exercise 2. (If you didn't finish this, choose
                            'spoilers/ex02.xml' instead).</item>
                        <item>Click convert and open the document in Microsoft Word. Note
                            the information that is retained and the information that is
                            lost. </item>
                        <item>Try this again, but use a more complex file such the one
                            from Exercise 6 (if you didn't finish this, choose
                            'spoilers/ex06.xml' instead). Note how in conversion to DOCX
                            format that it attempts to interpret additions, deletions,
                            unclear, expansions, and representing them in presentational
                            markup. </item>
                        <item>Try converting to a variety of other formats and see the
                            results you get. (Note: Not all conversions are equal!)
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>More on OxGarage</head>
                <p>Of course, OxGarage isn't just about converting TEI files to other
                    formats, it can also convert other formats to TEI! See <ref
                        target="http://www.oucs.ox.ac.uk/oxgarage/"
                        >http://www.oucs.ox.ac.uk/oxgarage/</ref> for more information. <list>
                        <item>Take one of the formats you have converted (e.g. DOCX) a
                            file in, and edit that file in Microsoft Word. Add some new
                            text, and divisions to them. Use 'heading2' style (or similar)
                            to add a new division at some point and add a few lines of
                            text.</item>
                        <item>If they are available, use some of the in-line styles the
                            Word provides, and mark some text with them.</item>
                        <item>Try converting the file back to TEI and seeing what is
                            preserved (and what isn't!)</item>
                        <item>Although most conversions are 'lossy', this is a good
                            mechanism for getting a large number of documents into a basic
                            TEI P5 XML structure, to then do further conversion work on
                            this. One of the things we do for funded research projects is
                            take on the work of 'up-converting' their files from Word to
                            TEI P5, but deducing as much additional structure and markup
                            as we can. Usually this kind of conversion is different for
                            every project, but builds on the common base that we have put
                            into OxGarage. </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>The TEI Guidelines</head>
                <p> The TEI Guidelines are the main output of the TEI Consortium and
                    contain chapters on a wide variety of TEI recommendations. Hopefully
                    you've had a chance to read a bit of them already. <list>
                        <item>Go to <ref
                                target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index-toc.html"
                                >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index-toc.html</ref>.
                        </item>
                        <item>Note the division into 'Front Matter', 'Text Body', and
                            'Back Matter', look at the kinds of things present in each
                            section.</item>
                        <item>Choose a chapter from the 'Text Body' section and note how
                            the left-hand table of contents shows the general divisions
                            (and previous/next chapters) and how the small right-hand
                            navigation allows you to move forward/backwards through the
                            sections.</item>
                        <item>Notice also that greyed out '¶' character after any
                            sub-division (or sub-sub-division) heading. This is a link to
                            that section in particular. This is useful if you want to cite
                            a section of the TEI Guidelines in conversation. (e.g. on the
                            TEI-L mailing list) </item>
                        <item>Notice that all elements, attributes, classes, and datatypes
                            are links through to the reference pages about that object. </item>
                        <item>If you look at the examples provided, most of them will have
                            green backgrounds, which means that this snippet is valid in a
                            TEI file (assuming it was put in the right place). Some
                            examples might have amber (feasibly valid if some missing
                            elements were provided), or red (invalid against the default
                            schema). Sometimes it is necessary to show examples which are
                            invalid to demonstrate mixing of namespaces or when discussing
                            XML itself.</item>
                        <item>Click on any element name in the prose to go to the
                            reference page for that element. The information here can be
                            very useful when you want to look up what the definition of an
                            element is, where it is allowed, or what is allowed inside it.
                            At the bottom are one or more examples, and a link through to
                            a list of all the examples in the TEI Guidelines which use
                            this element. </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>The TEI Consortium Website</head>
                <p>The TEI-C Website <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/</ref> is the central location leading to
                    all things TEI related. <list>
                        <item>Click the 'Home' link on the menu (if you are still on the
                            TEI Guidelines), and look at the home page. Note the newsfeed
                            that is provided on the left, and the menu bar.</item>
                        <item>If you hover your mouse over the menus a drop-down menu
                            should appear, look at each menu and familiarise yourself with
                            the kinds of resources on the TEI-C website. </item>
                        <item>If you explore enough, you should also find items like the
                            minutes of meetings of the Board and Technical Council. The
                            TEI, where possible, attempts to conduct a large part of its
                            business publicly since it is really a product of its own
                            community (e.g. the Technical Council mailing list archives
                            are openly available for public viewing, and most of the work
                            is freely available on Sourceforge).</item>
                        <item>The TEI consortium provides XSLT stylesheets to transform
                            TEI to various formats. These are what underlie the OxGarage
                            conversions above. They are freely available for anyone to use
                            from the TEI Sourceforge Subversion repository. You can read
                            about them at Tools -> Stylesheets, or at: <ref
                                target="http://www.tei-c.org/Tools/Stylesheets/"
                                >http://www.tei-c.org/Tools/Stylesheets/</ref>.</item>
                        <item>Explore the rest of the TEI-C Website!</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>The TEI Wiki</head>
                <p>The TEI Wiki is a community developed location for all sorts of
                    TEI-related information. <list>
                        <item>Go to <ref target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/"
                                >http://wiki.tei-c.org/</ref> and read the main
                            page.</item>
                        <item>How many different XSLT Stylesheets are provided on the TEI
                            wiki?</item>
                        <item>How many pages on 'Tools' are there? </item>
                        <item>What Special Interest Groups (SIGs) have pages on the TEI
                            Wiki. Look at the Manuscripts SIG for an example. </item>
                        <item>Look on the Technical Council page, to see its last agenda. </item>
                        <item>In order to edit the wiki you need to request an account. If
                            you think this is something you'll need, why not do so now!
                            (It may take a couple days, it is approved by volunteers!)
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>The TEI Sourceforge Site</head>
                <p>The TEI Sourceforge site is currently used to manage the work of the
                    TEI Technical Council in maintaining the TEI Guidelines and various
                    tools that accompany them (e.g. Roma and the Stylesheets). It is also
                    the location that allows the community to submit bug and feature
                    reports. <list>
                        <item>Go to <ref target="http://tei.sourceforge.net/"
                                >http://tei.sourceforge.net/</ref> and notice that there
                            are links to the project summary, bug reports, feature
                            requests, file downloads and code repository. Explore each of
                            these!</item>
                        <item>Click feature requests or go to <ref
                                target="http://purl.org/tei/fr"
                                >http://purl.org/tei/fr</ref> (with no trailing
                            slash).</item>
                        <item>Look through some recently submitted feature requests and
                            click on one of them. </item>
                        <item>Read the details of the tick noting whether it has been
                            assigned to anyone, and whether there are any comments at the
                            bottom. If there are, read them.</item>
                        <item>Anyone who has registered for a Sourceforge account is able
                            to comment on tickets, and the TEI encourages community
                            participation. (So if you see a ticket you want to comment on,
                            register/log in and comment! </item>
                        <item> Returning to <ref target="http://tei.sourceforge.net/"
                                >http://tei.sourceforge.net/</ref> click on 'Code
                            Repository'. This allows you openly to browse the Subversion
                            repository used by the TEI for its development. </item>
                        <item>If you click on 'P5', 'Source', then 'Specs', you'll find
                            the folder of all of the specifications for individual
                            elements. If you choose one of these you'll see the revision
                            history for this element. </item>
                        <item>The Sourceforge site is a useful repository for the TEI that
                            allows it to undertake ongoing development in an open and
                            transparent manner. Being able to post bugs and feature
                            request here makes you part of this development effort.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>The TEI-L Mailing List</head>
                <p>The TEI-L mailing list is the main form of communication within the TEI
                    Community. Questions on there range from those entirely new to the TEI
                    to those who have been using the TEI for a couple decades. You should
                    not be afraid to post straightforward sounding questions, just make
                    sure you've checked the TEI Guidelines and Website first and are clear
                    about what you want to do and why you are confused. You will almost
                    certainly be guaranteed an answer, sometimes several competing ones!<list>
                        <item>Go to the TEI-L Archives at: <ref
                                target="http://listserv.brown.edu/archives/cgi-bin/wa?A0=TEI-L"
                                >http://listserv.brown.edu/archives/cgi-bin/wa?A0=TEI-L</ref>
                            (or click on the link in the last paragraph on the TEI-C
                            Website home page).</item>
                        <item>Read through some TEI-L messages from June 2012, choose some
                            which sound interesting based on their subject line.</item>
                        <item>Try sorting by Date (they are defaultly sorted by
                            Subject).</item>
                        <item>Try searching (on the right-hand side) for some keyword that
                            interests you.</item>
                        <item>Consider subscribing to the mailing list!</item>
                        <item>Another archive of the TEI-L messages are available from:<lb/>
                                <ref target="http://blog.gmane.org/gmane.text.tei.general"
                                >http://blog.gmane.org/gmane.text.tei.general</ref> and
                            another one at: <lb/> <ref
                                target="http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/"
                                >http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/</ref>.
                        </item>

                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>TEI By Example</head>
                <p>TEI By Example provides a variety of freely-available online tutorials
                    the demonstrate a number of different stages in encoding a TEI file.
                    There is a general introduction to text encoding and step-by-step
                    tutorials provide introductions to eight different aspects of TEI
                    markup with lots of examples. Real life examples are provided for each
                    tutorial and the theory provided can be tested with tests and
                    exercises. A tools section gives an annotated overview of XML encoding
                    technology and a validator for fragments of TEI. <list>
                        <item>If you have not already done so, visit TEI By Example at:
                                <ref target="http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/"
                                >http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/</ref>.</item>
                        <item>Choose a Tutorial that is interesting to you and skim read
                            the tutorial (you do not have to read it in depth at this
                            point, you may choose to do so later).</item>
                        <item>Look at the corresponding Examples section for that
                            Tutorial, and see what things you do not understand. (Look
                            them up in the Tutorial section).</item>
                        <item>Have a look at the corresponding Exercise for the Tutorial
                            section. (You don't need to do it, just get a sense of the
                            kind of exercises provided.) </item>
                        <item>TEI By Example is a good resource that it would benefit you
                            to return to at a later date and work through.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>




            <!-- Self-Assessment -->
            <div>
                <head>Self-Assessment</head>
                <p>Check if you understand some of the core principles of this exercise by
                    answering the following questions: <list>
                        <item>What is OxGarage good at? What is it not good at?</item>
                        <item>How do you get to an element's reference page on the TEI
                            Website?</item>
                        <item>What kind of information do you find on the TEI Wiki?</item>
                        <item>How do you submit a bug or feature request to the
                            TEI?</item>
                        <item>Have you joined the TEI-L mailing list? </item>
                        <item>What do you think of TEI-By-Example?</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>

            <!-- Next  -->
            <div>
                <head>Next?</head>
                <p>This is the last exercise of this workshop, and we hope you feel like
                    you've had a (quick!) but broad overview of some of the things the TEI
                    can do. Your learning is by no means complete! Read the TEI
                    Guidelines! Use TEI-By-Example! Join the TEI-L mailing list and ask
                    questions! If you have Oxford specific TEI questions you can email us
                    on <ref target="mailto:tei@oucs.ox.ac.uk">tei@oucs.ox.ac.uk</ref>, but
                    you are more likely to get a wider range of answers on the TEI-L
                    mailing list. All of the exercises will be made available from a link
                    on the DHOXSS website, and <ref target="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/"
                        >http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/</ref>. </p>
            </div>
</div>        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
