<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Exercise 9: Customise the TEI with Roma</title>
                <author>TEI @ Oxford</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>July 2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Oxford</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative Commons
                        Attribution license.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Various previous talks, TEI Guidelines, etc.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>$LastChangedDate: 2012-05-28 10:23:52 +0100 $.</date>
                <name>$LastChangedBy: jamesc$</name>
                <note>$LastChangedRevision: 10412 $</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div>
                <head>Exercise 9: Customise the TEI with Roma</head>
            <!-- Learning Outcomes -->
           
            <div>
                <head>Learning Outcomes</head>
                <p>When you successfully complete this exercise you should be able to: <list
                        type="bulleted">
                        <item>Analyse the TEI elements, attributes and values you need for your TEI
                            XML document </item>
                        <item>Tailor a TEI schema to your TEI XML file in Roma </item>
                        <item>Use a different schema in oXygen</item>
                        <item>Generate human-readable specifications of your TEI schema in Roma </item>
                        <item>Set the value of existing attributes</item>
                        <item>Be aware of the underlying TEI ODD XML format</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <!-- Summary -->
            <div>
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>In this exercise we will customise the TEI to remove those elements we do not
                    think we'll use. In order to customise a TEI schema you need to know which
                    elements you want to use, and which you don't, which sometimes involves a
                    lengthy document analysis process. In our case we'll shortcut that by telling
                    you what to include or not include. You will learn to create a new schema, and
                    download and use it in oXygen. You'll learn how to constrain the acceptable
                    values for an attribute, and require its presence. You'll have a look at the
                    underlying TEI ODD XML format which enables this customisation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Starting Up</head>
                <p>Load up the file 'spoilers/ex06.xml' in oXygen and save it under a new name. Open
                    up a web browser and go to <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Roma/"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/Roma/</ref>. (There is also a development version of
                    this at <ref target="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/Roma/"
                        >http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/Roma/</ref>.)</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Your Current Schema</head>
                <p>oXygen already knows about the TEI, it comes bundled with an open source TEI
                    Framework (oxygen-tei) that helps it understand how TEI files are meant to work. <list>
                        <item>In oXygen with 'spoilers/ex06.xml' (or whatever you saved it as)
                            loaded, move the cursor to just inside a paragraph after the opening
                                <gi>p</gi>.</item>
                        <item>If you type a '&lt;' at this point, as you know, oXygen will give you
                            a dropdown list of all the elements allowed inside a <gi>p</gi>. </item>
                        <item>Scroll down the list of elements, referring to the pop-up tooltip if
                            you want to know what the elements are for. Notice such elements as
                                <gi>address</gi>, <gi>camera</gi>, <gi>incident</gi>,
                                <gi>metamark</gi>, and <gi>notatedMusic</gi>.</item>
                        <item>Hit escape to leave the dropdown menu and delete the '&lt;' that you
                            had added.</item>
                        <item>You certainly have a lot of choices for elements you can add here! But
                            in any project it is unlikely that you are going to want all those
                            choices. Also, increased choice of what elements to add can lead to
                            greater human error and inconsistency, and we don't want that!</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Roma: Starting a New Schema</head>
                <p>Roma enables you to customise the TEI schema and remove those bits you are not
                    going to use. <list>
                        <item>Go to <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Roma/"
                                >http://www.tei-c.org/Roma/</ref> in your browser and note that you
                            are given four options from which to start: <list type="ordered">
                                <item><hi>Build up:</hi> this allows you to create a new
                                    customisation by <emph>adding</emph> elements and modules to the
                                    smallest recommended schema </item>
                                <item><hi>Reduce:</hi> this allows you to create a new customisation
                                    by <emph>removing</emph> elements and modules from the full
                                    tei_all (largest) schema</item>
                                <item><hi>Template:</hi> this allows you to create a customisation
                                    from a template provided by the TEI as a starting point</item>
                                <item><hi>Open:</hi> this allows you to open an existing
                                    customisation that you have saved previously. </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>In our case, let's start by choosing 'reduce', and clicking 'start'. </item>
                        <item>Set your parameters, change the following things: <list>
                                <item><hi>Title:</hi> 'TEI with maximal setup' is kind of boring,
                                    why not call it something like 'My special TEI customisation'. </item>
                                <item><hi>Filename:</hi> change 'tei_all' for something like 'myTEI'
                                    (don't include spaces). </item>
                                <item><hi>Author name:</hi> You aren't Sebastian! Change this to
                                    your name! </item>
                                <item>You can leave the description as it is for now.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Click 'Save' at the bottom of the page. Notice how the box in the
                            upper right tells you which customisation you are working on.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Adding and Deleting Modules</head>
                <p>Modules are groupings of TEI elements for structural or semantic reasons. For
                    example there is a 'dictionary' module which contains most of the elements
                    needed for writing dictionaries. If you aren't writing a dictionary, you
                    probably don't need that module. Below is a list of all the TEI modules:</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head>List of TEI Modules</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell>analysis </cell>
                        <cell>Simple analytic mechanisms</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>certainty </cell>
                        <cell>Certainty and uncertainty</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>core </cell>
                        <cell>Elements common to all TEI documents</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>corpus </cell>
                        <cell>Corpus texts</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>dictionaries </cell>
                        <cell>Dictionaries</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>drama </cell>
                        <cell>Performance texts</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>figures </cell>
                        <cell>Tables, formulæ, notated music, and figures</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>gaiji </cell>
                        <cell>Character and glyph documentation</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>header </cell>
                        <cell>The TEI Header</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>iso-fs </cell>
                        <cell>Feature structures</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>linking </cell>
                        <cell>Linking, segmentation and alignment</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>msdescription </cell>
                        <cell>Manuscript Description</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>namesdates </cell>
                        <cell>Names and dates</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>nets </cell>
                        <cell>Graphs, networks, and trees</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>spoken </cell>
                        <cell>Transcribed Speech</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>tagdocs </cell>
                        <cell>Documentation of TEI modules</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>textcrit </cell>
                        <cell>Critical Apparatus</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>textstructure </cell>
                        <cell>Default text structure</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>transcr </cell>
                        <cell>Transcription of primary sources</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>verse </cell>
                        <cell>Verse structures</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Click on the 'Modules' tab to go to the page that allows you to
                            add/delete modules from your schema.</item>
                        <item>Notice that because we've started with a 'maximal' schema, the list of
                            selected modules on the right is completely the same as the list of TEI
                            modules on the left.</item>
                        <item>Click 'remove' next to 'analysis' on the right-hand side. Note that it
                            vanishes from this list, but remains on the left-hand side where you
                            could add it back if you wanted it.</item>
                        <item>Remove 'analysis', 'certainty', 'corpus', 'dictionaries', 'drama',
                            'figures', 'gaiji', 'iso-fs', 'linking', 'nets', 'spoken', 'textcrit',
                            'verse', and 'tagdocs'! </item>
                        <item>Well! With removing that many maybe we should have started by building
                            up instead of reducing down? You should be left with: 'tei' (you can't
                            remove this one in Roma), 'core', 'header', 'msdescription',
                            'namesdates', 'textstructure', and 'transcr'. Why do you think we have
                            left these modules? </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Including or Excluding Elements</head>
                <p>We have shrunk down the TEI to just a few modules, but those modules contain
                    elements that we don't want. <list>
                        <item>Click on 'core' (note: not 'remove' but the word 'core') on the
                            right-hand side. This should take you to a page listing all of the
                            elements in the 'core' module. </item>
                        <item>Each row of this table has: <list>
                                <item>the element</item>
                                <item>whether it is Included or Excluded</item>
                                <item>the name being used for the element</item>
                                <item>a question mark linking to the reference page for this
                                    element</item>
                                <item>a description of the element</item>
                                <item>a link to change its attributes</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>It is possible to Include or Exclude all the elements by clicking this
                            word in the table header. </item>
                        <item>From 'core' exclude the following elements: 'addrLine', 'address',
                            'analytic', 'biblStruct', 'binaryObject', 'distinct', 'divGen', 'gb',
                            'headItem', 'headLabel', 'imprint', 'index', 'listBibl', 'measure',
                            'measureGrp', 'meeting', 'mentioned', 'monogr', 'postBox', 'postCode',
                            'relatedItem', 'rs', 'said', 'series', 'sp', 'speaker', 'stage',
                            'street', 'teiCorpus', 'term', 'textLang', and 'time'. </item>
                        <item>Wow! That's a lot less elements in your TEI schema. <hi>Remember to
                                click 'Save' at the bottom of the page!</hi></item>
                        <item>We could go through to each of the other modules removing elements
                            from there, but you get the idea. In a real life situation you would
                            work through carefully <emph>only</emph> including elements that you
                            really needed. The tighter your schema, the more consistent your data!
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Saving Your Schema</head>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>If you click on the 'Schema' tab you will see a drop down menu listing
                            various schema formats to generate. The TEI uses a meta-schema format of
                            its own called ODD which allows it to generate these different formats. </item>
                        <item>Generate a schema either in Relax NG Compact Syntax, or Relax NG XML
                            Syntax. These really are the best choice. </item>
                        <item>When you click 'generate' your browser should automatically download the
                            schema file. Find wherever it has saved it, and move it (not copy,
                            move) it to the place you have saved the 'ex06.xml' (or whatever you
                            saved it as) file. They should be in the same directory.</item>
                        <item rend="bold">Do not close down your browser window or you'll have to do
                            that all again.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Associating Your Schema in oXygen</head>
                <p>oXygen has been using the tei_all schema by default because it recognises (from
                    the TEI element in the TEI namespace) what kind of files we have been creating. <list>
                        <item>Go to oXygen and the file you have previously loaded ('ex06.xml' or
                            whatever you saved it as).</item>
                        <item>With this file open go to the 'Document' -> 'Schema' menu and note the
                            icon next to 'Associate Schema'. This icon should also be on your oXygen
                            toolbar. Click either the icon, or 'Associate Schema'. </item>
                        <item>Click on the little folder icon next to 'URL' in order to 'Browse for
                            local file'. Find the schema file you saved earlier, select it, and then
                            click 'OK' when back in the oXygen dialog box.</item>
                        <item>When you click 'Ok' then oXygen should add a line that looks something
                            lke this:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
&lt;?xml-model href="myTEI.rng" type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?></egXML>
                            at the top of your file. </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Trying It Out</head>
                <p>Remember those elements like 'address' and 'camera' that you could add within a
                    paragraph? <list>
                        <item>Go to somewhere just after a <gi>p</gi> opening tag, and insert an
                            '&lt;' to get a dropdown list from oXygen.</item>
                        <item>Are any of the elements you excluded available? No? Good! If they are,
                            then chances are you didn't click 'Save' after Including/Excluding them,
                            go back and do it again!</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Constraining the <att>type</att> Attribute on <gi>div</gi></head>
                <p>Removing elements is all well and good and is the first step in customising your
                    schema, but we want to do more. Let's customise the <att>type</att> attribute on
                        <gi>div</gi> to only allow certain values. <list>
                        <item>Go back to Roma in your browser (hopefully you didn't shut it and lose
                            all your work?)</item>
                        <item>Click on the 'Modules' tab.</item>
                        <item>Click on the 'textstructure' module name. </item>
                        <item> On the row containing 'div' click on 'Change Attributes' on the far
                            right-hand side. </item>
                        <item>This should take you to a page listing all the possible attributes on
                                <gi>div</gi>. This is also where you would include/exclude use of
                            those attributes if we wanted to change that. </item>
                        <item>Scroll down to 'type' and click on it. This should take you to a page
                            allowing you to set various options for the <att>type</att> attribute.
                            Set them as follows: <list>
                                <item><hi>Is it optional?</hi> This allows us to control whether the
                                    attribute is <emph>required</emph> or not. Let's make our
                                        <att>type</att> attribute required, so click 'no' it is not
                                    optional.</item>
                                <item><hi>Contents</hi> This would allow us to change what type of
                                    datatype is allowed and how many times it should appear. Let's
                                    leave that just as it is as 'Text'. </item>
                                <item><hi>Default value</hi> would allow us to set a default value
                                    for the attribute if you didn't supply one. Let's force
                                    ourselves to supply one and so leave this blank. </item>
                                <item><hi>Closed list?</hi> enables us to say whether our list of
                                    values is fixed, or merely a suggestion. Let's be rigorous and
                                    say that it is a closed list. Answer yes! </item>
                                <item><hi>List of values</hi> is where we give the values we want to
                                    supply to the schema as valid values for the <att>type</att>
                                    attribute on <gi>div</gi>. We give this as a comma-separated
                                    list. So write in:
                                        <code>prose,verse,drama,chapter,somethingElse</code>.
                                </item>
                                <item><hi>Description</hi> allows us to change the description of
                                    this attribute. Add the phrase 'Our modified type attribute ' to
                                    the start of the description. </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item rend="bold">Click 'Save' at the bottom of the page. </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Trying It Out Again</head>
                <p>Let's go try out the changes we made. You know how to do this now: <list>
                        <item>Click on the 'Schema' tab.</item>
                        <item>Choose one of the Relax NG formats from the dropdown list. </item>
                        <item>Click 'Generate' </item>
                        <item>Find where the file has downloaded it and copy it over the previous
                            version you had there. </item>
                        <item rend="bold">Do not close down your browser!</item>
                        <item>Go back to oXygen, and the 'ex06.xml' (or whatever you renamed it as)
                            file, and go to the 'Document' -> 'Validate' -> 'Reset Cache and
                            Validate' menu item. </item>
                        <item>You document should validate fine and you should have a happy green
                            square. </item>
                        <item>Go to the first <gi>div</gi> tag in the document that looks like
                                <code>&lt;div type="prose"&gt;</code> and change it to be just
                                <code>&lt;div&gt;</code>. </item>
                        <item>Your document should not be valid. You should have an angry red
                            square. If it is still valid 'Reset Cache and Validate' again, and
                            ensure that it is pointing to the correct schema. The error message it
                            should be providing is that that <code>element 'div' missing required
                                attribute 'type'</code> or something similar. </item>
                        <item>Put your cursor immediately after the 'v' in <gi>div</gi> and press
                            space. oXygen should provide a dropdown list of attributes available on
                                <gi>div</gi>. Scroll down until you find <att>type</att> and note
                            that it is in bold. This is because we made it required. </item>
                        <item>Select <att>type</att> and notice that oXygen gives you another
                            dropdown list of the possible values. This is because we provided the
                            values and said that this was a closed value list. </item>
                        <item>Choose one of the values, perhaps 'prose'. Your document should again
                            be valid and have a happy green square. </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Saving Your Customisation</head>
                <p>This is great, but what if you want to save your customisation, and come back
                    later to do more work? <list>
                        <item>Go back to your web browser and click on the 'Save Customization' tab. </item>
                        <item>Your browser should automatically start downloading an XML file. Move
                            it to somewhere convenient, for example where you put the schema.</item>
                        <item rend="bold">Do not shut your web browser yet!</item>
                        <item>This is the file that you could upload when going to the 'New' tab on
                            Roma (the very first page with the four choices), if you had selected
                            'Open existing customization'. (Don't do this now though!)</item>
                        <item>Open this XML file in oXygen. It might not be formatted or indented
                            properly. If not go to the 'Document' -> 'Source' -> 'Format and Indent'
                            menu, or click the Format and Indent icon on the toolbar, or press
                            'control-shift-p'.</item>
                        <item>Read through the file to get a sense of how it relates to your
                            customisation. Note how <gi>moduleRef</gi> includes those modules you
                            have asked for, and how the 'core' module is included except for the
                            list of attributes you excluded. </item>
                        <item>Look at the <gi>elementSpec</gi> for <gi>div</gi> and see how we've
                            changed it. </item>
                        <item>Note that this file is a TEI file just like the ones you've been
                            editing, it just uses special elements from the 'tagdocs' module.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Generating Reference Documentation</head>
                <p>Roma does not only generate schemas, but also customised reference documentation. <list>
                        <item>If you return to your web browser and click on the 'Documentation'
                            tab.</item>
                        <item> Choose HTML web page from the dropdown menu and click 'Generate'. </item>
                        <item>If your browser has downloaded the file, instead of opening it, open
                            the saved file with your web browser.</item>
                        <item>You should get a web page starting with a table of contents listing
                            the elements. Scroll down and click on <gi>div</gi>. </item>
                        <item>Notice that this has the <att>type</att> attribute as required, and
                            lists the legal values. Notice, however, that the example has not
                            changed and it says <code>type="poetry"</code> in that.</item>
                        <item>Try generating some PDF documentation as well. Which do you
                            prefer?</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>More About Roma</head>
                <p>Roma the web front-end is a bit of a dated interface to a command line script and
                    the OxGarage web service. When you generated the documentation this used
                    OxGarage and you didn't even notice!</p>
                <p>Some people write their TEI ODD customisation files entirely in XML and do not
                    use the Roma web interface at all. There are a number of things that the Roma
                    web interface can't do which the TEI ODD language underneath is capable of.
                    Notice, for example, that you weren't able to provide descriptions of each of
                    the attribute values you entered for <att>type</att>? You can do that in the
                    underlying XML. Some people do a combination of both Roma and hand editing.</p>
                <p>There is also a 'Sanity Checker' tab... click that and find out what happens! (It
                    might warn about the element <gi>term</gi> being used in <gi>keywords</gi> but
                    not being defined. That is fine!)</p>
            </div>
            <!-- Self-Assessment -->
            <div>
                <head>Self-Assessment</head>
                <p>Check if you understand some of the core principles of this exercise by answering
                    the following questions: <list>
                        <item>What is Roma?</item>
                        <item>How do you add and remove TEI modules using Roma?</item>
                        <item>How do you include/exclude individual elements using Roma? </item>
                        <item>How can you change attributes using Roma? </item>
                        <item>Is it possible to save your customisation in Roma? </item>
                        <item>What kinds of documentation can you generate in Roma? </item>
                        <item>What kinds of schemas can you generate in Roma? </item>
                        <item>What does an underlying TEI ODD customisation file look like? Is it a
                            TEI file like the ones you've been working with?</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <!-- Next  -->
            <div>
                <head>Next and More Reading</head>
                <p>Next we'll move on to some of the other tools and utilities offered by the TEI
                    Consortium. But first consider reading more about TEI ODD at: <list>
                        <item><ref
                                target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM"
                                >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM</ref>.</item>
                        <item>and also the Documentation Elements chapter at <ref
                                target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html"
                                >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html</ref>.</item>
                        <item>See also, <ref target="http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm"
                                >http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm</ref>.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
