<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Exercise 1: Create an XML Document</title>
        <author>TEI @ Oxford</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>July 2012</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Oxford</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative Commons Attribution
            license.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Various previous talks, TEI Guidelines, etc.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>$LastChangedDate: 2012-05-28 10:23:52 +0100 $.</date>
        <name>$LastChangedBy: jamesc$</name>
        <note>$LastChangedRevision: 10412 $</note>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
        <div>
            <head>Exercise 1: Create an XML Document</head>
      <!-- Learning Outcomes -->
      <div>
        <head>Learning Outcomes</head>
        <p>When you successfully complete this exercise you should be able to: <list type="bulleted">
            <item>mark up an XML declaration</item>
            <item>insert a text file into an XML editor</item>
            <item>mark up basic features of a poem</item>
            <item>create a well-formed XML document</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <!-- Summary -->
      <div>
        <head>Summary</head>
        <p>This exercise will walk you through creating an XML document in the oXygen editor and
          introduce a variety of ways to mark this document up. You will first start a new document,
          then insert some unmarked up text into the editor, and then mark up the stanzas or
          line-groups (lg) and lines (l). You will learn to check that your document is well-formed
          or not. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Starting A New XML File</head>
        <p> Let's start a new XML file by following the following steps: <list type="bulleted">
            <item>Load up the oXygen XML Editor if it isn't already loaded by using the Windows Start Menu, or double-clicking
              the icon on the desktop. </item>
            <item>Once the editor has fully loaded from the 'File' menu select 'New' and under 'New
              Document' select 'XML Document'. This should open up a blank document with an XML
              Declaration added.</item>
            <item>An XML Declaration looks like:
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
              </egXML>
              and The XML declaration in the element tells anything processing your XML file, including
              the editor, that this is an XML file and what version of XML you are using through the
              @version attribute. It also conveys which characters the program may expect in
              attribute @encoding. XML version 1.0 is a W3C recommendation from 2008. UTF-8
              (Universal Character Set Transformation Format - 8 bit) contains most characters from
              all human writing systems. The XML declaration needs no closing tag as it takes the
              form of a special processing-instruction that starts and ends with an angle-bracket
              and a question mark. </item>
          </list></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Creating a Division</head>
        <p>Let's create a division of a text using the <gi>div</gi> element. This is a generic
          division or section element. <list type="bulleted">
            <item>On the line below the XML declaration type: <gi>div</gi>.</item>
            <item>Notice what happens when you type the final '&gt;'. oXygen is trying to help you
              and inserts in the closing <gi>/div</gi> tag. This is because it knows the rules of
              XML, and knows that if you type an opening <gi>div</gi> you are required to have a
              closing <gi>/div</gi> sooner or later.</item>
            <item>We haven't said what type of division this is, so lets categorise it as 'verse' by
              adding a @type attribute. Move the cursor back until your just after the letter 'v' in
              the opening tag. Press space, and then type: <code>type="</code> and notice what
              happens when you type the quotation mark. oXygen is again trying to help you by
              putting the closing quotation mark, because it knows that attribute values must always
              be quoted.</item>
            <item>In between the quotation marks type '<code>verse</code>' to categorise our division
              as being verse.</item>
            <item>Move back until you are directly in between the opening <gi>div</gi> and closing
                <gi>/div</gi>. Press 'enter' a couple times to give yourself some space inside the
              element.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Inserting Some Text</head>
        <p>We are going to use the Wilfred Owen poem <title>Strange Meeting</title> as an example
          for this exercise. But it would waste a lot of time if we asked you to type the whole poem
          in, so we've done that for you. <list type="bulleted">
            <item>Make sure your cursor is in-between the opening <gi>div</gi> and the closing
                <gi>/div</gi> and go to the <hi>Document</hi> menu and select 'File' and from there
              then 'Insert File'. <hi>Note: This is from the 'Document' menu on the menu bar, not
                the 'File' one.</hi></item>
            <item>Select 'strange-meeting.txt' as the file to insert.</item>
            <item>The start of your document should look like:
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> 
                &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
                  <div type="verse"> 
                    STRANGE MEETING 
                    
                    It seemed that out of battle I escaped
                    Down some profound dull tunnel, long since scooped
                    Through granites which titanic wars had groined. 
                    
                    [...a lot more text...] 
                  </div>
              </egXML>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Encoding the Heading (using 'Surround with Tags')</head>
        <p>The text 'STRANGE MEETING' at the top of the poem is obviously a heading. The TEI
            <gi>head</gi> element should be used to mark this. To mark this do the following: <list
            type="bulleted">
            <item>Highlight the text 'STRANGE MEETING' with the mouse.</item>
            <item>Either press control-e as a shortcut key, or right-click and under 'Refactoring'
              select 'Surround with Tags'. A box should pop up and type <code>head</code> into it.
              Notice how oXygen helps you again by putting the opening tag before what you had
              highlighted and the close tag afterwards.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Marking Stanzas (using both 'Surround with Tags' and 'Split Element')</head>
        <p> Let's mark the stanzas that appear doing the following steps: <list type="bulleted">
            <item>Highlight the first stanza, from "It seemed" to "had groined".</item>
            <item>Using control-e, or the menus, as you did above, mark this stanza as an
                <gi>lg</gi> element.</item>
            <item>Add a @type attribute with a value of 'stanza' to the <gi>lg</gi> element so it
              looks like: <gi>lg type="stanza"</gi>.</item>
            <item>The start of your document should now look like:
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
                <div type="verse">
                  <head>STRANGE MEETING</head>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                    It seemed that out of battle I escaped
                    Down some profound dull tunnel, long since scooped
                    Through granites which titanic wars had groined.
                  </lg>
    
                  [...a lot more text...] 
                  </div>
            </egXML>
            </item>
            <item>But if we have lots of stanzas, marking each one of them seems a lot of work, but
              there is a (possibly) easier way.</item>
            <item> Highlight the entire rest of the poem, from "Yet also there" to "Let us sleep
              now....'", and then surround all of it in an <gi>lg</gi> element (by pressing
              control-e)</item>
            <item>Of course it is silly to have the entire rest of the poem marked as a single
              line-group, but go and add a type="stanza" attribute to the opening tag. </item>
            <item>If you move the cursor to just before the start of each stanza, e.g. just before
              where it says "With a thousand pains", and press alt-shift-d (or select Refactoring ->
              Split Element from the right-click menu), oXygen should split the <gi>lg</gi> element,
              ending it here and starting it just before where there cursor is located. </item>
            <item>Do this for other stanzas that are not marked yet.</item>

          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Marking Lines</head>
        <p> We've marked all the stanzas but we've not marked the lines. <list type="bulleted">
            <item>Highlight the first line in the first stanza, press control-e to surround with a
              tag, and type 'l' as the element name. (<gi>l</gi> is the line element, meaning a line
              of metrical verse). </item>
            <item>It might be a bit painful to mark up each and every line this way, you could try
              using the split-element technique above, but there is another shortcut to try as well.
              Highlight the second line and press control-/ and notice that oXygen has wrapped the
              line in a <gi>l</gi> element. The reason for this is that control-/ is the 'surround
              with the last element I surrounded something with' shortcut key.</item>
            <item>Using this technique, quickly mark all the remaining lines.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Format and Indent</head>
        <p>Our poem is marked up, but some of the markup might be a bit messy. <list type="bulleted">
            <item>Make sure that your file is 'well-formed'. You'll be able to tell it is
              well-formed because oXygen will have a happy green square in the upper right-hand
              corner. If it is red, you better find the problem (where a red bar on the right-hand
              side is) and correct the mistake! </item>
            <item>Now let's format and indent our file. This tidies up some of the whitespace and
              indents elements based on their place in the hierarchy. Either select the 'Format and
              Indent' icon from the toolbar (it looks like some indented lines), or go to the menus:
              'Document' -> 'Source' -> 'Format and Indent'.</item>
            <item>Formatting and indenting your markup is not necessary, it could all be on one big
              long line, but it makes it much easier for other people to read. </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <!-- Saving Your Work -->
      <div>
        <head>Saving Your Work</head>
        <p> Let's save our work: <list>
            <item>Is your work well-formed? Do you have a happy green square or an angry red
              one?</item>
            <item>From the 'File' menu select 'Save' or click on the Save icon (looks like an
              old-style 3.5" disk)</item>
            <item>Save the file using the name 'exercise01.xml' or another name of your
              choice.</item>
          </list></p>
      </div>

      <!-- Self-Assessment -->
      <div>
        <head>Self-Assessment</head>
        <p>Check if you understand some of the core principles of this exercise by answering the
          following questions to yourself: <list>
            <item>How do you start a new XML document in oXygen?</item>
            <item>What is an XML declaration?</item>
            <item>What is a well-formed document?</item>
            <item>How do I 'Surround with tag' and repeat that action quickly?</item>
            <item>Why might using the 'Split element' approach be useful?</item>
            <item>What is the function of each element and attribute in your current file? </item>
            <item>What is the advantage of formatting and indenting your markup? </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <!-- Next  -->
      <div>
        <head>Next?</head>
        <p> Your XML file may be well-formed but it is not yet <hi rend="bold">valid</hi> because it
          doesn't validate against a particular schema (such as those which are customisations of
          the TEI). Next we will have a short introduction to the structure of TEI documents and
          some of the most frequently used elements. If you are finished early you may wish to
          browse through the TEI Guidelines online at <ref
            target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index-toc.html"
            >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index-toc.html</ref>. In particular
          you might want to look at the Elements appendix of reference pages for individual
          elements. Consider looking up all the elements you've used in this file to see how they
          are defined. </p>
      </div>
        </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
