<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Exercise 2: Create a TEI Document</title>
        <author>TEI @ Oxford</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>July 2012</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>University of Oxford</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative Commons Attribution
            license.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Various previous talks, TEI Guidelines, etc.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>$LastChangedDate: 2012-05-28 10:23:52 +0100 $.</date>
        <name>$LastChangedBy: jamesc$</name>
        <note>$LastChangedRevision: 10412 $</note>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
        <div>
            <head>Exercise 2: Create a TEI Document</head>
      <!-- Learning Outcomes -->
      <div>
        <head>Learning Outcomes</head>
        <p>When you successfully complete this exercise you should be able to: <list type="bulleted">
            <item> discern the elements and attributes needed for a minimum valid TEI XML file </item>
            <item>associate a TEI XML file with a schema </item>
            <item>have used the TEI namespace</item>
            <item>create a minimum TEI header and text body </item>
            <item>check for both validity and well-formedness</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <!-- Summary -->
      <div>
        <head>Summary</head>
        <p>This exercise will walk you through creating a TEI XML file and inserting the work you
          did previously into it. You'll learn about the required aspects of the <gi>teiHeader</gi>
          and the basic structure of a TEI file. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Start a New XML File</head>
        <p>Follow the same steps you did for the first exercise to start a new blank XML file.
          Although we could start a file with a TEI P5 template, for this particular exercise that
          would be cheating! <list type="bulleted">
            <item>Load up the oXygen XML Editor if it isn't already loaded by using the Windows
              Start Menu, or double-clicking the icon on the desktop. </item>
            <item>Once the editor has fully loaded from the 'File' menu select 'New' and under 'New
              Document' select 'XML Document'. This should open up a blank file with an XML
              Declaration added.</item>
            <item>An XML Declaration looks like:
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
              </egXML>
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Inserting a <gi>TEI</gi> Element</head>
        <p>All TEI files start either with a <gi>TEI</gi> element or a <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element.
          In most cases you'll want a <gi>TEI</gi> element. These elements have a special
          psuedo-attribute called 'xmlns' that indicates the namespace a set of elements are from.
          This is inherited by any elements inside it (unless overridden). This is how we can be
          sure we're talking about, say, a <gi>title</gi> element from the TEI rather than any other
          schema. <list type="bulleted">
            <item> Add a <gi>TEI</gi> element and then add it to the TEI namespace
              (http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0). Maybe add a few blanks line between the starting and
              closing tag. Your file should look like:
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="false">
                  &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> 
                  &lt;TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    
                  
                  &lt;/TEI>
              </egXML>
            </item>
            <item>Notice what happens in oXygen and how it helps you input this. Also notice that
              your file may now have an angry red square rather than a happy green one! Is your file
              well-formed? (yes, it is!) Why is this red then? </item>
            <item> If it is red it is because your version of oXygen is prepackaged with all sorts
              of TEI goodness, and in this case it recognises that files starting with <gi>TEI</gi>
              in the TEI namespace are to be associated automatically with a TEI schema that it has
              stored. It is complaining that you do not have a <gi>teiHeader</gi> in your file
              because all valid TEI files must have this.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Adding a <gi>teiHeader</gi></head>
        <p> Inside the <gi>TEI</gi> element we need to add a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element. <list
            type="bulleted">
            <item>Put the cursor between the starting and closing <gi>TEI</gi> element and type in a
                <gi>teiHeader</gi> element. Notice that oXygen provides the closing
                <gi>/teiHeader</gi> element. If the correct option is set in oXygen, it understands
              the TEI schema and knows that certain content is required inside a
              <gi>teiHeader</gi>. It can automatically provide that markup. If not, you'll have to
              type it in. The resulting file should look like:
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="false">
                  &lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title> </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt> </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc> </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
</TEI>
             </egXML>
            </item>
            <item> Notice that your file still has an angry red square rather than a happy green
              square. This is because there is still stuff needed even though you've added some
              markup. First, add a title of something like "My 'Strange Meeting' document" by adding this
              text between the starting and closing <gi>title</gi> tags. There are other elements
              which are allowed here in <gi>titleStmt</gi> such as <gi>author</gi> (Wilfred Owen),
                <gi>editor</gi> (Jon Stallworthy), that you could add but aren't really required for
              this exercise. You could use the more general <gi>respStmt</gi> (with a <gi>name</gi>
              element with your name and a <gi>resp</gi> element with something like 'TEI P5
              Encoding' in it) to record your own work if you wish, but as with the other
              embellishments this isn't necessary for this exercise. </item>
            <item> Then add a paragraph <gi>p</gi> inside the <gi>publicationStmt</gi> with some
              text to record what this file is for, perhaps something like "An exercise for learning
              TEI." </item>
            <item>Inside sourceDesc we should add a <gi>p</gi> with some text like: "The primary
              resource of this file is Strange Meeting from Jon Stallworthy's edition, available on
              the First World War Poetry Digital Archive." To make this even better, we might
              surround the title 'Strange Meeting' with a <gi>ref</gi> element with a
                <att>target</att> attribute with a value of
              'http://www.oucs.ox.ac.uk/ww1lit/collections/item/3350' because that is URL from which
              we got this text.</item>
            <item> Your <gi>teiHeader</gi> should now look something like:
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
       <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>My 'Strange Meeting' document</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>An exercise for learning TEI.</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p> The primary resource of this file is <ref target="http://www.oucs.ox.ac.uk/ww1lit/collections/item/3350">Strange
                        Meeting</ref> from Jon Stallworthy's edition, available on the First World
                    War Poetry Digital Archive. </p>

            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
              </egXML>
            </item>
            <item>Notice that even though this is a complete <gi>teiHeader</gi> with all the
              required aspects, our file as a whole isn't valid.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Add a <gi>text</gi></head>
        <p>All TEI files, in addition to a <gi>teiHeader</gi> with <gi>fileDesc</gi> containing a
            <gi>titleStmt</gi>, <gi>publicationStmt</gi>, and <gi>sourceDesc</gi>, need to follow
          the header with at least one of: <gi>sourceDoc</gi>, <gi>facsimile</gi>, or <gi>text</gi>.
          In our case we're going to add a <gi>text</gi> element. To do this: <list type="bulleted">
            <item>Add a couple of blank lines after the closing <gi>/teiHeader</gi>.
            </item>
            <item> Insert a <gi>text</gi> element and inside that a <gi>body</gi> element. (The
                <gi>text</gi> element requires a <gi>body</gi> element because if you don't have a
              text body, what are you encoding?)</item>
            <item> The <gi>text</gi> section of the file should look something like:
              <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <text>
        <body>     
         <!--We will put our poem here  -->      
              
        </body>
        
    </text>
              </egXML>
            </item>

          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Adding Our Poem</head>
        <p>This is a good start but we need to put something inside the body. Luckily, we have already
          encoded a poem in the previous exercise, so we can use that! <list type="bulleted">
            <item>With the cursor in between the opening and closing <gi>body</gi> tags go to the
              'Document' menu on the menu bar, and select 'File', and 'Insert File'. Select the file
              you saved earlier if you finished the first exercise. If you didn't then in the
              spoilers directory there is a file called 'ex01.xml' which has the completed first
              exercise.</item>
            <item> But wait, as soon as you've added this we get a bit of a problem! oXygen will
              complain that we've got an XML declaration in the middle of our file. Delete this
              redundant XML declaration!</item>
            <item> Your document should now be valid and have a happy green square in the upper
              right-hand corner! If it isn't, try to solve the problem by looking at the error
              message that is provided.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Saving Your Work</head>
        <p> Let's save our work: <list>
            <item>Have you formatted and indented your work automatically? </item>
            <item>Is your work well-formed? Do you have a happy green square or an angry red
              one?</item>
            <item>From the 'File' menu select 'Save' or click on the Save icon (looks like an
              old-style 3.5" disk)</item>
            <item>Save the file using the name 'exercise02.xml' or another name of your
              choice.</item>
          </list></p>
      </div>

      <!-- Self-Assessment -->
      <div>
        <head>Self-Assessment</head>
        <p>Check if you understand some of the core principles of this exercise by answering the
          following questions: <list>
            <item> Which elements and attributes do you need for a minimum valid TEI XML document? </item>
            <item>What three parts of the <gi>teiHeader</gi> are required in all TEI conformant
              documents?</item>
            <item>Where are these elements and attributes allowed? </item>
            <item>What is the function of each element and attribute you've used? </item>
            <item>Why do you think these elements and attributes are required in TEI XML? </item>

          </list>
        </p>
      </div>

      <!-- Next  -->
      <div>
        <head>Next and More Reading</head>
        <p> This exercise and the previous one should have given you some experience editing XML and
          making a valid TEI file. Next time we'll get an more in-depth introduction to various
          other TEI modules and learn more about the <gi>teiHeader</gi>. <list>
            <item>If you are finished early you may wish to
              browse through the TEI Guidelines online at <ref
                target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index-toc.html"
                >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index-toc.html</ref>.</item>
            <item>In particular you might want to look at the Elements appendix of reference pages for individual
              elements. Consider looking up all the elements you've used in this file to see how they
              are defined.</item>
            <item>What other elements are allowed inside the <gi>text</gi> element? What would you use them for?</item>
            <item>What other parts of the <gi>teiHeader</gi> are there? What are they for?</item>
            <item>You may wish to read the chapters on Default Text Structure <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DS.html">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/DS.html</ref>
              or Elements Available to All TEI Doccuments <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html</ref>.
            </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
        </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
