<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Oxygen: tutoriel</title>
        <author>Lou Burnard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>MEET</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative Commons Attribution
            license.</p>
        </availability>
        <date>juin 2011</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Some bits may be lifted from previous talks/workshops by the TEI Community.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>


      <head>Before you begin...</head>
      <p>In this and subsequent exercises you will be using the XML editor Oxygen to work with data
        files we've prepared for you. Oxygen should be installed on your work stations already: you
        can start it up by just clicking on the Oxygen XML Editor icon on the desktop, or selecting
        it from the Programs menu in the usual way. <!-- graphic of XML Editor icon needed -->
      </p>
      <p>We recommend you to keep all the files you make during the exercises in a single folder. We
        refer to this below as your <ident>Work</ident> folder. We will put this in place in your
        home directory, with all the files you'll need. </p>



      <div>
        <head>Editing TEI-XML using Oxygen - 1</head>
        <p>In the first part of this little tutorial you will learn how to use Oxygen to : <list>
            <item>create a born digital XML document</item>
            <item>add XML tags to a document</item>
            <item>continously validate the document against a simple schema</item>
            <item>display the document in various ways</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Oxygen can be configured for use in several languages, including English, French, German,
          and Italian. If you'd prefer to work in some language other than English, use the
          Preferences command, the first option on the Options menu (fifth from left on the menu
          bar), to change it. This tutorial mostly assumes you are using the English version, though
          some of the illustrations are taken from the French version, and so may not match exactly
          what you see on the screen.</p>


        <!--
<p>Si Oxygen n'est pas encore installé sur votre poste, vous pouvez
l'installer facilement:
<list>
<item>copiez sur votre bureau les fichiers
<ident>oxygen-licence.txt</ident> et <ident>oxygen.exe</ident> (pour
Windows) ou <ident>oxygen.zip</ident> (pour MAC). Si ces derniers ne
sont pas disponibles, vous pouvez les télécharger du site Oxygen à
<ptr
target="http://www.oxygenxml.com/download_oxygenxml_editor.html"/>
</item>
<item>Cliquez sur l'icone du fichier approprié à votre machine et
suivez la procedure d'installation indiquée.</item>
<item>La première fois que vous lancerez le
logiciel, il vous demandera de copier-coller le contenu du licence,
qui est contenu dans le fichier <ident>oxygen-licence.txt</ident>. Ce
licence est temporaire: vous pouvez en telecharger une autre du site
ci dessus.</item>
</list></p>
    -->
        <div>
          <head>The born-digital document</head>
          <p>The TEI is not just for encoding ancient documents from their paper or stone originals.
            It's also useful for the creation of new documents, starting <foreign>ex
              nihilo</foreign>....</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Creating a document</head>
          <list>
            <item>Start Oxygen. </item>
            <item>Click on the New icon top left (or choose New from the File menu, or type CTRL-N)
              to open the New dialog box )</item>
            <item>Oxygen offers you a choice of various pre-defined templates for your new document,
              grouped under four headings ("Recently used", "New Document", "Global templates", or
              "Framework templates" in English). These groups are organised hierarchically : you can
              open or close subgroups by clicking the blue key icon to the left of the folder icon. </item>
            <item>Open the last group <ident>Framework templates</ident>, then within it <ident>TEI
                P5</ident>, then <ident>Bare</ident>, to choose a very simple TEI schema. </item>
            <item>
              <graphic height="5cm" url="../Graphics/new-bare-1.png"/>
            </item>
            <item> Click the <ident>Create</ident> button at the bottom. Oxygen displays a minimal
              TEI document, which we will now complete.</item>
          </list>

          <p>By default, Oxygen shows you a number of windows. In the centre is the main workspace,
            containing your document. At lower left, you can see the <ident>Summary</ident> window
            which gives you a view of the hierarchic structure of your document. </p>
          <p>
            <graphic height="2cm" url="../Graphics/outline-1.png"/>
          </p>
          <p>As you see, a TEI document is divided in two : the upper part, tagged
              <gi>teiHeader</gi> contains metadata ; the lower part, tagged <gi>text</gi> contains
            the data. </p>
          <p>
            <graphic height="5cm" url="../Graphics/nouveau-bare-2.png"/>
          </p>
          <p>As before, you can open or close parts of the Outline display by clicking the blue key
            icon. If you click on a tag name in the Outline view, the corresponding part of the
            document itself is selected in the Editor window.</p>
          <p>At the bottom of the Editor window you can see three buttons labelled Text Grid and
            Author. These change the way the document is displayed : for the moment, since we are
            not afraid of tags, we will stay in the default Text mode, but you may like to click on
            the others to see what they do. </p>
          <p>Let's begin by giving our document the three pieces of essential metadata needed for
            every TEI document : a title, a note on its publication, and another note on its
            sources. Oxygen has proposed some default text for each which needs to be completed or
            corrected ... <list>
              <item>Replace the word <q>Title</q> (between the tags <gi>title</gi> and
                  <gi>/title</gi>) by a title for your document. It's up to you to find a good
                title! Something like <q>Experimenting with Oxygen</q> will do, but you may want to
                be more specific. </item>
              <item>Replace the two other bits of text by some appropriate phrases. For example, you
                might put something like <q>Unpublished draft</q> or <q>Distributed on my blog</q>
                in the publication statement, depending on your ambitions for this text. For the
                  <gi>sourceDesc</gi>, even though there is no pre-existing source, you are required
                to put something: we suggest <q>An original work, produced as part of a TEI-Epidoc
                  Workshop</q>. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Oxygen always tries to keep your document valid. What happens if you mess things up? <list>
              <item>Delete a few letters within any tag : for example, change
                  <gi>publicationStmt</gi> to <gi>publicat</gi>. </item>
              <item>Oxygen does its best. First, it changes the corresponding end-tag to match (so
                it becomes <gi>/publicat</gi>): the document is thus still well formed. But it's no
                longer valid -- there is no such element as <gi>publicat</gi> in the schema.
                Consequently the faulty tags are underligned in red, there's an error message at the
                foot of the screen, and on the right there are some red marks indicating visually
                where the error occurs. .</item>
              <item>Click on one of the red marks and see if you can follow the logic by which one
                error leads to another.</item>
              <item>Click CTRL-Z (or choose <ident>Undo</ident> from the <ident>Edit</ident> menu)
                to return to a state of grace ... you will see that the little red square at top
                right becomes green when all errors have been corrected.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Oxygen also encourages you to keep your document valid. It can offer you a choice of
            tags to enter, but it will offer only those which are valid at the current point in the
            document. <list>
              <item>Put the cursor at the end of the 7th line, or the start of the 8th, between
                  <gi>/title</gi> and <gi>/titleSmt</gi>;</item>
              <item>type <code>&lt;</code> and pause ;</item>
              <item>the green square becomes red because you have not yet entered the name of an
                element.</item>
              <item>Oxygen suggests a list of the tags which can legally appear at this place in the
                document : at this point, you can add an <gi>author</gi> element, or another
                  <gi>title</gi>, close the <gi>titleStmt</gi>, or insert an XML comment. </item>
              <item>Let's take the first suggestion : select <gi>author</gi> and hit RETURN. Oxygen
                will insert both start and end-tags for the new element.</item>
              <item>Note that the cursor stays inside the opening tag <gi>author</gi> just in case
                you now want to enter some attributes for it (type a space if you are curious to see
                what attributes are available). Move the cursor one character to the right and type
                your name, since you are the author of the file.</item>
              <item>You may like to experiment to see what other elements are available at other
                points in the document : as you will see, this is a really simple schema with very
                few elements.</item>
            </list>
          </p>

        </div>


        <div>

          <head>Adding text to the document</head>
          <p>Now let's start adding some real content to our document. It's up to you what you write
            and (within limits) how you tag it. </p>

          <p>To start with, how will your document be organized? A document containing just one
            paragraph, though possible, seems unlikely. The schema we are using allows you to mark
            up : <list>
              <item>sections or subsections or subsubsections or ... (we will call them all
                divisions). Tag these with <gi>div</gi>
              </item>
              <item>headings for the divisions. Tag these with <gi>head</gi></item>
              <item>lists, also containing headings, labels and items. Tag these with <gi>list</gi>,
                  <gi>head</gi>, <gi>label</gi>, or <gi>item</gi> as appropriate</item>
              <item>paragraphs. Tag these with <gi>p</gi></item>
            </list> Let's go !</p>

          <p>In the rest of this part of the tutorial we will start showing you some of the tricks
            and short cuts provided by the Oxygen program. . </p>

          <p>Firstly, a big question. Obviously, the program can't generate the actual content of
            the document we're writing, but do we really have to type in all the tags as well ? Not
            at all : Oxygen is there to help. You've already seen how it can suggest a list of
            possible elements to be inserted at a given point in the text. It can also propose tags
            to wrap around any part of the document. </p>

          <list>
            <item>With your mouse, select <emph>the whole content</emph> of the <gi>body</gi>
              element, i.e. the start and end tags for the <gi>p</gi> and the three words it
              contains <code>&lt;p>Some text here&lt;/p></code>. </item>
            <item>Type CTRL-E or choose <ident>XML Refactoring - Surround with Tags </ident> from
              the <ident>Document</ident> menu.</item>
            <item>Oxygen offers you a choice of all the elements it knows about. Choose the one that
              makes sense here : <gi>div</gi>. Then click on <ident>Accept</ident></item>
            <item>This <gi>div</gi> element will contain the first section of your document. You
              might like to give it a title, by inserting a <gi>head</gi> element before its first
              paragraph. </item>
            <item>It would also be useful to number your divisions explicitly : for that you can use
              the attribute <att>n</att> which is available on every TEI element, including
                <gi>div</gi>. </item>
            <item>Put the cursor <emph>inside</emph> the <gi>div</gi> tag, just before the &gt; et
              type a space. Oxygen offers a list of available attributes. </item>
            <item>Choose <att>n</att> and hit RETURN. Oxygen warns you that you must supply a legal
              value for this attribute, and the cursor remains inside the quote marks.</item>
            <item>Type (for example) <code>1</code>, and your document becomes valid once more.
            </item>
          </list>

          <p>Your document should now look like this :</p>
          <p>
            <graphic height="3cm" url="../Graphics/body-shot.png"/>
          </p>
          <p>Now you need to add some text to the paragraph : hopefully a bit more interesting than
              <q>some text here</q> ! Describe your first reactions to Oxygen ; give us your views
            on the current economic crisis ; write about your childhood -- it's up to you! The point
            of the exercise is to get you used to the idea of writing in an XML editor as easily as
            you would write in a word processor.</p>
          <p>No doubt you will soon feel the need for a new paragraph, or for a bulleted list. How
            do you close the current paragraph and start a new one? Just hitting RETURN a couple of
            times doesn't seem to work. Is there a better way of doing this without having to type
            the tags <gi>/p>&lt;p</gi> ? Of course there is. </p>
        </div>


        <div>
          <head>Divide and conquer</head>
          <p>Let's assume you have several hundred words in one paragraph, which you now want to
            split up into several paragraphs. </p>
          <list>
            <item>Put the cursor at each point where you want to split the paragraph </item>
            <item>Type CTRL-ALT-D or choose <ident>XML Refactoring - Split element</ident> from the
                <ident>Document</ident> menu.</item>
          </list>
          <p>You can of course do exactly the same thing to split up your one <gi>div</gi> element.
            Take care that you choose the right place to do the splitting though. You must put the
            cursor <emph>between</emph> two <gi>p</gi> elements, not within one of them.</p>
        </div>



        <div>
          <head>Making tagged text readable</head>
          <p>Are you beginning to worry about the amount of tagging in your document ? </p>
          <p>You can tidy up the tagging you've inserted by clicking on the "Format and Indent"
            button, typing CTRL+SHIFT+P, or choosing <ident>Source->Format and Indent</ident> from
            the Document menu. But maybe you'd rather just get rid of all the tags ?</p>
          <list>
            <item>At the bottom of the screen there are three tabs : Text Grid and Author. Choose
              the last of these. The way your document is displayed now looks quite different, and
              there is also a new menu TEI P5. Choose <ident>Tags Display Mode</ident> and look at
              the various possibilities it offers</item>
            <item>You can display the tags as little icons, large icons, or not at all</item>
            <item> Note also that your document is now formatted -- different elements have
              different colours, and the layout is more like that of a word processor. </item>
            <item>In Author mode, you <emph>can</emph> split an element just by hitting RETURN
              twice. Try it!
              <!-- Attention : en mode auteur
Oxygen vous propose plusieurs éléments possibles qui ne sont pas
disponibles dans le schéma Bare : il faut s'en méfier.--></item>
          </list>


          <p>Later on, we will see how you can control the formatting of your document using a
              <term>stylesheet</term>.</p>

          <p>After all this work, don't forget to save your document in your Work folder ! </p>

        </div>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>À la découverte d' Oxygen - 2</head>
        <p>In this second part of the exercise we'll experiment with using Oxygen to : <list>
            <item>encode a pre-existing document in TEI XML</item>
            <item>represent some typical literary structures</item>
          </list>
        </p>

        <div>
          <head>Sample text</head>
          <p>In this essay we will encode a Petrarchan sonnet, respecting its organization into
            stanzas and lines. To make your life easier, we have prepared a transcription already
            for you, so you don't need to do quite so much typing as in the previous exercise...
          </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Create a new document</head>

          <p>As you did before, open Oxygen and click on the New icon at top left to open the New
            document dialogue. This time, when asked to choose which schema to use, we suggest you
            select <ident>TEI P5</ident> and then <ident>TEI-Lite</ident>. This will give you a more
            useful schema than the minimalist one we used in the first exercise.<list> <item>As
                before, Oxygen gives you the basic TEI structure, with a few extra components. </item>
              <item>Complete the TEI header quickly, as you did before. We suggest the following as
                title <q>A Petrarchan Sonnet in TEI-XML format</q>, and as source <q>Transcription
                  taken from "Il Canzoniere" di Francesco Petrarca, edited by Gianfranco Contini.
                  Edizione Einaudi, 1964</q></item>
              <item>Remove everything proposed as content for the <gi>body</gi> element, taking care
                to retain the <gi>body</gi> et <gi>/body</gi> tags. </item> </list>
          </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Adding text to the document</head>
          <p>You can, of course, type out the poem for yourself as you did before. But this time we
            propose the following method : <list>
              <item>Check that your cursor is <emph>between</emph> the <gi>body</gi> and
                  <gi>/body</gi> tags in your empty document </item>
              <item>Choose <ident>File -> Insert File</ident> from the <ident>Document</ident> menu
                  (<hi>Note: Not the File Menu on the menu bar, but the one found under the Document
                  Menu!</hi>)</item>
              <item>Navigate to the file <ident>sonnet.txt</ident> which you will find in your
                working folder, select it and click Open.</item> <item>Your document is full of red
                lines but don't panic! we will sort that out in a moment. Look at the error message
                at the foot of the screen and see if you understand it.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Adding structure to the body of a document</head>
          <p>The structure of a document is important. In this case, the body contains : <list>
              <item>a heading ... to be tagged with <gi>head</gi>
              </item>
              <item>an octet and a sestet ... both to be tagged with <gi>div</gi></item>
              <item>four stanzas ... to be tagged with <gi>lg</gi></item> <item>14 lines ... to be
                tagged with <gi>l</gi></item> </list> Let's go !</p>


          <list>
            <item>Select the first two lines <q>Canzoniere (Rerum vulgarium fragmenta) VII
              </q></item>
            <item>Type CTRL-E and choose <code>head</code> from the list of available tags ; then
              click <ident>Accept</ident></item>

            <item>For extra marks, you may want to cut this heading in two, distinguishing the
              number (which is the number of the sonnet) from the general title which precedes it.
              If so, put the cursor before the number <q>VII</q> and use CTRL-ALT-D or some other
              way of splitting the heading as you did in the previous exercise.</item>
          </list>

          <p>Now for the poem itself. Our goal is to have each verse line tagged <gi>l</gi>
              (<q>line</q>), each stanza tagged <gi>lg</gi>, the octet tagged <gi>div
              type="octet"</gi> and the sestet tagged <gi>div type="sestet"</gi>. </p>
          <p>Of course there's more than one way to do this. We suggest one fairly quick way, but
            feel free to experiment with other approaches ! <list>
              <item>Select with your mouse the whole of the text of the poem. </item>
              <item>Surround the whole poem with one <gi>l</gi>. </item> <item>All the red lines
                disappear and the little green square reappears ! Have we finished? Sorry, no : a
                document can be valid while still containing lies... and it's a lie that a sonnet
                contains only one line! Lies can also be dangerous : hit the Indentation button on
                the toolbar (or type CTRL-SHIFT-P). </item>
            </list>
            <graphic height="3cm" url="../Graphics/onelineonly.png"/></p>
          <p>Since the line endings are not explicit in the markup, Oxygen is not obliged to respect
            them when formatting the display. To be both honest and explicit, we need to split this
            one line into fourteen. (If you can't remember where to split the line, you can bring
            back the original display by typing CTRL-Z) </p>
          <list>
            <item>Put the cursor at the end of the first verse line and type ALT-SHIFT-D </item>
            <item>Use the down arrow key to move down to the end of the next line and repeat </item>
            <item>(Or, if you prefer to live dangerously, you can also cut and paste the sequence
                <code>&lt;/l>&lt;l></code> at the end of each line).</item>
            <item>When you've finished, check that everything is correct by typing CTRL-SHIFT-P or
              hitting the Indentation button again.</item>
            <item>You now need to repeat essentially the same manoeuver for the stanzas : select all
              the lines and wrap them in an <gi>lg</gi>, then split that <gi>lg</gi> after the
              fourth, eighth, and 12th lines. (Take care that you do this splitting in the right
              place! your cursor should be between the end of one <gi>l</gi> and the start of the
              next, i.e. after the <gi>/l</gi> and before the following <gi>l</gi>) </item>
            <item>Finally, we suggest wrapping the first two stanzas in a <gi>div type="octet"</gi>
              and the second two in a <gi>div type="sestet"</gi>
            </item>
          </list>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Changing the display</head>
          <p>As you've already seen, Oxygen can display the hierarchic structure of our sonnet -- if
            you look in the Summary window to the left you should now see something like this : </p>
          <p><graphic height="4cm" url="../Graphics/summary-2.png"/>. </p>
          <p>And you can also, as before, switch to Author mode to see the text nicely formatted
            with no tags. </p>

          <p>The way texts are displayed in Author mode is determined by a series of instructions
            supplied by a separate document called a <term>stylesheet</term>. We will learn more
            about this tomorrow. To conclude this part of the exercise we'll show you how to make a
            few changes in the Author mode display of your sonnet.</p>
          <list>
            <item>First, put your document into Text mode</item>
            <item>Select <ident>XML Document</ident> et <ident>Associate stylesheet</ident> from the
                <ident>Document</ident> menu.</item>
            <item>In the dialogue that opens, click the CSS tab. Click the arrow at extreme right,
              select "Look for local file" and then navigate to a file called
                <ident>petrarch.css</ident> in your <ident>Work</ident> folder. Press Select.</item>
            <item>A line containing a "processing instruction" is added to the start of your
              document</item>
            <item>Now see what happens when you switch to Author mode.</item>
          </list>
          <p>You can edit the stylesheet to get different effects if you like. Open
              <ident>petrarch.css</ident> with Oxygen. But take care : <list>
              <item>CSS is not itself an XML language, but its syntax is fairly self evident. </item>
              <item>It is fairly simple to change the size of a font or the margins for all elements
                of a specified type </item>
              <item>For this exercise, we suggest you just try changing the colour of the title from
                purple to red. </item>
            </list>
          </p>

          <p>More complex transformations are easy with a more powerful stylesheet language called
            XSLT, as you will see tomorrow..</p>

        </div>
      </div>





      <div>
        <head>À la découverte d' Oxygen - 3</head>
        <p>In the third part of this tutorial you will learn how Oxygen can be used to : <list>
            <item>transform an existing Word document into TEI XML</item>
            <item>search for markup in a TEI XML document</item>
            <item>transform a TEI XML document into a different format </item>
          </list>
        </p>



        <div>
          <head>Something dramatic</head>
          <p>You've seen how to make a valid TEI document out of nothing at all, and out of a plain
            text file. In reality, many documents start life in a word processor such as Word or
            Open Office. Can Oxygen work with those too? </p>
          <p>In your Work folder you have a small Word document called <ident>goldoni.docx</ident>.
            This contains just the start of a famous Italian play from the 18th century: Goldoni's
              <hi rend="italic">Servitore di due padroni</hi>. You may like to open it to check that
            it is in fact a Word document, with nice formatting and no sign of any pointy
            brackets.</p>
        </div>


        <div>
          <head>Transformation from Word to TEI</head>
          <p>How can we convert this document into TEI-XML?</p>
          <p>We could save it in <soCalled>plain text</soCalled> format and use that ; we could cut
            and paste the text into Oxygen. But either method would be tiresome and would also lose
            information, such as the italic font which distinguishes (for example) stage directions
            from parts of a speech. </p>
          <p>Since this Word file uses formatting in a consistent way, using Word styles, it's
            possible to transform it to XML more or less automatically, losing very little
            information. Oxygen can be configured to do this for you, but we will use a different
            tool for a change. </p>
          <list>
            <item>Open your Internet browser, and visit
                <ref>http://www.tei-c.org/ege-webclient/</ref></item>
            <item>Click <ident>Text Documents</ident>. In the list of different formats proposed,
              check the box for Microsoft Word Docx</item>
            <item>A list of target formats appears to the right. Check the box for TEI P5
              XML.</item>
            <item>At the top of the screen a <ident>Browse</ident> button appears. Click on this and
              navigate to the file <ident>goldoni.docx</ident> in your <ident>Work</ident>
              folder.</item>
            <item>Click the big <ident>Convert</ident> button ... be patient </item>
            <item>The Garage will send you (after a brief delay) a file called
                <ident>goldoni.xml</ident>. Save it in your <ident>Work</ident> folder. (Note that
              if you are using Internet Explorer, you may have to reassure the software that you
              really do want to download this dangerous XML file)</item>
          </list>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Tag translating</head>
          <p>Let's see what OxGarage has made out of our Word file. At least it's a valid TEI
            document, even if it is full of lies...</p>
          <list>
            <item>Start up Oxygen, et open the file <ident>goldoni.xml</ident> which you just
              created.</item>
            <item>Don't look at the TEI Header for the moment : you can complete that later. Scroll
              down to the start of the play. </item>
            <item>If you look at the summary view, or change briefly to Author mode, you will see
              that the conversion has correctly identified the act and scene structure. It has
              however converted each speech into a <gi>div</gi>, containing a <gi>head</gi> and a
                <gi>p</gi>. This makes our life much easier. (It happened because in the Word file,
              we used a heading style to mark each speaker prefix )</item>
            <item>In Text view, put the cursor into any one of the <gi>div</gi> tags</item>
            <item>From the <ident>Document</ident> menu choose the <ident>XML-Refactoring -> Rename
                Element </ident> command (or type ALT-SHIFT-R).</item>
            <item>
              <p>Oxygen displays this dialogue box </p>
              <p>
                <graphic height="5cm" url="../Graphics/rename.png"/>
              </p>
            </item>
            <item>In the <code>New name</code> box, change <code>div</code> to <code>sp</code>,
              which is the name of the element we want, and check the box <ident>Rename all elements
                with the same name</ident>
            </item>
            <item>Click <ident>OK</ident> and all the <gi>div</gi> elements become <gi>sp</gi>s.
              (Our document is no longer valid, but we will fix that in a moment.)</item>
            <item>Now repeat this manoever for all the <gi>head</gi> elements : turn these all into
                <gi>speaker</gi> elements.</item>
            <item>Our document is still invalid : the <gi>div</gi> elements marking the scene and
              act divisions should not have been converted. But there are only a few of these, so it
              is not so hard to change them back. Click on the <gi>sp</gi> tag immediately before
              the words <q>ATTO PRIMO</q> and type ALT-SHIFT-R. This time click the <ident>Rename
                current element </ident>radio button before choosing <code>div</code> as the
              replacement.</item>
            <item>Repeat the manoever to rename the <gi>speaker</gi> element containing the words
              ATTO PRIMO as <gi>head</gi>. Repeat it again so that the sequence
                <gi>sp</gi><gi>label</gi><code>SCENA PRIMA</code> gets retagged as
                <gi>div</gi><gi>head</gi><code>SCENA PRIMA</code></item>
            <item>If you do this correctly, lots of red marks should disappear. Click on the first
              one still remaining to move down to the next scene, where you will need to repeat the
              manoever for a third time, so that the sequence <gi>sp</gi><gi>label</gi><code>SCENA
                SECONDA</code> gets retagged as <gi>div</gi><gi>head</gi><code>SCENA SECONDA</code>
              (You can also just correct the tags by retyping them if you like).</item>

          </list>
          <p>The stage directions in our text have all been converted to <gi>hi
              rend="Caption_Characters"</gi> elements because they were styled with a style of that
            name and we did not provide any mapping for that style name in the Word to TEI
            conversion. For the moment, simply convert all the <gi>hi</gi> elements to
              <gi>stage</gi> using the Rename Element command again. </p>
          <p>Finally, we will remove all the redundant <code>rend="Normal"</code> attribute
            specifications. This is easily done using the <ident>Find</ident> menu</p>
          <list>
            <item> Select the text <q> rend="Normal"</q> somewhere on the screen.</item>
            <item>Choose Find/Replace on the Find menu, or type CTRL-F</item>
            <item>Check <ident>Case sensitive</ident> and <ident>Wrap around</ident> in the Options
              . Uncheck the box labelled Enable XML search options. The dialog should look like this
              : </item>
            <item>
              <figure>
                <graphic url="../Graphics/noNormal.png"/>
              </figure>
            </item>
            <item>Press Replace All</item>
          </list>
          <p>If you'd like to improve your file further, here are some suggestions: <list>
              <item>Use the <att>type</att> attribute to distinguish different kinds of stage
                direction</item><item>Turn the sequence of <gi>p rend="Text body indent"</gi>
                elements at the start into a cast list, tagged with <gi>castList</gi>.
                </item><item>Look for words of Venetian dialect and mark them with
                <gi>foreign</gi></item><item>Add some information to the Header, such as the correct
                title and author, your name as encoder, and the source of this text (It is
                transcribed from the "Commedia", di Carlo Goldoni volume primo, nona edizione
                collezione: I grandi libri Garzanti Garzanti editore Milano, 1992 )</item>
            </list></p>
          <p>You'll notice that we did not specify a schema to use for this document. Consequently
            all the TEI elements are available for you to use... </p>
          <p>If you get lost or can't finish don't worry. Our suggested version of the file is
            available for you to look at in the file <ident>corr-goldoni.xml</ident>! </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Transformation du fichier</head>
          <p>Vous avez deja vu Oxygen faire une transformation de XML : si vous affichez votre
            document en mode Auteur, vous allez voir que les titres sont maintenant plus jolis,
            numerotés et mises en evidence, et que les annotations sont affichees avec une police
            plus petite, mais peut etre pas à l'endroit que vous les attendiez.</p>
          <p>Essayons d'autre transformations. Il serait impressionant de transformer notre fichier
            directement en HTML ou PDF pour l'afficher, n'est-ce pas? <list>
              <item>Sur le barre aux outils, il y a un bouton qui contient une fleche rouge. Cliquez
                la dessus (ou taper CTRL-MAJ-T, ou sélectionnez Document -> Transformation ->
                Appliquer le scenario de transformation ) </item> <item>En Oxygen un <q>scenario
                  de transformation</q> associe un document avec une feuille de style, et la fait
                tourner. Par défaut, vous voyez <code>TEI P5 XHTML</code> et <code>TEI P5
                PDF</code>. Séléctionnez le scenario qui vous plait, et regardez ce qu'il donne, en
                cliquant le bouton <ident>Transformer maintenant</ident>. Experimentez-l' autre
                !</item>
              <!--              <item>Bien sur, on peut configurer ces transformations à volonté, et en créer des
                nouveaux. Pour vous en donner le goût, on va finir en vous proposant une
                transformation qui n'a rien à faire avec la visualisation.</item>
-->
            </list></p>
          <!--
          <p>La feuille de style qui controle une transformation s'écrit dans un autre langage XML,
            qui s'appelle XSLT : sujet fascinant, mais peut etre pas pour les debutants. Vous
            trouverez quelques exemplaires de feuilles de styles XSLT dans votre dossier. Pour en
            servir, il faut créer une nouvelle transformation en Oxygen <list>
              <item>Cliquez sur la flèche rouge (CTRL-MAJ-T) de nouveau</item>
              <item>Cliquez le bouton <ident>Nouveau</ident> pour ouvrir la fenetre Nouveau
                Scenario. Dans cette fenetre: <list>
                  <item>choisir un nom pour le scenario : on vous propose "texte-brut"</item>
                  <item>specifier la location du fichier XSL souhaité, en cliquant sur le petit
                    icone dossier jaune à droite du champs <ident>XSL URL</ident>. Ceci vous permets
                    de naviguer au dossier <ident>Travaux</ident> : sélectionner le fichier
                      <ident>texte-brut.xsl</ident> et cliquer <ident>Ouvrir</ident>.</item>
                  <item>sélectionnez <ident>Saxon HE 9</ident> du menu <ident>Transformateur</ident>
                  </item>
                  <item>Cliquer <ident>Accepter</ident> pour terminer, et <ident>Transformer
                      Maintenant</ident> pour voir le resultat. </item>
                </list></item>
            </list></p>
          <p>Comme vous voyez, c'est possible de transformer notre document XML ou bien dans un
            format d'affichage, ou bien dans un format d'analyse tres classique. </p>
    -->
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
