<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advanced use of ODD : workshop proposal</title>
            <author>Lou Burnard Consulting</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Prepare pour MUTEC</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>ne numerique</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="20140206">Revised after initial comments from Mutec</change>
         <change when="20140201">Initial draft on eurostar</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Workshop objectives</head>
            <p>ODD ("One Document Does it all") is an XML documentation system in the literate
               programming paradigm which was originally designed as a means of expressing
               customizations of the TEI. Its current version, however, goes beyond this to provide
               a generic tool for the documentation and management of any XML encoding scheme, not
               necessarily one based on the TEI, although it is most often used in that context.</p>
            <p>A major difficulty for TEI novices has always been how to select amongst the hundreds of elements and attributes defined within it. An ODD provides a well defined way of declaring that selection once it has been made, ut the procedure of defining an ODD remains mystwerious for many, despite the existence of tools suchj as Roma which provide a simpler intereface.</p>
            <p>In this workshop we hope to shed light on these mysteries. More concretely,
               participants will gain:</p>
            <list>
               <item>a detailed practical knowledge of the whole of the currently defined ODD
                  system</item>
               <item>an understanding of the various ways in which it may be used to customise the
                  TEI (séléction and modification of components, addition of new components)</item>
               <item>an understanding of the formal TEI specifications for elements, macros, and classes, together with their use in the construction of the TEI schema </item>
               <item>hands on experience in the creation and develpment of TEI schemas adapted to the needs of specific projects dealing with a variety of primary materials</item>
               <item>experience in the use of currently available ODD processing  tools </item> 
            </list>
            <p>The Workshop will be of most use to people whose role includes training
               non-technically-oriented staff on the best use of ODD, or otherwise providing
               technical support to the TEI community. </p>
            <p>Amongst other topics we intend to cover the following: <list>
                  <item>going beyond Roma: how to use ODD for documentation;</item>
                  <item>using Schematron to implement additional constraints</item>
                  <item>how to chain ODDs together </item>
                  <item>using "ODD by example" to generate an ODD; comparison between this and a
                     project defined ODD </item>
                  <item>conversion between exclusive and inclusive style ODDs; implications of the
                     choice</item>
                  <item>concepts, implementation, and implications of "Pure ODD" </item>
               </list></p>
         
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Practical details</head>
            <p>The workshop will run for a full day, and will consist of a mixture of discussion,
               formal presentations, and hands-on practical work. For the latter, participants will
               be expected to provide their own laptops (unless a training room with workstations is
               available). Although any XML-editor may be used, the materials we prepare will assume
               that an up to date installation of oXyGen is available on each participant's
               machine.</p>
            <list type="gloss">
               <label>public</label>
               <item>No more than 10-15 participants will be accepted. They should have some
                  knowledge of the basics of TEI and of XML. General IT skills (for example, file
                  management, how to use an editor etc.) are assumed. </item>
               <label>trainers</label>
               <item>The workshop will be run by  Lou Burnard and Sebastian Rahtz <ab/>. </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Provisional programme</head>
         
              
                  <list>
                     <label>morningi</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>Discussion de l'usage actuel de ODD dans les projets de
                              participants: ils souhaitent traîter quels types de document et en
                              quelles manières? quels problèmes rencontrés, quels opérations
                              d'amélioration, de maintenance ou de contrôle ils souhaiteraient
                              mener? </item>
                         
                           <item><ref target="initODD.xml">Initiation au format ODD</ref> : syntaxe des spécifications ; exercice
                              simple de création d'un ODD non-TEI élémentaire ; concept de "Pure
                              ODD".</item>
                           <item>Rappel de l'organisation et du contenu de la TEI : <ptr target="carteTEI.xml"/> </item>
                           <item><ref target="talk-cartes.xml">Cas d'étude</ref> : construction d'un ODD pour le balisage des cartes
                              postales avec Roma ; puis génération d'un ODD à partir d'un corpus de
                              documents existants : comparaison et discussion des deux méthodes.</item>
                                                </list>
                     </item>
                     <label>afternoon</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item><ref target="teiODD.xml">ODD "under the hood"</ref> : présentation of TEI P5 source code.  explication de
                              fonctionnement de quelques personnalisations ; usage de moduleRef ; ODD par
                              inclusion ou exclusion : implications techniques et mode de conversion. </item>
                           <item>Gestion, validation et traitement d'un ODD avec Oxygen et d'autres outils.
                              Principes de conformité. Niveau de formalisation nécessaire dans la chaîne de
                              pérennisation CINES-TGIR Huma-num </item>
                           <item>Revue et discussions </item>   
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
            
            
         </div>
      
        <div>    <head>Literature</head>
           <listBibl>    <bibl>
               <note>Specification complète du langage ODD</note><ref
                  target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html"
                  >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html</ref></bibl>
            <bibl><note>Description du traitement des fichiers ODD</note>
               <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM"
                  >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM</ref></bibl>
            <bibl>
               <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Support/Learn/odds.xml">Getting started with P5
                  ODDs</ref>
               <note>Article discursif (P5)</note></bibl>
           <bibl><title>Resolving the Durand Conundrum</title>
              <author>Lou Burnard</author> <ref target="http://jtei.revues.org/842">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative: Issue 6 | December 2013 </ref><note>Article introducing and explaining some proposed modifications to the ODD System; implemented as "Pure ODD"</note></bibl> 
              <!--Lou Burnard, « Resolving the Durand Conundrum », Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative [Online], Issue 6 | December 2013, Online since 22 January 2014, connection on 06 February 2014. URL : http://jtei.revues.org/842 ; DOI : 10.4000/jtei.842-->
              <bibl>
               <ref target="http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm"
                  >http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm</ref>
               <note>Introduction tutoriel (P4)</note></bibl>
            <bibl><ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml"
               >http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml</ref>
               <note>Introduction tutoriel</note></bibl>
            <bibl>
               <author>
                 Lou Burnard
               </author>
               <author>
                 Sebastian
                  Rahtz
               </author><title>RelaxNG with Son of ODD</title>
               <ptr
                  target="http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2004/Burnard01/EML2004Burnard01.html"/>
               <title level="m">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages 2004</title>
               <note>Technical description of the new ODD system developed for TEI P5.</note>
            </bibl>
            <bibl><author>James
               Cummings</author>
               <title level="m">ODDly Pragmatic: Documenting encoding practices in Digital
                  Humanities projects</title><ref
                     target="http://blogs.it.ox.ac.uk/jamesc/2013/09/21/oddly-pragmatic/">[Blog
                     entry summarizing talk given at JADH 2013]</ref>
            </bibl></listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
