<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_minimal.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_minimal.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Converting Word documents to TEI XML in oXygen</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Can you convert Word documents to TEI XML in oXygen?</head>
         <p>Yes you can!</p>
         <p>A Word docx file is actually a compressed archive containing several other files,
            including XML files which can be manipulated and converted in the same way as any other
            XML file. oXygen knows this, and comes with predefined XSLT stylesheets for converting
            from docx to TEI P5. The conversion can also take into account any Word styles found,
            which makes it possible to customize the way your Word file,is converted, in order to
            produce more intelligent markup than would otherwise be possible.</p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>In this little tutorial we'll step through the process, using as example a test file
            produced by the DifDepo project. If you want to play along, you can download the test
            file from <ref
               target="https://code.google.com/p/tei-fr/source/browse/trunk/Projects/Difdepo/Testfiles/testStyles.docx"
               >here</ref></p>
         <list>
            <item>In oXygen, use the usual Open dialog to select the docx file</item>
            <item>A window opens to the left of the main screen headed "Navigateur d'Archives". It
               shows the file structure of the docx archive.</item>
            <item><graphic url="navigateur-1.png"/></item>
            <item>Click the blue key next to the folder called word to see the contents of this
               folder</item>
            <item><graphic url="navigateur-2.png"/></item>
            <item>Select the file called document.xml and double click to open it (may take a few
               moments if the file is large)</item>
            <item><graphic url="document-word.png"/></item>
            <item>As you see, this is an XML document, with lots of XML tags, using many different
               namespaces, most of them defined by Microsoft. Let's convert it!</item>
         </list>

         <list>
            <item>With the <ident>document.xml</ident> file open in your main editing window, select
                  <ident>Transformation -> Configurer les Scenarios de transformation</ident> from
               the <ident>Document</ident> menu. Or type <code>CTRL-MAJ-C</code>. Or click the
               little spanner icon (this one : <graphic url="spanner.png" height="7mm"/>) </item>
            <item>oXygen shows you the transformation options available for this kind of document.
               This should include one called DOCX TEI P5, which is the default TEI conversion. </item>
            <item><graphic url="configurer-1.png"/></item>
            <item>To see what it does, check the little box next to it, and press the<ident>
                  Appliquer associe(s</ident>) button at the bottom. A new window opens at the
               bottom of the screen in which oXygen displays messages relating to the conversion
               process ; you may safely ignore these. </item>
            <item>In the main editing window, you should now see a TEI-conformant document. (Choose
               Source > Indenter le document from the Document menu, or type CTRL-MAJ-P or click the
               Indent button (this one: <graphic url="indent.png" height="7mm"/>) if it is displayed
               as a single line on the screen) Scroll down to see how the Word styles have been
               converted. </item>
            <item><graphic url="converted-1.png"/></item>
            <item>Note that many of the paragraphs have a rend attribute. The values of this
               attribute correspond with the Word style used in the original docx file. You can use
               these values to make a more intelligent conversion.</item>
         </list>
         <list>
            <item>Close the tab labelled Test_tous-styles-TEI-P5.xml to return to the window
               containing document.xml, your source Word document.</item>
            <item>Click on the spanner again to reopen the Configurer Scenarios de Transformation
               dialog and this time click the Edit button at the bottom. This will enable you to
               reconfigure the bdefault conversion process.</item>
            <item>You can't modify a built in configuration scenario, so oXyGen offers to make a
               copy for you to play with. <graphic url="yesno.png"/>. Press <ident> Oui.</ident>
            </item>
            <item>The <ident>editer le scenario ANT </ident> is displayed to enable you to configure
               your new version of the transformation scenario. <graphic url="editer-scenario-1.png"
               /></item>
            <item>Let's begin by changing its name to something sensible: change "DOCX TEI P5
               copier" to "DOCX TEI P5 Oulipo" for example.  Then press the Parametres tab to see
               what else can be modified.</item>
            <item><graphic url="editer-scenario-2.png"/></item>
            <item>This dialog allows us to change the default input and output paths for this
               transformation and also to specify a <term>profile</term>. The TEI Stylesheet package
               included with oXygen supplies a small number of predefined sets of customized
               stylesheets called profiles. You can use or modify an existing profile to get the
               effects you want in your own project (not covered here). In this exercise, we will
               use the Oulipo profile. </item><item>Select the word Profile and  press the Edition button. </item>
            <item/>
            <item><graphic url="modifier-parametre.png"/></item>
            <item>Add the word oulipo in the box labelled Valeur and press Accepter to return to the
               Editer le scenario Ant dialog. Press Accepter again.</item>
            <item>Your new transformation scenario should now be available in the Configurer
               Transformation Scenario dialog. Check the little box next to it, and uncheck the box
               next to the default Scenario.</item>
            <item><graphic url="configurer-3.png"/></item>
            <item>This OULIPO profile includes rules to handle the Word styles which were simply
               passed through as values for the rend attribute in the default transformation
               scenario.  (These rules are written in XSLT; we don't tell you here how to write
               them). Run the transformation again, by pressing Appliquer associes.  You should see
               something rather different this time...</item><item><graphic url="converted-2.png"/> </item>
         </list>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
