<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Exercise 7: Encoding Spoken Text</title>
                <author>TEI @ Oxford</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <date>July 2012</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Oxford</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative
                        Commons Attribution license.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Various previous talks, TEI Guidelines, etc.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>$LastChangedDate: 2012-05-28 10:23:52 +0100 $.</date>
                <name>$LastChangedBy: jamesc$</name>
                <note>$LastChangedRevision: 10412 $</note>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Exercise 7: Encoding Spoken Text</head>
            <!-- Learning Outcomes -->
            <div>
                <head>Learning Outcomes</head>
                <p>When you successfully complete this exercise you should be able to:
                        <list type="bulleted">
                        <item>Encode a transcription of spoken text</item>
                        <item>Use a <gi>recordingStmt</gi> in the header to document an
                            audio source </item>
                        <item>Record participants in a linguistic interaction</item>
                        <item>Mark utterances, pauses, and other incidents</item>
                        <item>Understand basic use of a <gi>timeline</gi> element </item>
                        <item>Use other markup in a spoken text transcription</item>

                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>

            <!-- Summary -->
            <div>
                <head>Summary</head>
                <p>This exercise starts with a TEI template and quickly makes a
                    transcription of an audio interview into a full valid TEI P5 file. The
                    interviewer (Stuart Lee) is interviewing Ian Hislop, who had recently
                    done a television programme 'Not Forgotten' about the impact on
                    British society of the First World War. We will mark up the
                    utterances, pauses, and other aspects of a fragment of this
                    interview.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Starting Up</head>
                <p>With oXygen loaded, start a new TEI P5 document by going to 'File' ->
                    'New' -> 'Framework Templates' -> 'TEI P5' -> 'All', and modify the
                    headers as below.</p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>Creating a Better Header</head>
                <p>The default template header isn't very good, let's make it better. <list>
                        <item>Modify the default <gi>fileDesc</gi> element to have a
                            better <gi>title</gi> and <gi>publicationStmt</gi>. This
                            document will be a transcribed fragment of an interview with
                            Ian Hislop for teaching purposes. Your <gi>fileDesc</gi>
                            should look something like:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<fileDesc>
    <titleStmt> 
      <title>Fragment of interview with Ian Hislop for teaching purposes</title>
    </titleStmt>
    <publicationStmt>
       <p>Used for a teaching exercise at DHOXSS TEI Workshop</p>
    </publicationStmt>
</fileDesc>
</egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>Use the <gi>recordingStmt</gi> element inside
                                <gi>sourceDesc</gi> to describe the source of the material
                            as an (audio in this case) recording. This recording is 27
                            minutes and 9 seconds long, and was made by OUCS on the 7th
                            September 2007. So our <gi>sourceDesc</gi> looks something
                            like:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<sourceDesc>
<recordingStmt>
    <recording type="audio" dur="PT27M09S">
        <respStmt>
            <resp>Recording by</resp>
            <orgName ref="#OUCS">Oxford University
             Computing Services</orgName>
        </respStmt>
        <date when="2007-09-07">7th September, 2007</date>
    </recording>
</recordingStmt>
</sourceDesc>
</egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item> After the end of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element but before
                            the closing <gi>/teiHeader</gi> tag, insert a
                                <gi>profileDesc</gi> element, and within that a
                                <gi>particDesc</gi>. This is where we’re going to record
                            the participants in the interview. Inside here create a
                                <gi>listPerson</gi> with two <gi>person</gi> elements. The
                            first (interviewer) should have an xml:id attribute value of
                            ‘SL’. This is the interviewer and his name is Stuart Lee.
                            Create a <gi>persName</gi> inside the <gi>person</gi> for him.
                            Also inside the <gi>person</gi>, alongside the
                                <gi>persName</gi>, create a <gi>note</gi> with a
                                <gi>ref</gi> inside. The <att>target</att> attribute’s
                            value should be <ref
                                target="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~stuart/Site/About_Me.html"
                                >http://users.ox.ac.uk/~stuart/Site/About_Me.html</ref>
                            with the <gi>ref</gi> content being something like 'Stuart
                            Lee’s home page'. </item>
                        <item>In the second <gi>person</gi> element, add an
                                <att>xml:id</att> attribute value of ‘IH’. The person
                            being interviewed’s name is Ian Hislop, a well known UK
                            comedian and editor of the satirical Private Eye magazine.
                            Create a <gi>note</gi> for him with a <gi>ref</gi> that points
                            to his wikipedia page: <ref
                                target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian_Hislop"
                                >http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian_Hislop</ref> Your
                                <gi>profileDesc</gi> should look something like:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<profileDesc>
<particDesc>
    <listPerson>
        <person xml:id="SL">
            <persName>Stuart Lee</persName>
            <note>
                <ref target="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~stuart/Site/About_Me.html">
                    Stuart Lee's home page</ref>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="IH">
            <persName>Ian Hislop</persName>
            <note>
                <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian_Hislop">
                    Ian Hislop's entry in Wikipedia</ref>
            </note>
        </person>
    </listPerson>  
</particDesc>
</profileDesc>    
</egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>Your document should be well-formed valid, and have a
                            happy green square!</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Adding the Transcription and Utterances</head>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Inside the <gi>body</gi> element, delete any paragraph that
                            is there, and insert the 'hislop.txt' file by going to the
                            'Document' -> 'File' -> 'Insert File' menu. (Otherwise you
                            could copy and paste it from notepad or similar). </item>
                        <item>oXygen will complain that you have a bunch of text just
                            inside <gi>body</gi>, let’s solve that first by adding some
                            structure. </item>
                        <item> Replace the [gap for sampling purposes] at the start and
                            end of the text with a <gi>gap reason=”sampling”/</gi>.
                        </item>
                        <item>Around <hi>each</hi> line-break separated utterance
                            (including the speaker name) wrap a <gi>u</gi> element.
                            (highlight and press 'control-e'; or you could put it in one
                                <gi>u</gi> element and split it with 'alt-shift-D' in
                            front of each one.) </item>
                        <item>Your first utterance should look something like:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<u>
Lee (24.27-24.36):
So em d-em having read [clicking sound: 0.17s] the Wipers Times
now and and your [pause: 0.62s] view that 
th th the thirties was that that
prisonment you say 
</u>
</egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>Your document should be well-formed and valid now, with a
                            happy green square, sort out any problems before progressing
                            further.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Making Better Utterances</head>
                <p>While our markup might be well-formed and valid it is a long way from
                    the truth. <list>
                        <item> The first person to speak didn’t really say ‘Lee
                            (24.27-24.36):’. </item>
                        <item>These are artifacts left by the transcriber to give a time
                            stamp and indicate which person was speaking. </item>
                        <item>Go through and comment out each of these lines by
                            highlighting it and pressing 'control-shift-comma' (or
                            selecting ‘Toggle Comment’ from the right-click menu). </item>
                        <item>Let’s use this information now to add some extra metadata to
                            each of the utterances. </item>
                        <item>For each utterance add a who attribute with a value of #
                            followed byt the corresponding <att>xml:id</att> value of the
                            person you are pointing to. </item>
                        <item>So your first utterance should look something like:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<u who="#SL">
<!-- Lee (24.27-24.36): -->
So em d-em having read [clicking sound: 0.17s] the Wipers Times
now and and your [pause: 0.62s] view that 
th th the thirties was that that
prisonment you say 
</u>
</egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>Repeat this for all the utterances using '#IH' and '#SL'
                            where appropriate. </item>
                        <item>Note: we are not going to use the timestamps in this
                            exercise, but do not delete them. Having XML comments in your
                            file doesn't cost you anything, but they can be deleted by
                            other applications processing the files. So they are a good
                            place to temporarily store information (such as where you are
                            having a problem with some encoding, or how far you have got
                            through a file).</item>

                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Incidents and Pauses (and Regular Expressions)</head>
                <p>Our audio transcriber has rigorously recorded the number of seconds of
                    a clicking sound that they heard and the pauses that speakers made in
                    speaking. We want to turn these non-spoken notes into markup. <hi>If
                        you want to listen to the audio clip it is provided as
                        'hislop.mp3'. You probably don't have time to listen to the whole
                        interview but it is provided as 'ian_hislop.mp3'. (The transcriber may have mis-heard some words here and there.)</hi><list>
                        <item>In the first utterance replace “[clicking sound: 0.17s]”
                            with:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><incident dur="PT0.17S">
                                <desc>clicking sound</desc>
                            </incident></egXML>
                            and “[pause: 0.62s]” with
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><pause dur="PT0.62S"/></egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item> We want to do this throughout the document, but doing this
                            manually is a bit of hard work. If you cannot get Regular
                            Expressions to work, you can always do this manually, but this
                            might make it a bit quicker! Press 'control-f' (or 'Find' ->
                            'Find/Replace' in the menus) to bring up the search and
                            replace dialog window. </item>
                        <item> Make sure the ‘Regular expression’ option is ticked. We are
                            going to use regular expressions (sometimes called 'regex' or
                            'regexes') to make the search and replacing more powerful. </item>
                        <item>In this case put <code>\[clicking sound: ([0-9.]*)s\]</code>
                            into the ‘Text to find:’ box. This means that we’re looking
                            for a literal square bracket, followed by the text ‘clicking
                            sound:’ then any combination of numbers and ‘.’ followed by an
                            s and a closing bracket. We have to escape the brackets
                            because they are used as part of the regular expression
                            language. </item>
                        <item>In the Replace with: section put:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><incident dur="PT\1S">
                                <desc>clicking sound</desc>
                            </incident></egXML>
                            which has us insert the incident element and adds the string
                            of text that we found in parentheses in the search
                            (represented by \1) to the duration value we’re adding to the
                            replacement. </item>
                        <item>Click ‘Find’ a couple times to make sure this is finding the
                            recorded clicking sounds. If so, click ‘Replace All’. Check
                            that this has done what you want. </item>
                        <item>Do the same with the pauses that have been recorded by using
                                <code>\[pause: ([0-9.]*)s\]</code> as the text to search
                            for and
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><pause dur="PT\1S"/></egXML>
                            as the text to replace it with. </item>
                        <item>When regular expressions are used carefully, they can make
                            text replacement and markup a quicker job. What do you think
                            are the dangers of using regular expressions?</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Encoding a Timeline</head>
                <p>Having a timeline is optional, but gives you a way to relate one point
                    in a spoken text to another. In our case it is a bit artificial so you
                    can decide whether to encode it our not. <list>
                        <item>Inside the <gi>body</gi> before the first <gi>gap/</gi>
                            element put the following <gi>timeline</gi> construction. We
                            could put this in the header, or a number of places, but this
                            is as good a place as any.
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <timeline unit="min" xml:id="recordingStart">
        <when xml:id="fragmentStart" interval="24.27"/>
        <when xml:id="TS2" interval="24.36"/>
        <when xml:id="TS3" interval="24.42"/>
        <when xml:id="TS4" interval="25.13"/>
        <when xml:id="TS5" interval="26.35"/>
        <when xml:id="TS6" interval="26.36"/>
        <when xml:id="TS7" interval="27.09"/>
 </timeline>
</egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>What this does is set up a timeline, with units in minutes
                            and then has a series of <gi>when</gi> elements with
                                <att>xml:id</att> attributes that we can then point at
                            from the body of our transcription. The fragment we are using
                            is 24.27 minutes through the interview. The next speaker says
                            something at 24.36, etc. These correspond to the times in the
                            comments inside your <gi>u</gi> elements. </item>
                        <item>This means that we can add a <att>start</att> and
                                <att>end</att> (where desirable) to the <gi>u</gi>
                            elements to point to these <gi>when</gi> elements. </item>
                        <item>Our first utterance opening tag now looks like:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <u who="#SL" start="#fragmentStart" end="#TS2">
                                So em d-em having read 
                                ...
                            </u>
                        </egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item> For our second we've only indicated the start:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <u who="#IH" start="#TS2">
                                    <!--Hislop (24.36):-->
                                    Yeah.
                                </u>
                            </egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>The
                            third:<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#SL" start="#TS2" end="#TS3">
                            <!--Lee (24.36-24.42)-->
                        ...
                            </u>
                        </egXML></item>
                        <item>Fourth:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#IH" start="#TS3" end="#TS4">
                            <!--Hislop (24.42-25.13):-->
                            <pause dur="PT0.76S"/> Not really I mean
                                ...
                        </u></egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>Fifth:<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <u who="#SL" start="#TS4">
                                <!--Lee (25.13):-->
                                Yes.
                            </u>
                        </egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sixth:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <u who="#IH" start="#TS4" end="#TS5">
                                <!--Hislop (25.13-26.35)-->
                                um <pause dur="PT0.50S"/>  which I saw again and
                                ...
                            </u>
                            </egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>Seventh:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <u who="#SL" start="#TS5">
                                <!--Lee (26.35)-->
                                hmm
                            </u>
                        </egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>Eighth:
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <u who="#IH" start="#TS6" end="#TS7">
                                <!--Hislop (26.36-27.09)-->
                                I think it's difficult to read the history of the century
                                ...
                            </u>
                        </egXML>
                        </item>
                        <item>If you have done all that your document should be
                            well-formed and valid with a happy green square. If it isn't,
                            find the problem!</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Other Things to Encode</head>
                <p>There are some other things we could encode like: <lb/>
                        <gi>title</gi>s, <gi>note</gi>s, and <gi>persName</gi>s. <list>
                        <item>There are three titles mentioned 'Wiper Times', 'The
                            Gassed', and 'Voices'. Mark them up as titles, removing any
                            quotation marks that indicated they were titles if they
                            exist.</item>
                        <item>There are two notes recorded by the transcriber: one has
                            'John Singer Sargent, 1918' in it (remove the square brackets
                            before marking it as a <gi>note</gi>. The other is 'syllables
                            -damental while laughing', mark this as a note as well. This
                            last one could also have been marked using the <gi>shift</gi>
                            element, but let's leave it as a note for simplicity. </item>
                        <item>There are a number of personal names, mark these as
                                <gi>persName</gi>.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>


            <!-- Saving Your Work -->
            <div>
                <head>Saving Your Work</head>
                <p> Let's save our work: <list>
                        <item>Is your work well-formed? Do you have a happy green square
                            or an angry red one?</item>
                        <item>Have you formatted and indented your work automatically? </item>
                        <item>From the 'File' menu select 'Save' or click on the Save icon
                            (looks like an old-style 3.5" disk).</item>
                        <item>Or if you prefer use the 'File' then 'Save As' menu item to
                            save the file using the name 'exercise07.xml' or another name
                            of your choice.</item>
                    </list></p>
            </div>

            <!-- Self-Assessment -->
            <div>
                <head>Self-Assessment</head>
                <p>Check if you understand some of the core principles of this exercise by
                    answering the following questions: <list>
                        <item>What element in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> is used to document
                            the details of a recording that acts as a source?</item>
                        <item>How do you mark utterances in spoken texts? </item>
                        <item>What useful attributes can this element have?</item>
                        <item>How do you indicate pauses or other incidents?</item>
                        <item>What does a <gi>timeline</gi> look like? </item>
                        <item>How do you mark titles that someone has said? </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>

            <!-- Next  -->
            <div>
                <head>Next and More Reading</head>
                <p>Next we'll be looking at some linguistic markup. However, before that if
                    you have time you may wish to:<list>
                        <item>Look up the reference pages for each of the new elements
                            you've used.</item>
                        <item>You might want to read the chapter on 'Transcriptions of
                            Speech' at <ref
                                target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TS.html"
                                >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TS.html</ref>.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
