<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Séminaire ALGORITM: session 2 Transcription des comptes rendus de l'Oulipo</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <list type="gloss">
            <label>Seminar objectives</label>
            <item>
               <list>
                  <item>decide on a markup scheme for a subset of the Oulipo archive </item>
                  <item>experiment with different ways of marking up some samples </item>
                  <item>demonstrate rendering and analysis of marked up samples </item>
               </list></item>
            <label>Working files </label>
            <item>These need to be prepared...
               <list>
                  <item>we have about 200 or so page images relating to meeting minutes; a
                     selection of maybe a dozen needs to be made for working purposes</item>
                  <item>we make available all page images, plus plain text
                     transcriptions for the selected dozen, plus a few marked up according to a
                     preliminary schema</item>
               <item>if we had more than one day we could develop a schema before their very eyes; as
                  we don't I propose to prepare in advance a simple ms-transcription schema and write
                  an ODD for it; if time permits we can have a session on how to modify this schema if
                  it proves inadequate during discussion.</item>
               </list></item>
           
           
            <label>Proposed timetable</label>
            <item><list type="ordered">
                  <item>Introductions, explanations etc. (15 mins) </item>
                  <item>Investigation of the data. Students look at page images and propose things
                     that need to be captured (30 mins) </item>
                  <item>Presentation and validation of preliminary schema: look at a sample file
                     in Oxygen (40 mins) </item>
                  <item>11h: Coffee break (30 mins)</item>
                 <item>Students divide into three groups : 
                    <list> <item>Practical 1 : some students (working in pairs) mark up a document using Oxygen. </item>
                  <item>Practical 2 : other students mark up document in Word using predefined styles,
                     generate TEI from it (using predefined stylesheet), validate/correct </item>
               <item>Practicals 3 : yet other students experiment with web-based cooperative editing tool? </item></list> (60 mins) </item>
               <item>12h30 Lunch (90 mins) </item>               
                  <item>Practicals continue: all students move around and try different approach (30 mins)</item>
                     <item>Demonstrate functioning web apps able to do some of the following: <list>
                        <item>display graphic and transcription in parallel</item>
                        <item>visualise attendance records of oulipiens over time </item>
                        <item>word lists and co-occurence lists over time -</item>
                        <item>
                           display annotated versions of text</item>
                     </list> (60 mins)
                  </item>
                  <item>Review and discussion (30 mins)</item>
               </list></item>
         </list>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
