<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An oXygen Cheatsheet</title>
            <title xml:lang="fr">Un anti-sèche oXygen</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished as yet</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>All my own work</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2014-10-16">First draft, en route to Limoges</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Here's a list of the operations we do most when using oXygen, with a brief reminder of
            how to perform them.</p>
         <div>
            <head>Operations on a complete document</head>
            <list>
               <head>Create a new TEI XML document<lb/></head>
               <item><lb/>Click the New icon on the toolbar (this one <graphic url="newdoc.png"
                     height="7mm"/>), or select <ident>New</ident> from the File menu, or type
                  CTRL-N to open the New dialog box</item>
               <item>If you want to use one of the predefined TEI schemas, choose <ident>Framework
                     Template</ident>, then <ident>TEI P5</ident>, and then choose the schema you
                  want, for example <ident>Bare</ident>, <ident>Lite</ident>, <ident>all</ident>
                  etc. </item>
               <item>If on the other hand you want to use a personalised schema you have made
                  yourself, then choose <ident>New Document</ident>, then <ident>XML
                     Document</ident>, and click on the <ident>Customize</ident> button at the
                  bottom. In the dialog which then opens, you must specify where the schema you want
                  to use is to be found, for example by navigating to the <ident>out</ident> folder
                  if it is locally stored, choosing the right schema file, and clicking the Open
                  button</item>

               <item>In either case, click on the <ident>Create</ident> button at the bottom. oXygen
                  displays a minimal template for your chosen TEI schema. </item>

            </list>

            <list>
               <head>Process an ODD</head>
               <item>Open a valid ODD file</item>
               <item>In the <ident>Document</ident> menu, choose <ident>Transformation</ident> ->
                     <ident>Configure Transformation Scenario(s)</ident>, or type CTRL-SHIFT-C, or
                  click the spanner icon (this one : <graphic url="spanner.png" height="7mm"/>) on
                  the toolbar. </item>
               <item>A list of available transformation scenarios is displayed. Tick the box next to
                  those you want to apply: for ODD, the most useful are probably TEI ODD XHTML and
                  TEI ODD to RELAXNG Compact</item>
               <item><graphic url="scenarios.png" height="7cm"/>
               </item>
               <item>Click the <ident>Apply Associated</ident> button to start the
                  transformation(s); you can safely ignore the messages that scroll by in the lower
                  window</item>
               <item>By default, XHTML will be displayed using your default browser, while an RNC
                  output will be saved in a folder called <ident>out</ident>, which oXygen will
                  create in the current directory if necessary. </item>
            </list>

            <!--Lancez oXygen et ouvrez le fichier <ident>cartes-tei.odd</ident> qui se trouve dans
                     votre dossier <ident>Travaux</ident>
                  </item>
                  <item>Dans le menu <ident>Document</ident> sélectionnez <ident>Transformation</ident> ->
                     <ident>Configurer Les Scenarios de Transformation</ident>, ou tapez CTRL-MAJ-C, ou
                     cliquez l'icône sur la barre d'outils. </item>
                  <item>Les transformations possibles sont affichées. Déroullez pour trouver celles qui
                     concernent les ODD et cochez les cases qui vous interessent, par ex: TEI ODD
                     XHTML et TEI ODD to RELAXNG Compact</item>
                  <item><graphic url="../Graphics/oxy-scenarios.png" height="7cm"/>
                  </item>
                  <item>Cliquez sur le bouton <ident>Appliquer Associé(s)</ident> pour lancer les
                     transformations.</item>
                  <item>Si tout va bien, la sortie XHTML s'affiche dans le navigateur, et la sortie RNC sera
                     enregistrée dans un dossier <ident>out</ident>
                  </item>
               </list>-->
            <list>
               <head>Associate a TEI XML file with a schema</head>
               <item>The schema association for a TEI document is usually set up when the document
                  is created; if this is not done, oXygen will by default assume your file is to be
                  validated against TEI All. To change this, select <ident>Schema --> Associate
                     schema</ident> from the <ident>Document</ident> menu.</item>
               <item>Navigate to the schema file you want to use and press Open</item>
               <item>oXygen inserts a processing instruction (a PI) at the start of the document. </item>
               <item>If there are several such PIs, oXygen uses the last one. </item>
            </list>
            <!--  <item>Pour utiliser votre nouveau schéma, il suffit de sélectionner <ident>S Associate chema ->
                  Sélectionner un schéma</ident> sur le menu <ident>Document</ident> et puis de naviguer
                  jusqu'au fichier <ident>out/cartes-tei.rng</ident></item>-->
            <list>
               <head>Associate a TEI XML file with a stylesheet</head>
               <item>This can be done in two ways. ...</item>
               <item>To set up a default transformation scenario for a document, use the procedure
                  described above for transformation of an ODD file (but select a different XSLT
                  stylesheet, obviously)</item>
               <item>Alternatively, you can simply associate an XSLT or CSS stylesheet file with a
                  document by selecting <ident>XML Document -> Associate XSLT/CSS Stylesheet</ident>
                  from the Document menu. </item>
               <item>Whichever method you use, the transformation will be carried out without need
                  for further specification whenever you press the Transform button on the toolbar
                  (this one: <graphic url="transform.png" height="7mm"/> ); type CTRL-SHIFT-T; or
                  select <ident>Transformation -> Apply Transformation Scenarios</ident> from the
                     <ident>Document</ident> menu </item>

            </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Operations on the content of an XML document:</head>
            <list>
               <head>Reformat document in text mode</head>
               <item>Select <ident>Source -> Format and Indent</ident> on the Document menu; type
                  CTRL-SHIFT-P; or click the appropriate toolbar button (this one: <graphic
                     url="indent.png" height="7mm"/> )</item>
            </list>
                   <list> <head>Insert text from a file</head>
                      
                     <item>Put the cursor at the point in your document where you want the text to
                        be inserted</item>
                     <item> Choose <ident>File -> Insert File</ident> from the
                           <ident>Document</ident> menu (<emph>not</emph> the <ident>File</ident>
                        menu!) </item>
                     <item> Navigate to the file whose contents you wish to insert </item>
                     <item>Press Open</item>
                  </list>
         <list> <head>Tag a stretch of text</head>
               
                     <item>Select and highlight the stretch of text you want to tag with the
                        mouse.</item>
                     <item>Type CTRL-E or choose <ident>XML Refactoring -- Surround with
                           Tags</ident> from the <ident>Document</ident> menu</item>
                     <item>Select the tag you wish to use from the drop down menu (type its first
                        letter to scroll the list rapidly) </item>
                  </list>
       <list>   <head>Split a tagged element in two</head>
               
                     <item>Put the cursor at the place where you want to split the element. </item>
                     <item>Type ALT + SHIFT + D or choose <ident>XML Refactoring -- Split
                           Element</ident> from the <ident>Document</ident> menu</item>
                  </list>
<list>   <head>Untag an element</head>
               
                     <item>Put the cursor anywhere inside the element you wish to untag. </item>
                     <item>Type ALT + SHIFT + X or choose <ident>XML Refactoring -- Delete Element
                           Tags</ident> from the <ident>Document</ident> menu</item>
                  </list>

                   <list>   <head>Change the tagging of an element </head>
                      
                     <item>Put the cursor inside the start- or end-tag of the element you wish to
                        rename. </item>
                     <item>Choose <ident>XML Refactoring -- Rename Element</ident> from the
                           <ident>Document</ident> menu</item>
                     <item>Type the new name you want and indicate whether which occurrences you
                        want to change</item>
                     <item>Press OK to make the changes </item>
                  </list>
      <list>     <head>Comment out a stretch of text</head>
               
                     <item>Select and highlight the stretch of text you want to tag with the
                        mouse.</item>
                     <item>Type CTRL SHIFT COMMA; choose <ident>Edit -> Toggle Comment</ident> from
                        the <ident>Document</ident> menu; or click the appropriate button on the
                        toolbar (this one : <graphic url="comment.png" height="7mm"/>; repeat to
                        remove the comment tags</item>

                  </list>
            
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Operations on non-XML documents</head>
            <list >
               <head>Open and display an image file</head>
               <item>You can use the usual Open dialog to open an image file in JPG or PNG or TIFF
                  formats.The image opens in a separate window which you can dock within the main
                  editing area, resize, or move around or pin, using the window controls. You can't
                  however zoom or otherwise process the image: for that you need to install a plugin
                  such as <ref target="https://code.google.com/p/severin-image-viewer/ED">the
                     Severin image viewer</ref>. </item></list>
        <list><head>Open and convert a Word docx file</head>
                  
                     <item>In oXygen, use the usual Open dialog to select the docx file</item>
                     <item>A window labelled <code>Archive Browser</code> opens to the left of the
                        main screen. It shows the file structure of the docx archive.</item>
                     <item><graphic url="navigateur-1.png" height="4cm"/></item>
                     <item>Click the blue key next to the folder called <ident>word </ident> to see
                        the contents of this folder</item>
                     <item><graphic url="navigateur-2.png" height="4cm"/></item>
                     <item>Select the file called <ident> document.xml</ident> and double click to
                        open it (may take a few moments if the file is large)</item>
                     <item><graphic url="document-word.png" height="4cm"/></item>

                     <item>With the <ident>document.xml</ident> file open in your main editing
                        window, select <ident>Transformation -> Configure Transformation
                           Scenario(s)</ident> from the <ident>Document</ident> menu. Or type
                           <code>CTRL-SHIFT-C</code>. Or click the little spanner icon</item>
                     <item>For the default DOCX to TEI conversion, check the little box next to DOCX
                        TEI P5 and press the <ident>Apply Associated</ident> button </item>
                     <item><graphic url="configurer-1.png" height="4cm"/></item>
                  </list>
           

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
