<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Best practice recommendations for long term archiving of TEI XML
               resources</title>
            <author xml:id="lou">Lou Burnard</author>
            <author>Nicolas Larrousse</author>
            <funder>TGIR Huma-Num</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished draft circulated for comment</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>An original work: no pre-existing source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#lou" when="2013-10-20">Started draft</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="intro">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>This document arises out of a study commissioned by the TGIR Huma-Num in
               collaboration with the CINES. <!-- expand these acronyms and add details -->
            </p>
            <p>The object of the study was to assist the community of researchers wishing to deposit
               textual resources encoded using TEI XML with the CINES for long term preservation by
               formulating a series of precise recommendations, a Guide to Good Practice. Although
               the CINES already has extensive experience and expertise in the long term
               preservation of resources respecting generic standards such as XML and PDF, it was
               recognised that the increasing use of TEI-XML in the French research community
               offered both an additional opportunity and a challenge. On the one hand, as a more
               expressive and richer formalism than generic XML, TEI offers the possibility of
               ensuring the preservation of more contextual and semantic data forming part of a
               resource; on the other hand, the ways in which TEI XML is applied in practice varies
               quite widely amongst different researchers, and so simply to say that a document is
               "TEI-conformant" may leave unspecified a great deal of useful contextual information
               about it. </p>
            <p>Although the community of TEI users is highly diverse, its members share an
               understanding of the best way to use the TEI Guidelines, just as those Guidelines
               express a common understanding of how the structure and metadata associated with a
               textual resource should be documented and defined. This community of practice has
               been increasing in size and scope quite significantly over the last few years, and
               notably so in France, where a number of large-scale resource-creation projects have
               already expressed a committment to the use of TEI XML, just as several smaller scale
               individual resource projects have adopted and adapted it to their needs. For the
               purposes of this project we approached initially only a small number of projects,
               selecting those which were known to be engaged in the creation of significant amounts
               of TEI-XML material likely to be of long-term interest in the scholarly research
               community. Examples included the Open Edition project (CLEO), which will publishes
               several hundred scholarly books in a TEI format over the next few years; the CNRTL,
               which has long been responsible for creation and distribution of a wide range of
               TEI-encoded language corpora and is a major French partner in CLARIN;
               <!-- some more examples here? --></p>
            <p>The usefulness of TEI-XML as a format for scholarly analysis and interchange is
               widely accepted. However the question arises as whether TEI-encoded resources are
               also suitable for long term preservation purposes. More specifically, if a project
               wishes to ensure long term preservation of its resources, should it archive them in a
               TEI format, or should it regard the TEI format simply as a means to an end, archiving
               only a processed form of the TEI source as HTML or PDF, for example? For projects
               where the TEI form is considered only as a means to the end of displaying the texts,
               this may well be adequate. But since TEI to HTML or TEI to PDF are lossy
               transformations, in which the added value constituted by TEI structural annotation is
               systematically removed this seems in general a less than optimal solution. We would
               like to be able to preserve our digital resources without loss of information, so as
               to facilitate future use of that information by means of technologies not yet in
               existence. Such data-independence was, after all, one of the promises XML (and before
               it SGML) offered.</p>
            <p>If then it is decided to preserve the original TEI XML sources, what other components
               (schema files, stylesheets, etc.) should accompany them when submitting them for long
               term preservation in a digital archive? Should derived versions of the source (in
               such formats as HTML or PDF) also be preserved? TEI encoded resources typically
               contain mostly XML-encoded text, possibly with links to files expressed using other
               commonly encountered web formats for graphics or audio; is there advantage to be
               gained by treating them differently from any other XML encoded resource? When such
               resources are deposited in a digital archive, what tools and expertise will the
               archivist need to have available in order to ensure that they are valid and will
               continue to be usable? </p>
            <p> This study attempts to address these questions by providing (in section <ptr
                  target="#rex"/>) <list>
                  <item>recommendations for the data depositor, specifically about what documents
                     should accompany a resource to be archived ; </item>
                  <item>recommendations for the archiving services, specifically about what tools
                     may be used to validate TEI XML documents ; </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>A number of different scenarios are envisaged, depending on the technical expertise
               and other resources available to the depositor (and the archive). We provide some
               technical background on the technologies concerned in section <ptr target="#tech"/>
               below.</p>
            <p>Our study concerns primarily resources encoded using TEI-XML, though its
               recommendations may easily be generalised to cover comparable XML vocabularies such
               as Docbook or even other markup languages entirely. We do not consider other file
               formats, except where resources using them are likely to form part of a TEI-XML
               resource. We assume a basic knowledge of the TEI Recommendations, and also of the
               principles of long term archiving of digital resources, notably as practiced within
               the library community. A good overview covering most organisational aspects of this
               area is provided (in English) in the UK's Digital Preservation Coalition's online
               handbook at and we do not attempt to duplicate their recommendations here.
               <!--Comparable recommendations have been
               provided by other European agencies such as Minerva (?)--></p>
            <!--
               A voir dans l’introduction ???
Références à d’autres pratiques et formats de fichiers 
Contextualisation exemple avec la Data Preservation Coalition  (UK) 
Prendre contact avec Text-Grid & Deutche Text Archive
-->
         </div>
         <div xml:id="rex">
            <head>Recommendations</head>
            <p>Our first recommendation concerns the <hi>provision of metadata</hi> about the
               source. All TEI-XML files include a component known as the <term>TEI Header</term>,
               which may be very elaborate and detailed, or entirely minimalist. For archival
               purposes, however, we think it may be helpful to propose a specific subset of
               information that should be supplied by the Header for every kind of language
               resource. A project may well supply more metadata than is suggested here; if it
               supplies less, then the description of the resource will be correspondingly weaker
               and less useful. The Archive will be expected to use only the elements specified here
               as the basis of its cataloguing of the resource. </p>
            <p>Our second recommendation concerns the <hi>validation of the source</hi>. We propose
               that depositors should as far as possible ensure that TEI-XML resources are
               accompanied by a file which accurately describes their encoding practices and
               purposes. The most appropriate format for this description would be the TEI-XML
               vocabulary commonly known as ODD, although producing documentation in this format is
               not as yet as well-understood or widely practiced within the TEI community as might
               be desired; a point to which we return below. Documentation in other forms,
               accompanied by validation schemas, are also useful, but they do not necessarily
               guarantee that the resources concerned will be TEI conformant. For this, an ODD is
               necessary. </p>
            <p>In the absence of ODD documentation from which a more appropriate schema may be
               derived, the only validation check possible before a resource can be accepted into
               the Archive will be against the generic TEI_All schema. According to the definition
               of TEI conformance, those parts of a document using the TEI namespace most be valid
               against the TEI All schema, which includes declarations for all possible TEI elements
               and attributes. </p>
            <p>Our third recommendation concerns the <hi>physical organization of the source</hi>. A
               TEI-XML resource is an XML document, the root element of which is either TEI or
               teiCorpus. However, that resource may well be stored in one or more files. Any XML
               document may embed or transclude other XML resources, for example, by use of the
               xInclude standard. A TEI-XML document may also transclude other non-XML documents
               such as graphics or audio. And a TEI XML document frequently references other XML
               documents, without however implying that they should be included in the source
               itself.</p>
            <p>The METS standard addresses this problem in the general case, and it may be that an
               additional METS layer would be beneficial also as a way of combining ODD and resource
               in a single container. METS is widely used in the library community as a means of
               combining arbitrary components to form an archival object: see further <ref>Hathi
                  Trust Digital Object Specifications (METS and PREMIS)</ref>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="rex1">
            <head>Provision of Metadata</head>
            <p>A <gi>teiHeader</gi> element must be provided for each distinct <gi>TEI</gi> or
                  <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element in a resource. We recommend the following steps as part
               of the accession process: <list>
                  <item>Each header should be validated against a strict schema (to be supplied)
                     which will check the existence of required components listed below;</item>
                  <item>Each header will be modified, as a minimum to indicate that the header has
                     been validated for accession, and possibly also to indicate any significant
                     gaps found, as indicated below.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Multiple <term>levels</term> of metadata may be provided in the case of a
                  <gi>teiCorpus</gi>. For example, some information may relate to the corpus as a
               whole (for example, its title, the purpose for which it was created, its distributor,
               etc); other information may relate only to individual components of it (for example,
               the bibliographic description of an individual source text), or to groups of such
               components (for example, a taxonomic classification).</p>
            <div xml:id="D1iden">
               <head>Identification</head>
               <p>Under this heading we group information that identifies the resource, and
                  specifies the agencies responsible for its creation and distribution. <list>
                     <item>name of resource (<gi>title</gi> within <gi>titleStmt</gi>) [required]; </item>
                     <item>author and/or editor of the original from which the resource is derived
                           (<gi>author</gi> or <gi>editor</gi> within <gi>titleStmt</gi> as
                        necessary) [required where applicable] </item>
                     <item>producer (<gi>respStmt</gi> within <gi>titleStmt</gi>). The agency
                        (individuals, research group, "principle investigator", company, institution
                        etc.) responsible for the creation and form of the resource must be
                        specified. [required] </item>
                     <item>Information about any funding body or sponsor involved may also be
                        supplied using the <gi>funder</gi> element.</item>
                     <item> A <gi>publicationStmt</gi> is also required within the
                        <gi>fileDesc</gi>. If the resource has been formally published or
                        distributed, this will contain details of the agency (individual, research
                        group, company, institution etc) concerned; if not, it will contain text
                        stating that the resource has not been formally published. The following
                        elements may be used: <list>
                           <item>name of agency <gi>publisher</gi>, <gi>distributor</gi>
                           </item>
                           <item>contact details (postal address, email, telephone, fax)
                                 (<gi>pubPlace</gi>)</item>
                           <item>date first made available by this agency (<gi>date</gi>)</item>
                           <item>any specific identifier (e.g. a PURL or ISBN ) used for the
                              published version (<gi>idno</gi>)</item>
                           <item>information about access rights should be supplied within the
                              required <gi>availability</gi> element. This should explicitly
                              reference all applicable licences using the <gi>licence</gi> element
                              and may also indicate additional restrictions, e.g. where the corpus
                              may not be distributed in some geographic zones, or for some specific
                              purposes. </item>
                        </list></item>
                  </list></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="D1srce">
               <head>Source derivation</head>
               <p>Under this heading we group information that describes the sources from which the
                  resource was derived. </p>
               <p>TEI-XML resources may be derived from many different kinds of object. A
                     <gi>sourceDescription</gi> is required for each distinct source. Depending on
                  its nature, this will contain one of the following : <list>
                     <item><gi>bibl</gi> or <gi>biblStruct</gi> for books, newspapers, pamphlets
                        etc. originally printed; </item>
                     <item><gi>msDesc</gi> for unique manuscript archival documents or inscriptions; </item>
                     <item><gi>p</gi> or <gi>note</gi> for unpublished
                           <soCalled>born-digital</soCalled> materials;</item>
                     <item><gi>bibl</gi> or <gi>ref</gi> for web pages or other digitally
                        distributed materials</item>
                     <item><gi>recording</gi> for recorded or broadcast speech or video</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>All of these elements have their own detailed substructure, concerning which we
                  make no particular recommendations, since their use will be highly
                  project-specific. For archival purposes, it is required only that at least one of
                  the elements listed above appear. In the case of conventionally printed and
                  published material, a standard bibliographic description should be supplied or
                  referenced, using the usual conventions (author, title, publisher, date, ISBN,
                  etc.), and using a standard citation format. For other kinds of material,
                  different data is appropriate: for example, in transcripts of spoken data it is
                  customary to supply demographic information about each speaker, and the context in
                  which the speech interaction occurs. Standards defining the range of such
                  information for the use of particular research communities should be followed (for
                  example, defined by CLARIN) where appropriate. </p>
               <p>Other components of the <gi>fileDesc</gi> element such as <gi>extent</gi> may be
                  used, but are not required.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="D1enc">
               <head>Encoding description</head>
               <p>The second major subdivision of the TEI header is contained by an optional
                     <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element, and may potentially contain a very large number
                  of semi-structured metadata elements covering most aspects of the process by which
                  a source has been encoded. Its function thus overlaps with that of the ODD file
                  discussed in section <ptr target="#rec2"/>. Components of this element specify the
                  methods and editorial principles which governed the transcription or encoding of
                  the resource and may also include sets of coded definitions used by other
                  components. The following elements, many of which have quite extensive
                  substructure, are potentially available: <list>
                     <item>Project goals and research agenda (<gi>projectDesc</gi>); </item>
                     <item>Sampling principles and methods employed (<gi>samplingDecl</gi>);</item>
                     <item>Editorial principles and practices (<gi>editorialDecl</gi>); </item>
                     <item>XML tagging used (<gi>tagsDecl</gi>, <gi>styleDefDecl</gi>,
                           <gi>schemaSpec</gi>); </item>
                     <item>Reference schemes applied (<gi>refsDecl</gi> ; <gi>geoDecl</gi>) </item>
                     <item>Classification scheme used (<gi>classDecl</gi>)</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p> There is little agreement or common practice in the way these elements are used,
                  some projects providing extensive documentation, and others none at all. For our
                  purposes, therefore, we recommend only that as a minimum the <gi>projectDesc</gi>
                  element be supplied. This element is used to state explicitly the project goals
                  and research agenda associated with the creation of the resource. The persons or
                  agencies directly responsible will already have been mentioned as a part of
                  identifying the resource; the purpose of this section is to provide further
                  background on such matters as the purposes for which the corpus was created, its
                  design goals, its theoretical framework or context, its intended usage, target
                  audience etc. Although of necessity impressionistic and anecdotal, such
                  information can be very helpful to the user seeking to determine the potential
                  relevance of the resource to their own needs. </p>
               <p>Note that the <gi>schemaSpec</gi> discussed in section <ptr target="#rex2"/> may
                  also appear within the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> of a particular document. We do not
                  however recommend this for the following reasons: <list>
                     <item>full documentation of a schema requires more than simply a schema
                        specification;</item>
                     <item>an ODD usually applies to more than one TEI document;</item>
                     <item>if a document has both an associated ODD and a <gi>schemaSpec</gi> in its
                        header it is not clear which takes precedence in the case of disagreement
                        between them.</item>
                  </list>. If therefore a <gi>schemaSpec</gi> is present, it will only be used to
                  validate the document in the case where no other ODD is available. </p>
               <p>If other descriptive elements are supplied, they will be archived along with the
                  rest of the Header, and may be harvested to provide a richer description of the
                  resource but their presence is not required. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Profile Description</head>
               <p>The TEI Header permits a number of other <soCalled>non-bibliographic</soCalled>
                  metadata components within the <gi>profileDesc</gi> element. These include, for
                  example, information about the natural language or languages represented in a
                  resource (<gi>langUsage</gi>), ways in which it may be classified
                     (<gi>textClass</gi>, <gi>keywords</gi>, etc.) </p>
               <p>If any of these descriptive elements are supplied, they will be archived along
                  with the rest of the Header, and may be harvested to provide a richer description
                  of the resource but their presence is not required. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Revision Description</head>
               <p>This optional element is used to record significant stages in the evolution of a
                  resource. It should contain a series of <gi>change</gi> elements, in reverse
                  chronological order, most recent first. We recommend that at least one such
                     <gi>change</gi> element be supplied in order to record the date of archiving of
                  the source. If this is not present, then it should be added during the
                  accessioning process.</p>
          <!-- but it cant be the archiving date : it's the date of finishing -->
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="rex2">
            <head>Validation of the Source</head>
            <p>The idea of <soCalled>TEI Conformance</soCalled> goes beyond simple syntactic
               validity, i.e. conformance to the rules of XML. The TEI Guidelines now define quite
               explicitly the properties of a TEI-conformant document, and suggest ways in which
               those properties may be checked. They state that : <list>
                  <item>a TEI conformant document must be valid with respect to a schema called TEI
                     All (at least, as far as those parts of it which are taken from the TEI
                     namespace are concerned);</item>
                  <item>a TEI conformant document must be accompanied by an ODD documenting its
                     specific TEI usage; </item>
                  <item>a TEI document must respect the TEI conceptual model: that is, it must
                     respect the semantics of the TEI elements it contains. Clearly this constraint
                     is hard or impossible to validate entirely automatically, though some
                     indicative procedures can be identified.</item>
               </list></p>
            <p>The schema TEI All is distributed as part of the TEI Guidelines. We recommend, as a
               minimum, that every TEI resource (i.e. each <gi>TEI</gi> or <gi>teiCorpus</gi>) to be
               archived should be validated against it. </p>
            <p>We also recommend that each TEI resource archived should be accompanied by an
               additional free-standing document called an ODD. This is a formal specification of a
               TEI schema documenting the semantics of the elements, attributes, datatypes it
               contains. For the most part, of course, those semantics are as defined in the TEI
               Guidelines (more exactly, in a particular version of them, as specified by the
                  <att>version</att> attribute on the root element), but since the TEI offers many
               overlapping ways of doing the same thing, it may be necessary to supplement and make
               more precise the default documentation by means of additional user-supplied
               documentation. </p>
            <p>The ODD (<q>One Document Does it all</q>) format is defined in the TEI Guidelines,
               and has also been the subject of a small number of introductory guides and tutorials
               (see the bibliography). Nevertheless it is not as well known or understood within the
               broad TEI community as other parts of the TEI and hence not as widely used as it
               might be. Its importance to our project lies in the mechanisms it offers for
               validation and documentation of a TEI-XML resource beyond simple validity against the
               generic TEI All schema. </p>
            <p>An ODD document is a TEI-conformant XML document which describes a tagging system
               informally, in the same way as a typical project encoding manual, by listing the
               elements used, describing the circumstances in which they are applicable, providing
               examples of their usage, etc. It also contains a formally expressed specification of
               exactly which parts of the TEI architecture have been used, and how these have been
               modified. This is expressed by means of a <gi>schemaSpec</gi> ("schema
               specification") element and also optionally in running prose. </p>
            <p>A schema specification may express the components which are to be combined to form a
               schema in any of the following ways : <list>
                  <item>a list of <term>TEI modules</term> to be included by reference; </item>
                  <item>a list of TEI elements to be included by reference;</item>
                  <item>a subset of declarations from a named module, defined either by inclusion
                     ("select only x y and z from module a") or by exclusion ("select everything
                     except x y and z from module a") </item>
                  <item>modifications of certain parts of an existing specification, for example to
                     change class memberships, add a new usage example, suppress one or more
                     attributes, change lists of legal attribute values, etc. </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>An ODD may be written from scratch, like any other TEI XML document. It is more
               usually created (initially at least) by software such as the TEI applications
                  <ident>Roma</ident> or <ident>Byzantium</ident>, which allow the user to construct
               a new ODD using a relatively simple web interface to the full TEI specifications. The
               user can start from an existing schema and add or remove components, save an ODD
               specification for future manipulation and so on. These interfaces also provide simple
               access to the XSLT Stylesheets to process the ODD being constructed, generating from
               it either formal schemas in RELAXNG, DTD or W3C Schema or documentation files in HTML
               or PDF. An ODD can also be generated automatically by applying the <ident>ODD By
                  Example</ident> stylesheet to a body of existing valid TEI XML files. </p>
            <p>For the purposes of our project, the form of the ODD supplied is of little
               importance, provided that the <att>source</att> attribute is used to tie it to a
               specific version of the TEI Guidelines. (If this is not the case, the meaning of an
               ODD defined by exclusion may well change over time). However, for most purposes we
               consider that an ODD defined by inclusion is easier to understand and may therefore
               be preferred. </p>

            <p>We make the following recommendations for formal validation : <list>
                  <item>Is the document valid against TEI All?</item>
                  <item>If an ODD is supplied <list>
                        <item>is the ODD valid against TEI All?</item>
                        <item>Can a schema in RELAXNG, WSD, or DTD language be generated from the
                           ODD?</item>
                        <item>Is the document valid against each of the schemas generated in the
                           previous step?</item>
                     </list></item>
                  <item>Whether or not an ODD is supplied, an <soCalled>instance ODD</soCalled>
                     should be generated automatically from the set of documents being
                     archived.</item>
               </list>
            </p>

            <p>The schemas generated from an instance ODD may be used to validate and document
               related XML resources in the absence of a supplied ODD. </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="rex3">
            <head>Physical Organization</head>
            <!-- generate sip.xml from document !! -->
            <p>A TEI XML object, for the purposes of accessioning, should contain the whole of the
               root TEI or teiCorpus element. If portions of this document are embedded by means of
               xInclude statements or other URI reference, resolving these should be as simple as
               possible. For that reason, we recommend that before the object is archived its
               components should be moved to a simple directory structure, in which each x Included
               file is at the same level, and each embedded graphic or other media file is moved to
               a single <q>Media</q> directory at the same level. This in turn will require some
               modification of the existing source files, to ensure that URIs continue to be valid. </p>
            <p>For example consider the following imaginary TEI XML fragment: <egXML
                  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><![CDATA[
                 <body><include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../part1.xml"/>
                  <p>
                     This text contains a local pointer <ptr target="#section34"/> and a remote one <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org"/>
                  </p>
                    <include  xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="/home/demo/TEIstuff/part2.xml"/>
                  <p>This paragraph contains different kinds of media
                  <figure><graphic url="pic.png"/></figure>
                  <media
                     mime Type="video/mp4"
                     url="media/clip45.mp4"
                     dur="PT45M"
                     width="500px">
                     <desc>A 45 minute video clip to be displayed in a window 500
                        px wide </desc>
                  </media>
<p>               This paragraph contains a remote reference 
<name ref="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denis_Diderot">Denis Diderot</name> and also to a video 
stream <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aV25VdEMiBM">A video about Diderot</ref></p>              
               ]]></egXML> In this fragment, the contents of the files <ident>../part1.xml</ident>
               and <ident>/home/demo/TEIstuff/part2.xml</ident> should preferably be obtained
                  <hi>before archiving is carried out</hi> and inserted at the appropriate place in
               the source. If this is not possible (perhaps because the resulting file would be too
               large), the files concerned should be included within the archival package at the
               same level in the file structure as the file containing the fragment quoted here, and
               the <att>href</att> values modified, to point to "part1.xml" and "part2.xml"
               respectively. </p>
            <p>The values of each of the attributes <att>target</att>, <att>url</att>, and
                  <att>ref</att> should be checked during accession to ensure that the resource
               indicated by the URI is accessible. This can be done for XML content by means of an
               XSLT2 style sheet, using the <ident>doc-available()</ident> and
                  <ident>resolve-Uri()</ident> built-in functions. When the resource indicated by
               the <att>url</att> attribute is available, but is not stored in a local
                  <ident>media</ident> directory at the same level as the rest of the resource, we
               recommend that it should be obtained and copied to such a directory, and the source
               modified accordingly. </p>
            <p>URIs within a TEI-XML document which do not imply transclusion of text or media may
               be left unmodified in the source, although they should be checked for validity,
               particularly those which point locally (i.e. links of the form
                  <code>url="xxxx"</code> or <code>url="#xxx"</code>). In the general case however
               the only reliable way of checking a URI is to follow it, using a tool such as
                  <ident>curl</ident> to access the HTTP header for the indicated URL and then
               processing that. Such checking could be done automatically during the process of
               ingesting the source into the Archive. It is probably unreasonable, however, to
               expect all such links to be accessible all the time, particularly those pointing to
               arbitrary web sites outside the scope of the Archive's concerns.</p>
         </div>

         <div xml:id="pilot">

            <head>Pilot Implementation</head>

            <p>To perform the validation tasks suggested in section <ptr target="#rex2"/> above, the
               following software components are required: <list>

                  <item>An XML validator</item>
                  <item>An XSLT processor</item>
                  <item>The version of the TEI Guidelines indicated by the <att>source</att>
                     attribute on the supplied <gi>schemaSpec</gi></item>
                  <item>TEI Stylesheets to process ODD files</item>
                  <item>An XSLT style sheet to check availability of XML resources referenced by
                     URI</item>
                  <item>An XML processor to resolve X Included document fragments</item>
               </list></p>
            <!--Quels outils ?
Proposer un environnement logiciel en annexe 
Problème de vérification des URIs (images, sons vidéos  et SVG  Balise TEI « media » 
Existe t-il des validateurs d’URIs 
Prise en compte des Name-Space 
-->
         </div>
         <div xml:id="further">
            <head>Future work</head>
            <p>If the recommendations made in the present report are accepted, it is clear that work
               is needed on several fronts: <list>
                  <item>a tool kit to carry out the procedures outlined in section <ptr
                        target="#pilot"/> needs to be assembled, and tested against a substantial
                     body of TEI documents;</item>
                  <item>cost-effective ways of enhancing and correcting existing TEI documents to
                     meet the proposed level of description need to be determined;</item>
                  <item>the potential user community needs better guidance on how to document their
                     resources. For example, better documentation of the ODD system is needed: a
                     simple user guide or <foreign>antisèche</foreign>
                     <title>How To Write an ODD</title> would be very useful. </item>
               </list></p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="ack">
            <head>Acknowledgments</head>
            <p>The first draft of this report was produced in English by Lou Burnard. The French
               translation was prepared by Nicolas Larrousse. The content of the report was
               discussed initially with a small working group of members from Open Editions press,
               the French National Archives, and the CNRTL. Some of the ideas presented here were
               also the subject of a poster presented at the TEI's Annual Conference in Rome in
               October 2013. The report in its current shape owes much to the helpful comments
               received from .... ? </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="gloss">
            <head>Glossary</head>
            <list type="gloss">
               <label>TEI</label>
               <item>Text Encoding Initiative: an international membership consortium which manages
                  and maintains a set of recommendations for the encoding of textual and other
                  materials, initially in SGML, and now in XML. The TEI Guidelines are the de facto
                  standard for this kind of work within the arts and humanities research
                  community.</item>
               <label>schema</label>
               <item>a set of rules expressed using a formal language (examples include RELAXNG, W3C
                  Schema, and DTD) which can be used to validate the tagging of an XML
                  document.</item>
               <label>ODD</label>
               <item>("One Document Does it all") a format defined by the TEI which documents the
                  schema applicable to a set of TEI XML documents; also, a document in that
                  format.</item>
               <label>TEI module</label>
               <item>One of the 14 groups of declarations making up the TEI system. Each module
                  contains declarations for a varying number of elements and their attributes. Some
                  modules also declare classes , macros, or datatypes, although the bulk of these
                  infrastructural declarations are collected in a single module called
                     <ident>tei</ident>. </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="bibl">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl>
               <head>Literature on ODD</head>
               <bibl>
                  <note>Specification complète du langage ODD</note><ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html"
                     >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html</ref></bibl>
               <bibl><note>Description du traitement des fichiers ODD</note>
                  <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM"
                     >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM</ref></bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Support/Learn/odds.xml">Getting started with P5
                     ODDs</ref>
                  <note>Article discursif (P5)</note></bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm"
                     >http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm</ref>
                  <note>Introduction tutoriel (P4)</note></bibl>
               <bibl><ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml"
                     >http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml</ref>
                  <note>Introduction tutoriel</note></bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <author>
                     <forename>Lou</forename>
                     <surname>Burnard</surname>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <forename>Sebastian</forename>
                     <surname>Rahtz</surname>
                  </author><title>RelaxNG with Son of ODD</title>
                  <ptr
                     target="http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2004/Burnard01/EML2004Burnard01.html"/>
                  <title level="m">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages 2004</title>
                  <note>Technical description of the new ODD system developed for TEI P5.</note>
               </bibl>
               <bibl><author><forename>James</forename>
                     <surname>Cummings</surname></author>
                  <title level="m">ODDly Pragmatic: Documenting encoding practices in Digital
                     Humanities projects</title><ref
                     target="http://blogs.it.ox.ac.uk/jamesc/2013/09/21/oddly-pragmatic/">[Blog
                     entry summarizing talk given at JADH 2013]</ref>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <listBibl>
               
               <head>Digital Preservation</head>
               
               <bibl><title>CINES Recommandations, liste de formats etc.</title><ref target="http://facile.cines.fr/">FACILE</ref></bibl>
               <bibl>Digital Preservation Coalition <title>Preservation Handbook</title>: <ptr
                     target="http://www.dpconline.org/advice/preservationhandbook"/></bibl>
               <bibl>Hathi Trust <title>Digital Object Specifications (METS and PREMIS)</title>:
                     <ptr target="http://www.hathitrust.org/digital_object_specifications"/>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
