<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TEI as an archival format</title>
            <author>Lou Burnard</author>
            <author>Nicolas Larrousse</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished draft prepared for submission to TEI MM 2013</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Original work created in digital form</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2013-03-30">Complete first draft</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>

      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>We discuss the feasibility of long term archival preservation of digital resources in
               TEI format. As increasing numbers of digital resources are prepared using TEI, it
               becomes likely that their creators will wish to deposit them in that format. The
               digital archival community however has its own acceptability criteria some of which
               may require considerable additional effort for small scale pure TEI projects. We
               report on a pilot project, undertaken in conjunction with the CINES (the French
               National Digital Archive service), which aims to identify the technical requirements
               associated with the goal of long term preservation of TEI corpora. </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>

         <p>The adoption of the TEI as a common storage format for digital resources in the
            Humanities has many consequences for those wishing to interchange, integrate, or process
            such resources. The TEI community is highly divers, but there is a general feeling that
            all of its members share an understanding of the best way to use the TEI Guidelines, and
            that those Guidelines express a common understanding of how text formats should be
            documented and defined. There is also (usually) a general willingness to make resources
            encoded according to the TEI Guidelines available in that format, as well as in whatever
            other publishing or distribution format has been adopted by the project. The question
            arises as whether such TEI-encoded resources are also suitable for long term
            preservation purposes : more specifically, if a project wishes to ensure long term
            preservation of its resources, should it archive them in a TEI format? And if so, what
            other components (schema files, stylesheets, etc.) should accompany the primary resource
            files when submitting them for long term preservation in a digital archive? TEI encoded
            resources typically contain mostly XML-encoded text, possibly with links to files
            expressed using other commonly encountered web formats for graphics or audio; is there
            any advantage to be gained in treating them any differently from any other such XML
            encoded resource? </p>
         <p> This is not an entirely theoretical question : as more and more digitization projects
            seek to go beyond simply archiving digital page images, the quantity of richly encoded
            TEI XML resources representing primary print or manuscript sources continues to
            increase. In France alone, we may cite projects such as the ATILF, OpenEditions, BVH,
            BFM, Obvil and many more for all of which the TEI format is likely to be seen as the
            basic storage format, enabling the project to represent a usefully organised structural
            representation of the texts, either to complement the digital page images, or even to
            replace them for such purposes as the production of open online editions. When such
            resources are deposited in a digital archive, how should the archivist ensure that they
            are valid TEI and will continue to be usable ? One possibility might be to require that
            such resources are first converted to some other commonly recognised display format such
            as PDF or XHTML; and indeed for projects where the TEI form is considered only as a
            means to the end of displaying the texts, this may well be adequate. But since TEI to
            HTML or TEI to PDF are lossy transformations, in which the added value constituted by
            TEI structural annotation is systematically removed this seems to us in general a less
            than desirable solution. We would like to be able to preserve our digital resources
            without loss of information, so as to facilitate future use of that information by means
            of technologies not yet in existence. Such data-independence was, after all, one of the
            promises XML (and before it SGML) offered.</p>
         <p> The data archivist needs to be able to test the coherence and correctness of the
            resources entering the archive, and also to monitor their continued usability. For an
            XML-based format, this is a relatively simple exercise. An XML file must be expressed
            using one of a small number of standard character encodings, and must use a tagging
            system the syntactic rules of which can be written on the back of a not particularly
            large envelope. The algorithm by which an XML document can be shown to be syntactically
            correct, (”well formed”) is expressible within the same scope and producing a piece of
            software able to determe that correctness is consequently equally trivial. The XML
            Recommendation adds a layer of "syntactic validation" to this, according to which the
            use of XML tags within a set of documents can be strictly controlled by means of an
            additional document known  as a schema, defining for example the names of all permitted
            XML elements and attributes, together with contextual rules about their valid
            deployment. Syntactic validation of an XML resource against its schema is also a
            comparatively simple and automatic procedure, rerquiring only access to the schema and
            an appropriate piece of software. (Given the  dominant position enjoyed by  XML as a
            data format, the current wide availability of reliable open-source validators for it
            seems unlikely to change, even in the long term) </p>
         <p>However, the notion of "TEI Conformance" as it is defined in the current Guidelines goes
            considerably beyond the simple notion of syntactic validity. An archivist concerned to
            ensure the coherence and correctness of a new resource at this further level needs
            several additional tools and procedures, and a goal of our project is to determine to
            what extent the goal of ensuring such conformance is quixotic or impractical.  In
            particular, we  will investigate the usefulness of the TEI's ODD documentation format as
            a means of extending the scope of what is possible in this respect when using a
            conventional XML schema language such as RELAX NG or ISO Schematron. </p>
         <p>Our initial recommended approach for ingest of a conformant TEI resource might include :<list>
               <item>syntactic validation of each document against the most appropriate TEI schema;
                  for documents containing textual data this would naturally include TEI All, but
                  also any project-supplied XML schema, and also (for any ODD document supplied) the
                  standard TEI ODD schema;</item>
               <item>creation of a TEI schema from the supplied ODD and validation of the documents
                  against that in order to validate any project-specific constraints such as
                  attribute values; </item>
               <item>comparison of the ODD supplied with an ODD generated automatically from the
                  document set;</item>
               <item>definition and usage of a set of stylesheets to convert the resource into a
                  "lowest common denominator" TEI format</item>
            </list></p>
         <p>Such an approach suggests that the "submission information package" for a TEI resource
            will contain a number of ancillary documents or references to documents, notably to a
            TEI P5-conformant ODD from which a tailored set of syntactic and semantic validators can
            be generated using standard transformations. We hope to report on this and on the
            results of our initial experiments with some major French-language resources at the
            Conference.</p></body>
            
   </text>
</TEI>
