<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <body>
<div n="1">
<head>Presentation on the Occasion of Receiving the ADHO Antonio Zampolli Prize on Behalf of the TEI
Community</head>
<p>NANCY IDE
<lb/>DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTER SCIENCE
<lb/>VASSAR COLLEGE
<lb/>POUGHKEEPSIE, NEW YORK USA</p>
</div>
<div n="2">
<head>Part One: Context and Rationale </head>
<list>
<item>How was the TEI started?</item>
<item>Why was the TEI started?</item>
<item>What problems was it trying to solve?</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="3">
<head>Humanities Computing in the Mid-80s</head>
<list>
<item>Vocabulary, authorship, stylistic studies</item>
<item> Concordance-based:</item>
<item> Words, word patterns, combinations </item>
<item> Basic statistics:</item>
<item> Sorted frequencies of letters, words, phrases</item>
<item> Type-token statistics</item>
<item> Ranking collocates by strength of association </item>
<item> Vocabulary distributions over a text</item>
<item> Etc.</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="4">
<head>Software</head>
<list>
<item>Concordancing, frequency lists, etc.</item>
<item> Oxford Concordance Program (and MicroOCP)</item>
<item> University of Toronto’s Text Analysis Computing Tools (TACT)</item>
<item> WordCruncher</item>
<item> . . . </item>
<item>Input formats varied dramatically!</item>
<item> Differed from program to program, project to project</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="5">
<head>Encoding practices</head>
<list>
<item>Scores of schemes developed in 60s, 70s, 80s for</item>
<item>Representing special characters</item>
<item>Encoding logical divisions of text</item>
<item>Representing analytic or interpretive information</item>
<item>Reducing text critical apparatus to a linear sequence</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="6">
<head>The Problem</head>
<list>
<item>Substantial editing required to use a text encoded for one program or purpose with
another</item>
<item> . . . if even possible</item>
<item>It was a mess!</item>
<item> Or, as one attendee at the Poughkeepsie meeting in 1987 put it, “chaos”</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="7">
<head>Examples</head>
<list>
<item>Citation formats</item>
<item> Include an abbreviated form of a citation reference at the beginning of each line</item>
<!--<eg>VirAen01001arma virumque cano, Troiae qui primus ab oris</eg>
<item>COCOA format</item>
<item> Enclose references in angle brackets, embed in text</item>
<eg>&lt;W Shakespeare&gt;
<lb/>&lt;T Merchant of Venice&gt;
<lb/>&lt;A 2&gt;
<lb/> W = writer
<lb/> &lt;S 6&gt;
<lb/> T = title
<lb/> &lt;C Graziano&gt;
<lb/> A = act
<lb/> This is the penthouse under which Lorenzo
<lb/> S = scene
<lb/> C = speaker
<lb/> . . .
<lb/> L = line number (or program can count if true to text)
<lb/></eg>-->
<item>
<hi>Heavily influenced by hardware and software restrictions of the time </hi>
</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="8">
<head>Early Attempts</head>
<list>
<item>1967</item>
<item> Martin Kay argues for a “standard code in which any text received from an outside source can
be assumed to be”</item>
<item>1970s and early 80s</item>
<item> Discussion of a standard at various meetings of humanities scholars (San Diego 1977, Pisa
1980)</item>
<item> No consensus on how, or even whether, a standard should be developed</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="9">
<head>1986-7</head>
<list>
<item>Still plenty of discussion of need for a standard</item>
<item>1987 ICCH conference </item>
<item> Nancy Ide and Michael Sperberg-McQueen convince U.S. National Endowment for the Humanities
representative <hi>Helen </hi>
<hi>Aguerra </hi>to fund a workshop organized by the <hi>Association for </hi>
<hi>Computers and the Humanities (ACH)</hi>, to bring together the relevant people to determine how
and if such a standard would be possible</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="10">
<head>The Rest is History</head>
<list>
<item>November 11-12, 1987: NEH Workshop at Vassar (Poughkeepsie)</item>
<item>Thirty-two people from around the world attended</item>
<item> Representatives of text archives, humanities computing centers, professional
organizations</item>
<item> Organizations: ACH, ALLC originally</item>
<item> Antonio Zampolli involved Don Walker of the Association for Computational Linguistics
(ACL)</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="11">
<head>
<graphic url="nancy-11_1.jpg"/>
</head>
</div>
<div n="12">
<head>
<graphic url="nancy-12_1.png"/>
</head>
<list>
<item> Glitch in the Plan</item>
<item> Snowstorm in NY on November 11th, 1987</item>
<item>Travel from NY airports to Poughkeepsie very tricky!</item>
<item>Zampolli convinced a van driver to bring a group of participants stranded at JFK Airport to
Poughkeepsie, despite the snow</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="13">
<head>The Workshop</head>
<list>
<item>Two days of intense discussion led to agreement on</item>
<item>Need for common practice</item>
<item>Set of basic principles to guide the development of guidelines for encoding and exchange of
literary and linguistic data</item>
<item>
<hi>The “Poughkeepsie Principles”</hi>
</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="14">
<head>Motivating Background (1)</head>
<list>
<item><hi>Hardware constraints </hi>had a huge impact on encoding choices</item>
<item><hi>Existing software could be difficult </hi>for the non-computer scientist to install and
use</item>
<item>Accompanying <hi>documentation and metadata hard to specify </hi>in a readily available,
consistent way</item>
<item>Notion of <hi>separating prescriptive markup (how it looks) from descriptive </hi>
<hi>markup (what it is) </hi>was brand new (1986)</item>
<item>Specter of the argument that it would be <hi>impossible to define a single </hi>
<hi>standard </hi>that suits everyone </item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="15">
<head>Resulting Principles</head>
<list>
<item>Provide <hi>descriptive </hi>rather than <hi>prescriptive </hi>markup</item>
<item>Provide means for <hi>in-document metadata</hi></item>
<item>Focus on <hi>representing the required/desired </hi>
<hi>information</hi>, not on software requirements</item>
<item>Define a scheme that is <hi>hardware-, software-, and application independent</hi></item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="16">
<head>Resulting Principles</head>
<p>The scheme should <list>
<item> Be <hi>simple, clear, and concrete</hi></item><item> Be <hi>easy for researchers to use
</hi>without special-purpose software</item></list></p>
<p>But at the same time: <list><item> Allow for the <hi>rigorous definition </hi>and <hi>efficient
processing </hi> of texts</item></list></p>
</div>
<div n="17">
<head>Motivating Background (2)</head>
<list>
<item>The Poughkeepsie Principles everywhere reflect concern of archive representatives:</item>
<item>
<hi>Requirement for retrospective conversion </hi>of existing encoded texts</item>
<item>
<hi>Loss of investment </hi>in local expertise, software, and systems</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="18">
<head>Resulting Principle</head>
<p>The guidelines are intended to <hi>suggest</hi> principles for the encoding of texts in the
format </p>
<p>
<hi>Guidelines, not a standard!</hi>
</p>
</div>
<div n="19">
<head>Resulting Principle</head>
<list>
<item>The guidelines are intended to provide a standard format for <hi>data interchange </hi>in
humanities research</item>
<item> No requirement for conformance locally</item>
<item> TEI scheme will serve as a “pivot” format</item>
<item> Only transduction of local format to and from TEI scheme (vs. <hi rend="it">n</hi>-way
transduction among schemes)</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="20">
<head>Resulting Principle</head>
<list>
<item>The guidelines should define a <hi>recommended </hi>syntax for the format</item>
<item>No final decision in Poughkeepsie on the exact syntax</item>
<item> SGML was promoted by many, but not unanimously accepted</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="21">
<head>Resulting Principle</head>
<list>
<item>The guidelines should include a <hi>minimall</hi>set of conventions for encoding new texts in
the format</item>
<item>
<hi>No requirements </hi>will be made for the addition of information not already coded in the texts </item>
<item> Newly-encoded texts should include <hi>descriptive and bibliographic </hi>
<hi>information</hi>, and <hi>information about the encoding itself</hi></item>
<item> A <hi>recommendation</hi></item>
<item> Include means to <hi>extend </hi>the scheme</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="22">
<head>The Single Unfulfilled Principle</head>
<list>
<item>The TEI project originally intended to <hi>define a metalanguage for the description of
text-encoding schemes</hi>, and describe the new format and representative existing schemes in that
metalanguage</item>
<item> Abandoned this goal because</item>
<item> Anxiety over translation of existing schemes subsided as TEI took shape</item>
<item> SGML gained far wider acceptance after the Vassar meeting</item>
<item> Volume of new texts being encoded shifted the balance of concern away from converting legacy
data</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="23">
<head>Other Principles</head>
<list>
<item>
<hi>Polytheoricity</hi>
</item>
<item> Little (or no) unanimity concerning relevant features to encode</item>
<item> Balancing act:</item>
<item>
<hi>Preserve intellectual autonomy </hi>of researchers, but at the same time provide enough guidance
to <hi>avoid pointless variations </hi>in encoding </item>
<item> Solution:</item>
<item> Specific DTD, but also <hi>alternative means to encode the same thing </hi>when felt
necessary</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="24">
<head>Management</head>
<list>
<item>Entrusted to a <hi>Steering Committee </hi>with representatives of three supporting
bodies:</item>
<item> Association for Computers and the Humanities (ACH), </item>
<item> Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing (ALLC)</item>
<item> Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)</item>
<item> This group raised over a million dollars in North America and Europe to support the work of
TEI</item>
<item> Oversaw the development of the TEI Guidelines until 1996</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="25">
<head>Why Success This Time?</head>
<list>
<item><hi>More known about encoding problems </hi>and basic principles than in the past</item>
<item>Included a <hi>more robust representation </hi>of key organizations and active research
centers </item>
<item>Recent <hi>development of SGML </hi>provided the right tool for a simple, flexible, and
extensible encoding scheme</item>
</list>
</div>
<div n="26">
<head>Reflection</head>
<list>
<item>The size, scope, and influence of the TEI far exceeded what anyone at the Vassar meeting
envisaged</item>
<item>In retrospect, it is amazing to see how many foundational issues were addressed by the
TEI</item>
<item>TEI as a “pivot” (interchange) format</item>
<item>Problem of polytheoreticity</item>
<item>Adherence to existing standards where possible</item>
<item>Requirement to include bibliographic information and description of encoding scheme</item></list>
<p rend="box">Many of these issues still operative in efforts to develop text representation standards</p>

</div>
<div n="27">
<head>(Over to you, Michael)</head>
<p/>
</div>
</body>

  </text>
</TEI>
